←→

导言：

拉康第二次回到弗洛伊德

不要期待在我的话语里找到比“我不自诩有解决方案”更具颠覆性的东西。

雅克·拉康《精神分析的另一面》

英卡尔·马克思只是雅克·拉康教学中提到的众多理论家之一。其他经典思想家（尤其是柏拉图、笛卡尔和黑格尔）似乎给他的作品留下了更深的影响。在那么多对拉康颇具影响力的思想家中，我们为何偏偏要推崇马克思？难道想让拉康成为弗洛伊德-马克思主义中的又一位代表吗？（这一主义的努力早已失败，其试图通过将欲望解放为激进政治奠定基础）。还是说，这么做（偏爱马克思的理论）的目的仅仅是将拉康塑造为左翼思想家？

英这样的尝试，不出所料，很快就被大量有关拉康政治倾向的传记琐事和或多或少值得信服的轶事所反驳。这些材料说明，拉康倾向于戴高乐的保守主义[1]。我们也应当提及到他那臭名昭著的对待20世纪60年代末期学生和工人起义模糊不清的态度：当让-保罗·萨特、米歇尔·福柯、吉尔·德勒兹、菲利克斯·瓜塔利以及许多其他著名人物强烈认同共产主义革命愿景时，拉康却反对这些知识分子的思潮并自称为自由主义者。不仅如此，他还将学生们描述为要求一个新的主人的癔症者，并将“革命”的政治定义简化为天文学意义上的圆周运动[2]。他认为学生的要求只是表明了资本主义向“知识市场”的转变，或者说是为了召回如今听起来早就过时的说法——“知识社会”[3]。所有这些有意引起争议的言论使得拉康更像一个新哲学家派的[4]先驱，而非革命性的思想家。

英除了这些小插曲，在众多否认拉康与马克思观念一致的思想家中，拉康本人身先士卒。拉康认为自己的教学中最具颠覆性的方面体现在他不自诩有解决社会矛盾的方案。的确，拉康派精神分析学家经常在讨论政治问题时有所克制，这种奇怪的疏离会经常滑向犬儒主义[5]，而同时他们还试图在拉康对革命运动模棱两可的言论中为自己寻求合法性。因此就有了这样一个不可避免的问题：如果精神分析一再地表现为一种诡辩术，使左翼政治斗争的范围相对主义化，还质疑左翼对资本主义剥削形式的反抗，那么为什么仍然为精神分析延续至今的政治相关性作辩护呢？为什么我们还要将拉康的结构主义精神分析与马克思对政治经济学的批判联系在一起？毕竟，马克思提供了一套话语范式，声称能够给出解决方案（就这一点，无论是马克思的支持者还是反对者都很难不承认，其范式的确提供过解决方案）。

英拉康的教学通常与其著名的口号“回到弗洛伊德”联系在一起。在接下来的内容里，我将讨论拉康在20世纪60年代后期发起的第二次回到弗洛伊德运动，这场运动中，对结构主义语言学的参考（特别是索绪尔和雅各布森）补充了马克思的政治经济学批判。这样的发展趋势必然造成结构主义研究过程的激进化，以及对左翼和右翼的刻板印象的否定——这刻板印象形成于马克思和弗洛伊德以及他们的方法、概念和目标中。一些左翼人士可能会声称精神分析仅在资本主义框架下才能蓬勃发展，甚至觉得精神分析只不过是随着历史被发明出来的阶级疗法，只为资产阶级的心理健康服务。[6]这类批判很容易从福柯、德勒兹和瓜塔利那里找到理论支撑。尽管这三个人的哲学存在分歧，但他们都试图表明，有几种精神分析流派正积极促进欲望的规范化，进而公然地再生产资本主义统治秩序。德勒兹和瓜塔利坚持认为，欲望的神经症化，以及将心理冲突简化为“父亲-母亲-孩子”的俄狄浦斯三角结构，是典型的意识形态操作，其目的就是在资本主义-父权制秩序中维持欲望。[7]我们不得不承认，拉康也在不停地反驳这些指责，他揭示了俄狄浦斯情结在弗洛伊德理论中的神话地位并推翻了臭名昭著的关于阳具至上论——批评者们不停地将该理论矮化至解剖学意义来持续炮制着弗洛伊德主义的庸俗化版本。而这与弗洛伊德和拉康的精神分析的认识论的复杂性没有任何关系。

英同样也存在着自由市场意识形态者、认知行为治疗师和神经科学家的声音。他们很快认识到，精神分析是一种既耗时又费钱的做法，无法为社会（即市场的需求）提供其所需的：适应力强的、灵活的劳动力。因此，一方面，对左派来说，精神分析对社会只是起到规范化的作用，再无其他；而另一方面，对新自由主义者来说，精神分析的规范化程度是远远不够的，因而应该被抛弃。与上述两种路径相反，本书的指导原则是，精神分析仍然保留了症结点，无论是从认识论的还是政治的维度，精神分析都为对资本主义主体性的生产提供了不一样的批判性洞见。

英马克思的思想成果经常被人们评价为既是乌托邦的，又是灾难性的。人们说，马克思几乎创作了一部福音书，它试图瓦解资本主义的生产方式，预示一切社会矛盾的消除。人们经常会遇到这样一种观念：马克思呼吁建立无中介的、本真的人类关系，即《资本论》中提到的自由人的联合，却并未对此进行解释；马克思还呼吁消除所有主体和社会异化的可能变体。这正是人文主义马克思主义者和精神分析学家（以弗洛伊德为首）眼中的马克思的批判工作。[8]然而，我们当然可以说，马克思从未打算创制一个共产主义世界观，对未来社会秩序的推测也并不属于成熟的批判性成果。除此之外，《资本论》明确驳斥了对“关于费尔巴哈的提纲第十一条”[9]的传统解读，即理论和实践、解释和革命性变革的对立。

英马克思的批判工作反复表明，从解释到政治行动的过渡包含一个转变，即从哲学、政治和宗教世界观的生产——如弗洛伊德后来嘲讽的那样，这些人花时间于其上以填补现实的缺口——到唯物主义解释的转变。后者完全相反，它揭示现行世界观想要掩盖的缺口。[10]通过发现这些结构性缺口，唯物主义方法给出了对于支撑资本主义社会联结的逻辑关系的严谨理解，从而也发现了能使人们解决变革问题的结构性披露。正是在这一点上，拉康介入了关于马克思认识论和政治坐标的争论，提出了一种结构主义解读，这意味着一个更不正统但同样具有政治激进性的马克思。

英精神分析既不是福音书也不是世界观。拉康解读马克思的出发点是，政治经济学批判不应被视为书写共产主义历史必然性的史诗，也不应被当做将活的劳动从资本的吸血中解放出来的生机论尝试。马克思“资本幽灵般的否定性”VS“活生生的劳动的创造性潜力”的哥特式隐喻是误导性的。还记得吗，政治经济学批判始于对价值的考察，其中包含严密的逻辑；它甚至可以被认为是《资本论》中最黑格尔主义的部分，是一种相当于《逻辑学》的、凝缩了的马克思主义。对价值形式的分析表明，马克思认为革命潜力并不蕴藏在某种特定意识（即工人阶级的意识）中，而是在结构性的否定性——劳动力中，其占据着资本主义生产方式的（各种）矛盾相互汇聚的位置。同时，资本的出现与“能生钱的钱”的生机论相关联，精神分析在这种幻想当中帮助我们辨别出对“没有否定性的主体”的虚构假设。当马克思将作为主体的否定性重新引入纯粹生机论和资本主义自动的机械性时（这种机械性表现在被假设能“生生无穷”或“产金蛋”的力量中[11]。），他成熟的批判工程最无争议地与精神分析相交汇了。因此，马克思不断地在两个不同但密切相关的层面上运动：首先从生产的逻辑出发，解释了价值之间的抽象过程和看似中立的关系是如何支撑并再生产具体的社会对抗的。其次从幻想的逻辑出发，审视了客观表象的再生产，其压抑、扭曲和神秘化了现存的结构矛盾。生产的逻辑和幻想的逻辑是马克思批判观念的两个基本组成部分。

英只有通过重新引入资本主义同时产生和遮蔽的否定性——没有劳动力作为价值来源就没有资本主义生产方式，但没有对劳动力的遮蔽也就没有资本主义恋物癖——才能使批判工程成功揭示出那些对思考社会变革和新的主体性（其不再依赖价值形式的抽象普遍性）的生产来说十分必要的逻辑悖论。这意味着，马克思在资本主义生产方式的总体结构中对劳动力的定位揭示了主体的理论。对于拉康而言，这种主体化了的否定性的（逻辑的乃至同源的）答案就是无意识主体。因此，马克思在《资本论》中的主要努力——分析资本主义的结构性僵局，必然伴随着对主体的新的去心理化和去个体化的理解。马克思从这两个特征出发（正如阿尔都塞所主张的[12]），拒绝对主体的人道主义式的和认知的理解。他将这两者区分开：一是仍深植于认知经验主义理论和各种本质上唯心主义的世界观中的主体性；二是隐含在交换价值的自动性[13]中的主体。唯物主义的主体理论摒弃了经验主义和唯心主义，后两者共同努力将主体性简化为意识。

英马克思批判的基础之一正是价值的自动性，它在每一个不假思索的交换行为中发挥着作用。当马克思从使用价值和交换价值之间的分裂（这决定了商品的双重性）出发时，他实际上预见了结构主义的主要成就：差异体系的独立性。而且，这种自动性被设想为某种能够破坏甚至有废除资本主义潜力的变革之发源地。生产方式的变革归根结底是发生在生产的组织中的结构性错位。主体的概念在这个精确的语境中找到了它的位置。马克思的批判非但没有将这个主体仅当做资产阶级范畴而摒弃，还提供了必要的工具来区分主体的（经济、政治、司法和认知）虚构和真正的政治主体。如果说前者是抽象物，后者是否定性，那么抽象物和否定性之间的张力是唯物主义主体理论的核心。马克思主义的教益在这里是完全明确的：认知主体（包括卢卡奇的阶级意识的概念）不可能是政治的主体。相反，唯物主义批判的政治主体只能是去中心化、去个体化和去心理化的。在此，拉康强调了政治经济学批判在认识论和政治领域的颠覆性潜力，声称正是马克思发明了症状的概念。

英马克思是第一位研究症状的理论家，这意味着无产阶级是无意识主体——无产阶级指的不仅仅是一个经验主义的社会阶级，它表达了资本主义下普遍的主体处境。但是，作为症状——一种将现有社会秩序被压抑的真相重新铭刻在政治空间的形式，无产阶级使得对资本主义强加的虚伪和抽象的普遍主义（即商品形式的普遍主义）的摒弃成为必要。无产阶级被单纯视作经验主体到被视作无意识主体，随着这一转变的发生，阶级斗争的概念和现实也以不同的方式显现。它不再仅仅是实际存在的社会阶级间的冲突，而是社会现实与主体现实中结构性矛盾的显现，从而承担着与无意识相同的认识论-政治地位。无论是阶级斗争还是无意识，都不能代表某种不变的超历史本质——它们的全部“一致性”在于现存秩序再生产时伴随着的表象的扭曲。

英马克思和拉康反对将否定性与肯定性、死的与活的劳动、抽象结构与具体经验、结构与起源等概念简单对立。弗洛伊德-马克思主义和其他试图解放无意识欲望以及活的劳动的创造性潜力的失败表明：资本就是创造性潜力，资本就是生命，资本主义就是特定的生机论形式。当然，这并不意味着每一种生机论都理应被指责为资本的生机论。这只是试图质疑“糟糕的”否定性、异化和存在的匮乏，与“美好的”肯定性、创造性潜力和存在的完满之间过于轻易的对立。资本的动力学和适应性——其赋魅、扭曲和压抑主体的和社会的反抗，同化症状的和颠覆性的个性之能力——充分表明了资本可以被理解为没有否定性的生命，更准确的说，资本主义的效率和逻辑恰恰是由对这种生活、主体性和社会的幻想支撑的。关于这种生机论的幻想，马克思在《资本论》整本书对拜物教的批判不仅仅是哲学式好奇，因为它恰恰针对关于这三个资本主义抽象概念的内在创造性假设：商品、货币和资本。对拜物教的批判是对作为自发的资本主义哲学的生机论的批判。[14]如果我们回想一下马克思所列举的经济自由主义的四个基本概念——自由、平等、财产和“边沁”（私人利益）——我们就会再次遇到没有否定性的主体性和社会的幻想，尤其没有阶级斗争，这个马克思主义对跨越社会和主体的否定性的最重要称呼。

英弗洛伊德-马克思主义最显著的代表——威廉海姆·赖希和赫伯特·马尔库塞似乎也落入了类似的生机论陷阱。在他们各自的作品中，他们采取了驱力和文化的对立，这与弗洛伊德晚期快乐原则和死亡冲动的二分相呼应。根据弗洛伊德的文化著作，他们声称性是解放斗争的特殊领域，将它的创造性生机、“各式各样的倒错”与文化趋势、规范化（特别是作为资本主义规范化之代理者的商品形式）相对立。[15]如此一来，弗洛伊德-马克思主义相当于米歇尔·福柯所严正批判的性压抑假说，[16]这种假说甚至吸引了德勒兹和瓜塔利，在他们对精神分析的批判中可见一斑。弗洛伊德-马克思主义与精神分裂分析的最小公约数就在于此：资本主义的效率根植于对性的压抑、驱力的抑制和欲望的神经症化。社会压迫等同于精神结构的压抑，阶级矛盾变成了精神冲突的外部形式，而性能量被引导到资本主义生产模式下的压抑机制中，并遭受异化（阉割和商品化）。此时我们应该回想起，弗洛伊德-马克思主义的阐释主要集中在弗洛伊德的第二个话题（本我，自我，超我），在其中一种对无意识可疑的实体化——其通过推理的生理性隐喻、系统发生学幻想，尤其是“精神装置的能量模型”——表明了精神分析的一个更生机论版本的可能性。[17]

英既然弗洛伊德-马克思主义者将政治建基于思想的性解放的尝试遭遇了失败，拉康坚决反对将精神分析文本直接转译成马克思主义文本也就不足为奇了。相反，他强调了二者在逻辑上的密切关系，因此他迈出了退回到精神分析和政治经济学批判的共同认识论基础的必要一步。通过强调逻辑，拉康也将这种论调相对化了：期望马克思主义和精神分析含有一个实证的知识语料库，而这可能会导向一种新的政治世界观愿景。

英马克思《资本论》中的辩证法充分表明，批判的革命性质不在于某种世界观的承诺，而在于它的方法，在于分析维持商品形式表面上的普遍性和资本主义抽象概念幻想充盈的生机论的结构关系。如果马克思的政治计划确实包含“共产主义假说”[18]，那么这个“假说”应与牛顿的“我不做假说”相提并论。为什么？因为共产主义的假说以有关价值的唯物主义科学为基础，当然不与政治经济学的伪科学假说为伍，其包括：资本生命力所在的拜物教假说，关于市场稳态和自我调节特性的自由主义假说（亚当·斯密的“看不见的手”），以及资本主义社会关系的假说——建立于抽象的自由和平等，并辅以财产和私人利益。共产主义假说承担了不同的地位，它被铭刻在科学现代性的认识论视域中——马克思努力将他关于价值的科学和批判方法建基于其上。这种铭刻可以用唯物辩证法切入社会现实的方式来论证。它揭示了现有社会表象的内在断裂，因此重复了现代科学使用数学工具来把握物理现象的实在的方法。[19]辩证唯物主义的方法遵循现代认识论理想，辨别结构性的实在，也就是马克思在《资本论》中的核心假说：不存在所谓的社会关系。[20]或者如《共产党宣言》所说：“迄今为止，所有现存社会的历史都是阶级斗争的历史”，这首先意味着元历史并不存在。阶级斗争的多元性揭示了历史的去中心化，正如同无意识揭示了思维的去中心化。《资本论》还包含一种批判的认识论，这种认识论对将科学方法和知识运用于以下领域提出质疑：劳动力的历史转型、资本主义社会抽象物的起源、社会关系的两个否定性形象（劳动力和剩余价值）的引入。正是在这些论域中，拉康认出他的能指主体和客体小a。

英弗洛伊德将现代科学革命总结为对人类自恋的三大冒犯，伴随着三种科学的去中心化：关于宇宙（哥白尼，更恰当的说是牛顿）、关于生命（达尔文/华莱士），最后是关于思维（弗洛伊德）。因此，他毋庸置疑地指出，无意识（一种否定性的明确表现，一种没有认知主体的知识形式，以及一种实在话语的结果）的发现只有在现代科学的视域中才成为可能。更准确地说，弗洛伊德的无意识理论只有在现代科学革命的成果已经应用到人类的生产领域时才成为可能——简而言之，在马克思的认识论断裂之后，它才成为可能（阿尔都塞语）。

英科学革命作为使我们能思考否定性在社会关联中的功能和位置的一个环节，成为马克思与弗洛伊德的结构主义结合的基础，这一结合已在阿尔都塞那里出现，他无疑激发了拉康对政治经济学批判的兴趣。阿尔都塞是第一个系统地将马克思与结构主义计划联系起来的人。他坚持认为，马克思和弗洛伊德通过思考历史和思想中的否定性，颠覆了科学的概念。阿尔都塞将精神分析和政治经济学批判描述为“冲突性的科学”。[21]它们的对抗性特征来自于：二者都从对社会和主体领域的“否定性的坚持”出发，而非从对否定性的排除出发 [22]。从这个角度来看，异化同样是主体和社会的构成因素，是一个不再仅意味着匮乏，更是意味着转变的环节。在拉康对马克思的解读中，一个要点是试图通过重新解释异化的概念，来克服生机论式的肯定性和辩证法的否定性之间的对立。

英重申，这本书从这样的假设出发——对马克思的引用意味着拉康教学中的一个重要发展，开创了第二次“回到弗洛伊德”，其将重心从结构语言学转向政治经济学批判，从主体的表征转向原乐的生产。原乐（享乐，或弗洛伊德所说的力比多）因此作为精神分析的核心问题再次出现；弗洛伊德早已这么做了，但随着精神分析逐渐服从经济自由主义的理想和要求——在其中个体适应和重新融入现存社会秩序成为分析治疗的主要目标——它被系统地忽视了。原乐不仅提供了弗洛伊德理论政治重要性的特殊切入点，也揭示了经典结构主义的局限：去思考由能指自动性所产生的主体和客体。

英回想一下，弗洛伊德对无意识的发现主要强调了劳动（Arbeit）在满足无意识倾向（欲望或驱力）方面的作用，以及它不断地揭示了无意识的生产维度。此处被提及的劳动应该从字面上看。通过将劳动力这个富有能量的概念置于他的发现的核心，弗洛伊德概述了无意识的劳动理论。[23]拉康在1960年代后期的主要兴趣是围绕着弗洛伊德理论的这个重要方面发展的。在原乐的概念中，拉康将弗洛伊德的“精神能量”（力比多）和无意识劳动的概念结合在一起。为了充分确证弗洛伊德之发现的革命性，需要关于生产的理论。这是索绪尔的结构主义无法提供的，但是马克思做到了。

←→

Introduction:

Lacan's Second Return to Freud

Don't expect anything more subversive in my discourse than that I do not claim to have a solution.

Jacques Lacan, The Other Side of Psychoanalysis

中Karl Marx is just one of the many theorists referred to in Jacques Lacan's teachings. Other classic thinkers seem to have left a much deeper mark on his work, notably Plato, Descartes and Hegel. Why then, among such an abundance of influences, should one privilege Marx? Is it in order to make Lacan yet another representative of the Freudo-Marxist orientation, a tradition marked by a rather failed endeavour to ground radical politics on the liberation of desire? Or is the aim simply to turn Lacan into a leftist thinker?

中Such an attempt is, of course, immediately countered by a wealth of biographical trivia and more or less trustworthy anecdotes regarding Lacan's political preferences, which, it is said, inclined towards Charles de Gaulle's conservatism. We should also mention his notoriously ambiguous reaction to the student and worker uprisings in the late 1960s. While figures such as Jean-Paul Sartre, Michel Foucault, Gilles Deleuze, Felix Guattari and many others of comparable stature strongly identified with the promise of a communist revolution, Lacan went against the intellectual current and labelled himself a liberal. Moreover, he portrayed the students as hysterics who demanded a new master; he reduced the political definition of revolution to its astronomical meaning of circular movement and finally argued that the student demands were merely manifesting the transformation of capitalism into a 'market of knowledge' or, to recall the formula that may today already sound anachronistic, 'knowledge society'. All these consciously controversial statements make Lacan appear more like a predecessor of the nouveaux philosophes than a revolutionary thinker.

中In addition to these episodes, the various reservations against reading Lacan as a thinker whose ideas were consonant with Marx's were best taken up by the man himself. He saw the most subversive aspect of his teaching in the fact that he did not pretend to have a solution for social antagonisms. Indeed, among Lacanian psychoanalysts, one often encounters a restraint in discussing political matters, a peculiar distance that often drifts into cynicism and seeks legitimacy in Lacan's ambiguous remarks on revolutionary movements. Hence the inevitable question: if psychoanalysis recurrently appears as a form of sophistry that relativises the scope of leftist political struggles and questions their resistance to capitalist forms of exploitation, then why argue for its continued political relevance? Why associate Lacan's structural psychoanalysis with Marx's critique of political economy, which provides, and on this point at least both its supporters and opponents agree, the paradigmatic case of a discourse that claims to have a solution?

中Lacan's teaching is generally associated with its famous motto of a 'return to Freud'. In the following pages I argue that in the late 1960s Lacan initiated a second return to Freud, in which the reference to structural linguistics (particularly Saussure and Jakobson) was supplemented with Marx's critique of political economy. This development inevitably led to a radicalisation of the structuralist research programme and also a rejection of the stereotypes that public opinion, on the Left as well as on the Right, formed about Marx and Freud and their methods, concepts and goals. Some leftist voices would probably claim that psychoanalysis prospers only in the capitalist universe and even that it was historically invented to be nothing more than a class-therapy, serving the mental well-being of the bourgeoisie. Such critiques could easily find theoretical support in Foucault, Deleuze and Guattari, who, despite their philosophical differences, strived to show that several psychoanalytic currents actively contribute to the normalisation of desire and thereby openly reproduce capitalist forms of domination. Neurotisation of desire, reduction of psychic conflicts to the Oedipal triangle of Father-Mother-Child, as Deleuze and Guattari have insisted, is the paradigmatic case of an ideological operation that maintains desire in the capitalist-patriarchal order. We nevertheless have to acknowledge that Lacan insistently countered these criticisms, for instance by demonstrating the mythical status of the Oedipus complex in Freuds theories and by dethroning the infamous primacy of the phallus which the critiques of Freud continue to reduce to its anatomical signification, thereby reproducing the vulgarised version of Freudianism, which has barely anything in common with the epistemic complexity of Freudian and Lacanian psychoanalysis.

中There are also the voices of free-market ideologists, cognitive-behavioural therapists and neuroscientists, who immediately recognise in psychoanalysis a time- and money-consuming practice, incapable of providing society, that is, the demands of the market, with what it requires: an adaptable and flexible workforce. So while for the leftists all psychoanalysis does is normalise, for neoliberals it never normalises enough and should therefore be abolished. In opposition to these two options, the guideline of the present book will be that psychoanalysis remains a symptomatic point, both epistemologically and politically speaking, that offers a particular critical insight into the production of capitalist subjectivity.

中As for Marx, his work is often criticized as being at once utopian and disastrous. Marx is said to have composed something equivalent to a gospel that, in its endeavour to dissolve the capitalist mode of production, also promises the abolition of all forms of social antagonism. One often encounters the notion that Marx called for unmediated and authentic human relations, the association of free men mentioned in Capital but left unexplained, and hence for the elimination of all possible variants of subjective and social alienation. This is how both humanist Marxists and psychoanalysts(first and foremost Freud) perceived Marx's critical project. That said, we could certainly claim that Marx never intended to elaborate a communist worldview and that speculation about the future social order did not belong in his mature critical work. In addition to this, Capital openly refutes the conventional reading of the 11th thesis on Feuerbach, the opposition of theory and practice, interpretation and revolutionary change.

中Marx's critical project repeatedly shows that the passage from interpretation to political action involves a move from the production of philosophical, political and religious worldviews-which, as Freud would later mockingly claim, spend their time filling in the gaps of reality -to a materialist interpretation that, in quite the opposite fashion, uncovers the very gaps that existing worldviews strive to foreclose.By detecting these structural gaps, the materialist method provides a rigorous understanding of logical relations that support the capitalist social link, thereby also detecting the structural disclosure that enables one to address the question of change. It is precisely at this point that Lacan intervenes in the debates regarding Marx's epistemological and political coordinates, proposing a structuralist reading that implies a much more unorthodox, albeit no less politically radical, Marx.

中Psychoanalysis is neither gospel nor worldview, and the departure for Lacan's reading of Marx is that his critique of political economy should not be treated as an epic tale of the historic necessity of communism either. Nor is it a vitalist attempt to liberate living labour from the vampirism of capital. Marx's gothic metaphor of the ghostly negativity of capital versus the creative potential of living labour is misleading. Recall that the critique of political economy begins with an examination of value, containing a rigorous logic; it could even be considered the most Hegelian part of Capital, a condensed Marxian equivalent to the Science of Logic. The analysis of the value-form indicates that Marx locates the revolutionary potential not so much in a specific consciousness, that of the working class, but in a structural negativity, labour-power, which occupies the place where the contradictions of the capitalist mode of production are brought together. At the same time, the appearance of capital is associated with a vitalist fantasy, 'money-breeding money', in which psychoanalysis helps us to discern the fictional hypothesis of a subject without negativity. Marx's mature critical project most incontestably intersects with psychoanalysis at the point when it reintroduces negativity qua subject into what appears as the purely vitalist and autonomous machinery of capital, expressed in its presumed power to 'bring forth living offspring' or to 'lay golden eggs'. Marx thus continuously moves on two different but intimately related levels, that of the logic of production, which explains how the abstract and seemingly neutral relations between values support and reproduce concrete social antagonisms, and that of the logic of fantasy, which examines the reproduction of objective appearances, whose function is to repress, distort and mystify the existing structural contradictions. The logic of production and the logic of fantasy are the two basic components of Marx's notion of critique.

中Only by reintroducing the negativity that capitalism simultaneously produces and forecloses -there is no capitalist mode of production without labour-power as a source of value, but there is also no capitalist fetishisation of social relations without the foreclosure of labour-power-can the critical project succeed in uncovering the logical paradoxes that are the necessary precondition for thinking social change and for the production of a new subjectivity that no longer depends on the abstract universality of the value-form. This means, then, that Marx's localisation of labour-power in the general structure of the capitalist mode of production unfolds a theory of the subject. For Lacan the logical, and even homological, response to this subjectivised negativity is the subject of the unconscious. The analysis of the structural deadlocks of capitalism, Marx's central effort in Capital, is thus necessarily accompanied by a new-de-psychologised and de-individualised -understanding of the subject. With these two features Marx, as Althusser has insisted, rejected the humanist and the cognitive comprehension of the subject, distinguishing between subjectivity that is still embedded in the empiricist theories of cognition and in various, essentially idealist worldviews, on the one hand, and the subject that is implied by the autonomy of exchange value, on the other. A materialist theory of the subject rejects both empiricism and idealism, which come together in their efforts to reduce subjectivity to consciousness.

中One of the foundations of Marx's critique is precisely the autonomy of value, which operates in every innocent act of exchange. When Marx departs from the gap between the use-value and the exchange-value that determines the double character of commodities - he in fact anticipates the main achievement of structuralism: the isolation of the system of differences. Furthermore, this autonomy is envisaged as the terrain where the change that would destabilise and potentially abolish capitalism needs to be thought. The change of the mode of production is in the last instance a structural displacement in the organisation of production. The notion of the subject finds its place in this precise context. Far from rejecting it as a mere bourgeois category, Marx's critique of the subject provides the necessary tools to differentiate between the (economic, political, juridical and cognitive) fiction of the subject and the real subject of politics. If the former is criticised as abstraction, the latter is revealed as negativity, so that the tension between abstraction and negativity is the kernel of a materialist theory of the subject. The Marxian lesson is here entirely univocal: the subject of cognition (including Lukacs's notion of class-consciousness) cannot be the subject of politics. On the contrary, the subject of politics that a materialist critique can only be decentralised, de-individualised and de-psychologised. Lacan enters at this point by stressing the epistemologically and politically subversive potential of the critique of political economy in the claim that it was none other than Marx who invented the notion of the symptom.

中That Marx was the first theoretician of the symptom implies that the proletariat is the subject of the unconscious. This means that the proletariat designates more than an empirical social class. It expresses the universal subjective position in capitalism. But as a symptom, that is, as a formation through which the repressed truth of the existing social order is reinscribed in the political space, the proletariat entails a rejection of the false and abstract universalism imposed by capitalism, namely the universalism of commodity form. With the shift from the proletarian seen simply as an empirical subject to the subject of the unconscious, the notion and the reality of class struggle also appears in a different light. It no longer signifies merely a conflict of actually existing social classes but the manifestation of structural contradictions in social and subjective reality, thereby assuming the same epistemological-political status as the unconscious. Neither class struggle nor the unconscious stands for some invariable transhistorical essences -their entire ‘consistency' lies in the distortion of appearances that accompany the reproduction of the given order.

中Marx and Lacan reject the simple opposition between negativity and positivity, dead and living labour, abstract structure and concrete experience, structure and genesis. The failure of Freudo-Marxism and other attempts to free the creative potential of unconscious desire and of living labour suggests the conclusion that capital is creative potential, that capital is Life, and that capitalism is a specific form of vitalism. Of course, this does not imply that every vitalism should be denounced as being, in the last instance, a vitalism of capital. It merely strives to problematise the simple and all too comfortable opposition of the 'bad' negativity, alienation and lack of being, on the one hand, and the 'good' positivity, creative potential and fullness of being, on the other. The dynamics and adaptability of capital -its capacity to mystify, distort and repress subjective and social antagonisms, assimilating symptomatic or subversive identities and so on -sufficiently indicates that capital should be understood as life without negativity, or more precisely, that the efficiency and the logic of capitalism is supported by a fantasy of such life, subjectivity and society. With regard to this vitalist fantasy, Marx's critique of fetishism turns out to be more than a mere philosophical curiosity in the entirety of Capital, since it targets precisely the hypothesis of the inherent creative potential of the three central capitalist abstractions: commodity, money and capital. The critique of fetishism is the critique of capitalist vitalism as a spontaneous capitalist philosophy. If we recall Marx's enumeration of the four fundamental concepts of economic liberalism -freedom, equality, property and Bentham'(private interest)-we again encounter the fantasy of a subjectivity and society without negativity, notably without class struggle, this principal Marxian name for the negativity that traverses society and the subject.

中Freudo-Marxism's most visible representatives, Wilhelm Reich and Herbert Marcuse, seem to have walked into a similar vitalist trap. In their respective readings, they adopted the opposition between drives and culture that echoes in Freud's late dichotomy of Eros and Thanatos. Based on Freuds cultural writings, they declared sexuality the privileged terrain of emancipatory struggle and opposed its creative vitality, its 'polymorphous perversion' to the cultural tendencies, to normalisation and notably to the commodity form as the general agency of capitalist normalisation. Freudo-Marxism thus amounted to what Michel Foucault rightly criticised as the repressive hypothesis, a hypothesis that seduced even Deleuze and Guattari in their critique of psychoanalysis. The minimal common ground between Freudo-Marxism and schizo-analysis could be seen in the idea that the efficiency of capitalism is rooted in the repression of sexuality, the inhibition of drives and the neurotisation of desire. Social oppression is equated with psychic mechanisms of repression, the class conflict becomes an external form of psychic conflict, while libidinal energy is channelled into the restrictive mechanisms of the capitalist mode of production and subjected to alienation (castration and commodification). Here we should recall that Freudo-Marxist interpretations focused predominantly on Freud's second topic'(id, ego, superego), in which a problematic substantialisation of the unconscious, by means of rather speculative biological metaphors, phylogenetic fantasies, and most importantly by the energetic model of the psychic apparatus, indicate the possibility of a more vitalist version of psychoanalysis.

中With the failure of the Freudo-Marxist attempt to ground politics on sexual liberation in mind, it is not surprising that Lacan decidedly rejected direct translations of psychoanalytic contents into Marxist contents. He instead accentuated their logical affinity, thereby taleing a necessary step back to the common epistemological ground of psychoanalysis and the critique of political economy. By placing the accent on logic, Lacan also relativised the expectation that Marxism and psychoanalysis contain a corpus of positive knowledge that could potentially lead to a new political worldview.

中The dialectics of Marx's Capital sufficiently shows that the revolutionary character of critique is not in the promise of such a worldview but in its method, in the analysis of structural relations that sustain the apparent universality of commodity form and the fantasmatic vitalism of capitalist abstractions. And if Marx's political project indeed contains a ‘communist hypothesis’, then the term 'hypothesis' should be read in pair with Newton's hypothesis non fingo. Why? Because the communist hypothesis, grounded on a materialist science of value, most certainly does not assume the same status as the pseudoscientific hypotheses of political economy: the fetishist hypothesis of the vital forces of capital, the liberal hypothesis of the homeostatic and self-regulatory nature of the market(Adam Smith's 'invisible hand')or the hypothesis of the capitalist social relation founded on abstract freedom and equality, and supplemented with property and private interest. The communist hypothesis assumes a different status and is inscribed in the epistemological horizon of scientific modernity, on which Marx strived to ground his science of value and his critical method. This inscription can be demonstrated in the way materialist dialectics approaches social reality. It uncovers the immanent breaks in existing social appearances, thereby repeating the way modern science uses the mathematical apparatus in order to grasp the real of physical appearances. The dialectical materialist method, following modern epistemic ideals, discerns the structural real, which amounts to Marx's central hypothesis in Capital: there is no such thing as social relation. Or to quote The Communist Manifesto, ‘the history of all hitherto existing society is the history of class struggles’, which means, first and foremost, that History does not exist. The plurality of class struggles reveals the decentralisation of history in the same way as the unconscious exposes the decentralisation of thinking. Capital also contains a critical epistemology, which problematises the mobilisation of scientific methods and knowledge in the historical transformation of labour, in the genesis of capitalist social abstractions and in the introduction of two new figures of negativity in the social link: labour-power and surplus-value. It is in these that Lacan will recognise his subject of the signifier and object a.

中Freud summarised the movement of modern scientific revolution in three major insults to human narcissism, linked with three scientific decentralisations: of the universe (Copernicus, but one should rather say Newton), of life(Darwin/Wallace)and finally of thinking(Freud). He thereby undoubtedly indicated that the discovery of the unconscious -a specific manifestation of negativity, a form of knowledge without the subject of cognition, and finally a real discursive consequence -is made possible only in the horizon of modern science. More precisely, the Freudian theory of the unconscious becomes possible only once the consequences of modern scientific revolution have already been extended to the field of human production -in short, after Marx's epistemological break, as Althusser would have put it.

中Scientific revolution as a process that enables us to think the function and the place of negativity in the social link became the basis for the structuralist coupling of Marx with Freud already in Althusser, who undoubtedly inspired Lacan's interest in the critique of political economy. Althusser was the first one to associate Marx systematically with the structuralist program, insisting that, by thinking negativity in history and thought, Marx and Freud subverted the very notion of science. Althusser described psychoanalysis and the critique of political economy as ‘conflictual sciences’. Their antagonistic character comes from the fact that they both depart from the ‘persistence of the negative’ in the social and subjective sphere, rather than from its foreclosure. In this light, alienation also appears as constitutive of the subject and of society, a process that no longer stands merely for deprivation but also and above all for transformation. One of the main points in Lacan's reading of Marx lies in the attempt to overcome the opposition between vitalist positivity and dialectical negativity by reinterpreting the very concept of alienation.

中To repeat, the present book starts from the assumption that the reference to Marx signifies an important development in Lacan's teaching and inaugurates a second return to Freud that displaces the accent from structural linguistics to critique of political economy, and from the representation of the subject to the production of jouissance. Jouissance (enjoyment, or what Freud called libido) thereby reappears as the central problem of psychoanalysis; this was already the case with Freud, but it was systematically neglected in the progressive subordination of psychoanalysis to the ideals and demands of economic liberalism, through which the adaptation and reintegration of individuals into the existing social order became the main goal of analytic treatment. Jouissance does not only offer a privileged entry into the political importance of Freudian theory, it also reveals a limit of classical structuralism: to think the subject and the object that are produced by the autonomy of the signifier.

中We should recall that Freud's discovery of the unconscious places the main accent on the role of labour (Arbeit) in the satisfaction of the unconscious tendency (desire or drive) and that it constantly uncovers the productive dimension of the unconscious. This reference to labour should be taken literally. By placing the energetic notion of labour-power at the core of his discoveries Freud outlined a labour theory of the unconscious. Lacan's main point of interest in the late 1960s evolves around this important aspect in Freuds theory. In the concept of jouissance, Lacan brings together Freudian ‘psychic energy’ (libido) and the notion of unconscious labour. In order to fully determine the revolutionary character of Freud's discoveries, a theory of production was needed, a theory that Saussurean structuralism could not offer. But Marx did.

←→

第一章

“无意识就是政治”：

从索绪尔到马克思

结构与历史

英1963年是拉康教学发生关键转折的一年。在这一年，拉康被逐出国际精神分析协会。相应地，拉康创办了巴黎弗洛伊德学派，它的创立是为了与弗洛伊德遗产的官方捍卫者在建制与理论上分庭抗礼。学派的建立的目标是这样的一个组织：英该组织将完成这样一种劳动——这种劳动将在弗洛伊德打开的场域当中，打磨它真相的锋刃；这种劳动伴随着拉康以精神分析为名而引入的对世界的原初实践；这种劳动通过持续的批判，揭发阻碍它进步的偏离与妥协（阻碍是由于它的应用被矮化了）。[24]英这种基础行动并不掩盖其政治性，这尤其体现在他试图发展出精神分析颠覆性的政治、哲学和认识论维度。贯穿精神分析历史的偏离和妥协尤其体现在精神分析实践与自由市场经济的成功结合，这一结合在其他一些场合已被拉康所谴责。[25]有个著名的轶事：据说弗洛伊德在他们访问美国（1909年）期间对荣格说，美国人还不知道他和荣格正将他们带入一场瘟疫之中”。[26]反过来，处于狂热的弗洛伊德尚不知道美国资本主义已经有了对抗这种大陆疾病的解药。这种解药正是经济自由主义的意识形态。自由、平等、财产和私人利益，这种政治普遍主义与私人利己主义（或者像弗洛伊德可能会说的，“人类自恋”）的有效意识形态结合，成功地中和了精神分析对思考、主体性和社会本质的见解的激进性。在这满是机会的土地上，精神分析成功的代价很高——弗洛伊德在他关于无意识、主体间性和异化的研究中揭示的关键真相被人们遗忘。

英根据拉康的建基行动，学派的主要任务就是开启一个空间，在这个空间中劳动可以最终成为批判和真理相交织的过程。这里所讨论的劳动不仅仅是理论上的劳动，更是弗洛伊德归功于无意识的劳动。这种劳动形式包含着对于这样的过程的质询，该过程决定着主体的存在方式并伴随其直到转变点的到来。[27]对于拉康来说，重要的是有决心的工作者，而非数量。他将对弗洛伊德的回归当成这种劳动的例子，虽然这听上去很自命不凡，但其实他是在否定那些在移情的基础上建立精神分析机构的企图。后者可能能使精神分析社群团结在一起，但是代价是转变成一个教会——因此拉康提到了斯宾诺莎被逐出了教会。

英对于为什么移情必须被移除出学派（党派同理）之基础有一个重要的原因。通过将机构建立在肯定性的知识的生产而非批判性的真相（锋利的剃刀）之上，它将着力点从无意识的主体转移到了认知的主体之上。正如我们所知，拉康的制度性实验后来失败了，随后的各种组织形式都恢复了更为正统的制度政治。在1980年，学派最终被解散，因为其倒退回了移情关系，尽管拉康一直不停地拒斥对自己的主人身份的认同：英幸运的是，我从没说过我是弗洛伊德学派的，我不将自己当作知识的主体。确凿的证据是，我发明了假设应该知道的主体，这样精神分析学家就会停止相信——我的意思是认同它。[28]英该学派不仅致力于消除拉康和分析家群体之间的差异，还甚至想要消除分析家和被分析者之间的差异。当分析家不再被认同为有知识的，他们就被剥夺了他们的元位置，这个位置总已经是支配者（大他者）的位置。在这个意义上，假设应该知道的主体是个重要发明，它提供了对于精神分析语境内外的移情现象更深刻的洞见。移情不可避免地包含着恋物癖的时刻，通过它，知识被投射在他者之上并被转化成一种肯定性的内在品质。与此情况形成鲜明对比的是，拉康坚信，在和听众与分析家群体的关系中，他所担任的是被分析者的位置，在这里发挥作用的是与知识和主体相反的角色：无意识和能指的主体。当然，移情并不能从这样的关系中消除，这就是为什么拉康强调形式化在知识和真理传递过程中的重要性。只有逻辑可以成功调停两种同时存在的传递形式的对立，一种建立在爱之上，移情之爱，这会是种“哲学”的传递，仍然预设着主人的形象；另一种则是建立在话语的自动性（如数学的形式语言）之上，理想情况下它会构造出不围绕某个主人形象的共同体。言说者和解释者位置的分离避免了分析师认同自己作为知识的主体并相信自己拥有一些有关无意识的实在知识。通过形式化的传播，（拉康）废除了学派中所有成员不加批判地接受教条观念语库的想法。这（形式化传递）标示着一个劳动的过程，在其中拉康也是众多劳动主体中的一员，一个意志坚定的劳动者的典例——他的目标不是生产知识而是支持“劳动的转移”。[29]转移能够使坚定的劳动者克服他们个例的框架并走向普遍性（共同体）。一个个例成为普遍性能够从之被构建起来的结点。这样建构起来的普遍性不是包涵特殊情况的预设的抽象，而是一种具体的普遍性。它需要劳动——因此（需要）“劳动的转移”，需要劳动、形式化和传播之间的密切联系。我们可以在这里看到弗洛伊德“打通”（Durcharbeiten）一词在分析语境中的重要性。

英在被逐出协会之后，同样值得被提及的是拉康的第二次回到弗洛伊德。这种回归的标志是理论联盟的改变，随之的，对以前的教学内容大刀阔斧地重新解释。第一次回归众所周知地用结构语言学解读了弗洛伊德，并最终声称弗洛伊德理论先于索绪尔和雅各布森的语言学理论。转喻和隐喻，语言中的两个核心操作，是在无意识过程操纵意识和前意识材料的方式中被发现的。这两种语言操作转化为凝结和置换，这是无意识劳动的主要成就。回归弗洛伊德的语言学成为了拉康结构精神分析的同义词，这个早期发展的最凝练的公式，“无意识就像语言一样被结构起来”，已经变成了一种常见的看法。

英在被逐出协会之后，拉康逐步阐述了对弗洛伊德的另一种解读，发现了其与马克思的政治经济学批判的一种新的独特结合。离开语言范式的论域是在68年5月之后随即完成的，尽管这些政治事件并不是导致对回到弗洛伊德再定义的唯一条件。将论域转向批判范式并非与结构主义的限制无关，特别是在无意识生产的理论化和拉康教学中对原乐的问题的日益重视这两方面。

英然而，拉康的第二次回归弗洛伊德并没有简单地否认能指的结构主义隔离的重要性：英索绪尔和布拉格语言学派指出语言学建立在一个切割上，这是放置在能指和所指之间的横杠，为的是揭示差异，在差异中能指以绝对的方式被构建，并通过它有效地获得自动性。[30]英语言结构主义始于对能指自动性的认识和结构的极简主义。索绪尔从能指和所指之间的横杠开始，这使他能够分离语言符号的组成部分，并揭露它们关系的随意的本性。让我们回想一下，所讨论的横杠并不是针对词语和事物之间的外部关系，而是针对语言符号的内部一致性。因此，它指出了这两个组成部分之间没有任何牢固的、本质的或内在的联系，这意味着能指（一系列声音）和所指（相关的心理表征）之间的关系实际上是一种非关系：一种不稳定的、滑移的和无根据的联系。因此，索绪尔揭示了横杠的结构功能，并构想了能指的自动性，其独立于它与能指的联系，甚至独立于它与参照物的关系，即外部现实的元素。这种结构的极简主义的基本论点也可以表述如下：结构是一个切割。这种重新表述考虑了索绪尔最著名的隐喻之一，其中结构化的过程被解释为一种干预，它有序化声音和心理图像的无差别的、混乱的流动。这里至关重要的是，这个切割既可以被认为是差异的情况，也可以被认为是差异化的基础。[31]

英因此，索绪尔的能指以一种绝对和自主的方式构成，作为与另一个能指的差异，从而作为其自身的差异。能指链，这个语言结构最一般和形式化的表示，包含了一个切割的重复，从而形成了一个纯粹的差异或否定的链。结构语言学的革命性特征在于，语言理论不再预设稳定和意义明确的指称——无论是外部的还是内部的——而是通过切割，指向符号的两个组成部分之间的非关系和不稳定性。词语与事物的相遇，以及声音与意义的相遇，这不可避免地是偶然的，因为这样的相遇总是包含一种失败和错位，一种指称的扭曲。重申，结构语言学的内在论点是：语言是一种非关系，而不是关系。拉康强调能指的自动性，推动了这一前提走向前台。

英能指和所指之间的横杠引发了人文科学的认识论革命，因为结构主义范式打破了“亚里士多德主义”在语言学和语言哲学中的历史主导地位。在结构主义出现之前，语言几乎完全是根据亚里士多德的《工具论》中的概念来被设想的，在其中语言被定义为一种沟通和社会关系的工具和器官，以及一个自主、理性和清醒的主体之间的抽象约定。在结构语言学的视域下，语言是一个远远更加矛盾和复杂的对象，是一套抵抗总体化的差异系统。因为它是绝对的，自主的和不在场的，因此拉康使用在索绪尔那里分离了能指和所指的横杠，以期指示的大他者的不存在和主体的分裂。

英精神分析对无意识的发现与能指的自动性直接相关。人们能谈论无意识的前提是语言构建了一个自主寄存器——它不仅仅服务于交流，还能产生不能简化为认知和神经生物学过程的物质结果。因此，对无意识的发现要求我们拒斥语言学中亚里士多德主义——现存于语言分析哲学，乔姆斯基语言学和标准的传播理论（如哈贝马斯）之中。

英在精神分析中，能指的自动性得到了不同的表达。就无意识的显现（这恰恰是语言自动性的具象化）而言，人不能消除身体的存在，这是话语生产的场所，包含了两个方面：主体性的生产和享乐的生产。将语言与生产联系这一举动，重新提出了关于因果关系的旧哲学问题，这引导拉康将能指排列于物质因之中——在亚里士多德术语中反亚里士多德的一步。这种结构性因果关系的一个关键方面在第一次回到弗洛伊德时就已经主题化了，它将无意识的主体定义为能指不可避免的效果。但是，直到1960年代后期关于话语理论的发展，才为那些在精神分析一开始就出现的问题——能指的自动性问题以及关于无意识和享乐的主题——这一整个联系提供了框架。通过识出能指的因果关系，拉康果断地反抗了实用主义传统，后者将语言视作无关紧要的非物质性的和无效的存在。对于精神分析来说则相反，语言是一种物质性的和有效的非存在。[32]

英在这里，我们可以发现精神分析唯物主义的主要特征。语言真正的重要性在于它是一个否定性的开放系统（能指作为纯粹的差异），它被具象化成言说。通过言说，这些否定性被铭刻在活的肉体中。拉康的第二次回到弗洛伊德用非全概念指示这个开放的语言结构，从而提出了索绪尔式横杠的另一种含义。如前所述，在结构主义精神分析的背景下，同样的横杠表示主体的异化和大他者的不存在。划斜杠的主体（能指指向另一个能指）和划斜杠的大他者（差异的开放系统），都说明了能指的自动性的重要性。然而，这也是经典结构主义的局限初现之处。

英拉康的第二次回到弗洛伊德，与雅各布森推行的有关索绪尔的转向不无关系，后者将自动性从能指扩展到诗歌语言。借此，雅各布森表明，能指的诗化（语言上的歧义性[33]）应该与其形式化并行，作为其自动性的体现。与海德格尔（认为诗歌语言显露了原始的“存在感”）不同，雅各布森在诗歌中强调了语言的生产性维度，这个维度需要被置于能指和所指的关系之上，而在不同能指之间的关系中。从这个意义上讲，雅各布森的诗学与弗洛伊德关于能指的力比多投资相呼应。受雅各布森进展的启发，拉康将能指定义为享乐装置，[34]尽管雅各布森的语言学并不完全支持这个定义，因为它将话语的生产限制在意义的歧义性上。

英在第二次回到弗洛伊德中，拉康并没有提出任何可以与“无意识是像语言一样被结构起来的”相匹配的格言，但它最基本的观点却被高度囊括在一个看似高深莫测的表述中：“无意识就是政治。”[35]毫无疑问，这句话应该与第一句话对照着理解。如何理解从语言结构到政治的转变？拉康只是反对抽象的结构和具体的经验吗？并非如此。第二个格言努力克服结构和政治的对立，他们的反对者曾将这对立推动成为结构主义的代表。这个对对立的取消最清晰地表现在拉康对福柯的演讲“什么是作家？”（1969）那臭名昭著的介入中。在他的回应中，拉康坚决否认1968年的五月风暴否定了结构主义，甚至也没有否定拉康自己的结构概念——那与索绪尔的差异体系显著不同的概念：英先不管我是不是结构主义者，我想指出的是：这个领域——它被这场运动不甚清晰地显示出来——似乎并没有表达对主体的否定。我所讨论的是主体的依赖性，这是完全不同的；值得注意的是，在回到弗洛伊德的层面上，主体的依赖性与真正基本的东西有关，我们试图将它与“能指”这个表述分离……我不认为表述“结构没有降临街头”有任何正当性，因为如果五月的事件说明了什么，那么（他们说明的）正是结构在街头的降临。这段话正是在这个降临发生的地点被写下的——这仅仅向我们展示了一些司空见惯的，甚至是最为常见的内在于我们称之为行动的东西：它错误认识了自己。[36]英街头上的结构的概念表明，这一关键的结构主义概念既不代表一个无关紧要的、不变的差异系统，也不代表象征秩序的超验主义。结构降临到街头的特点是内在的断裂、矛盾和不稳定，这将能指的自动性置于一个不同的视角下。因此，拉康表明，社会变革的可能性应该在这个层面上被思考，因为只有严格的结构分析可以解释为什么社会运动的革命潜力（基于学生和工人的联盟）以失败告终，而且反倒促成了“新资本主义精神”的建立。[37]拉康对68年后反结构主义的不满的关键在于主体的概念。主体性的形式当然可以被思考为多种多样的，但有一种形式是社会结构的基础，那就是由话语关系的自动性引起的主体。正是在这个基础上，现有秩序决定了人们的思考和行动，也正是在这里，主体开始通过思考和行动反对现有制度。主体的依赖性通过68年5月风暴的行动者构想他们行为的方式可见一斑：在涂鸦中一个最明显的误解：“结构不在街头游行”。68年5月风暴的行动者和支持者反对结构和事件（或者说结构和政治），这是他们的关键失败之一。他们非但不将这次事件看作结构性真实的爆发，而是被一个纯粹真实的外部结构的幻想所引导，从而忽视了这样一个事实：他们所要求的自由化（例如教育方面）引发了更直接的知识商品化。[38]

英对拉康来说，政治事件表现了学生具体行为中的结构行为：一方面，通过结构关系，主体的决定之间的对立；另一方面，主体对体系压迫的抵制。从这个意义上说，68年5月风暴确实是一个行动。这不仅是因为政治主体显现了它自己，还因为它在行动主体（革命学生）看待自己的位置和他们在整个资本主义制度的转变中的行动的位置之间有不可忽视的转变。因此，结构在街头的降临形成了一个关于政治、结构和无意识之间的联系的明确论点：能指逻辑所强调的结构性悖论与横贯现有社会秩序的对立直接相关。如果无意识可以与政治相关联，或者说，如果政治行动包含了能指的主体作为其内在否定性，那么弗洛伊德的概念并不意味着超然的和私人的经验，相反，其提供了对相同结构性动力（这最终导致社会联系的不稳定）的洞察。简而言之，政治行动是结构性矛盾和逻辑形式的实现。

英“无意识是政治”这句话包含了结构的概念的转变，同时提供了对于精神分析与政治之间联系的特定理解。它坚持认为无意识的发现意味着政治上的变革，尽管不是把政治简化为无意识的复合体的意思。拉康毫无疑问地表明“无意识是政治”并不意味着“政治是无意识”。后者确实意味着政治的心理学化，将政治内容简化为无意识的复合体。无意识与政治之间的“是”并不是反身性的。它更关注的是将无意识主体正式纳入政治领域，认为社会联系是通过异化和否定性构建的——尤其是在马克思的批判之后。因此这并不意外，拉康的第二次回归弗洛伊德运动致力于阐述一种证明了无意识机制对占主导的社会关系的逻辑依赖性的话语理论。因此，第二次回归弗洛伊德运动并不仅仅将无意识等同于语言结构，而是将无意识等同于结构真实，表征与生产的交织，能指因果关系的两面性。因此，拉康将标志着他的早期教学以及整个古典结构主义的的符号秩序先验论问题化了。

英这种强调无意识的实在地位的新唯物主义导向，暗示了两种相反的主张，即语言的结构是无意识的条件同时无意识不能完全还原为象征结构。相反，它（该导向）证明了一个关于能指自动性的本体论丑闻，这个自动性会在其结构一致性崩溃之时变得最为真实（例如弗洛伊德的创伤）。语言从它的关系层面退回的越多，其实际的效果就越明显。通过这一举措，拉康避免了无意识的直接本体化和实体化，以及将其简单简化为在既定的资本主义话语语境中的单一的话语结构。

英语言结构主义的局限性在另一个对于拉康的经典公理的重新表述中得到了解决：英人们在结构与辩证法之间制造出虚假的对立，结构是共时的因而在历史之外，而辩证法是历时的，沉浸在时间之中。但这并不准确。在我的书中，读一读标题为《罗马话语》的文章，你就能估计出我对历史的重视程度，在我看来它和无意识的语域范围是相同的。无意识就是历史。已经经历的[le vécu]是以一个首要的历史性标志的。这些都白纸黑字地写在我的书上[39]。英“无意识即历史”驳斥了两种错误的对立：结构与辩证法之间的对立，无意识与历史之间的对立。这些对立只是标志着战后大陆哲学的结构与发生学之间更根本对立的变体。如前所述，这种对立需要被结构和历史性的具体交织所取代，这并不掩盖其辩证法的主张。我们可以理解为什么这样的对立对精神分析没有多大意义。无意识处于共时性和历时性的交叉点，这意味着它一方面不断地表现出转变和不稳定性，而在另一方面表现出暂时的固定性。这样，结构和历史的二分法就完全失效了，毫无意义。对于弗洛伊德来说，仍和心理结构都包含着运动，其中心理冲突也能够被独立出来。因此，他有关结构的思想归结为这种内在的动力而不是某种非历史的僵化关系。结构稳定性的最低限度能够建立在凝缩与位移的过程之上，这能在语言学上找到等价物——隐喻与转喻。但这里需要再次重复，如果没有它们的历时维度，这两个操作是不可想象的，历时性在这情景中引入了时间性。历时性是个必要的条件，这使得弗洛伊德能够将凝缩和位移理论化为无意识劳动的具体成就。

英弗洛伊德对结构和历史交织的看法最有激情的时刻，大概是他将无意识与罗马相比较时（尽管这么做并非无关紧要）。在《文明及其不满》一书中可以了解到，罗马的历史不同于真实的罗马，前者以无法重建的废墟和碎片的形式存在，无意识的永恒之城就像一个全息图，其中一切都保存完好：所有建筑都留存在其所在历史阶段，城市的所有过去都始终存在。[40]就时间性的本质部分是腐败、变化和遗忘而言，无意识似乎不知道时间，而从另一个角度来看，它只不过是时间：历史压在当下，表现为话语的中断、失误、做梦和笑话，以及“永恒的当下”（马克思和恩格斯认为它是意识形态的最基本操作）的中断。因此，（谁的？）主要的意识形态成就在于拒绝时间性、宣布历史的终结，统治话语的虚假永恒化。

英弗洛伊德自然地意识到他这个比喻的局限性，比起准确地定义结构和无意识的时间性之间的关系，其更体现的是他本人对罗马的迷恋的背叛。在（弗洛伊德）早期的关于屏蔽记忆[41]的文章中，有另一个关于它们之间关系的更合适的论述。在该文中，弗洛伊德指出，人类的记忆不是不可更改数据的档案，而是经过不断修改的集合。这些修改远非中立，而是表达了异构的心理实例与其特定倾向之间不可简化的冲突。在此，值得注意的是，弗洛伊德从屏蔽记忆解释其他记忆（可能是历史上更准确的记忆）的方式中得出的结论：英伪造的记忆是我们最先意识到的：记忆的原始材料——来自被伪造之物的痕迹，我们仍然不知道它的原始形式。对这一真相的认识无疑减弱了屏蔽记忆和我们童年时的其他记忆之间的区别。确实值得怀疑的是，我们是否有任何来自童年的记忆：我们具有的可能只有与童年有关的记忆。我们童年的记忆向我们展示的最初的岁月，并非它们过去所是的样子，而是它们出现在后来回忆时的样子。在这些回忆的时候，童年的记忆并没有像人们常说的浮现；它们是在当时形成的。还有许多动机——并不考虑准确还原一段记忆——不仅形成了记忆，也参与了记忆本身的选择。[42]英这一段的直接教益毫无疑问：历史并不存在，换言之，历史不是事件的客观历史，正如记忆不是中立事实的档案。相反，弗洛伊德建议把它看作是一系列变形、错位、重写，以及最重要的——冲突，然而这些都包含了支持整个运动的最小结构关系，或者只是运动中的一个结构。历史像语言一样结构起来，而就像语言一样，历史并不存在，但对主体有实质性的影响。

英弗洛伊德在这种历史的呈现中遇到的是回溯性的因果关系，这在他之后对无意识的历史性的概念中也有所体现。回溯不只是从现在的视角修改历史事件的意义。在某种意义上，这种具有强大回溯力的修改构成了对过去的历史和记忆。回溯性被认为是因果关系的形式，而不是对客观事实的扭曲。童年早期记忆（这决定主体的一系列后续发展的事件）的形成，在主体历史的回溯性建构和转变中起着主要作用。

英在此，我们可以回忆这种回溯最著名的例子：在“狼人”一例中引发症状的创伤事件。这个事件不只是“客观地”发生在患者童年早期的某个时候，然后在之后的生活中反复出现。这是回溯性建构因果关系的名副其实的效果，它将曾经的偶然遭遇或观察与一个焦虑的梦联系在一起，在这个梦中，病人看到狼坐在家庭房子门前的树上，透过卧室的窗户一动不动地盯着他。在此，弗洛伊德如何对该梦的内容加以阐释并不重要；重要的是，他自己公开承认不重要的实际事件在过去引发了疾病——回溯性因果关系已经提供了对事件足够正式的阐释，与在现实中可能发生的具体事情相比，这个阐释有着同等的创伤性效果。因此，创伤并非延续到当下的单一的先验事件，而是时间关系的实在效果，通过它，当下能回溯性地改变过去，转而重新定义当下。对弗洛伊德来说，结构和历史是不可分割的，甚至是一样的，而克服它们的简单对立的概念正是回溯性（Nachträglichkeit）。

英在他的《费加罗报》的采访中，拉康从他关于罗马的话语中生发了以下关键段落，其揭示了无意识和历史之间的关系：“在我的历史中，无意识一章被一个空白或谎言占据：这是被删减的一章。但真相可以重现；它通常已经被写在其他地方了。”[43]首先，真理是写在主体的身体上的，作为异化和话语生产的物质载体。无意识的特点是对立和矛盾（由删减和谎言足见），这些弗洛伊德无意识的具体特征。相比于其他特征，它不包含结构性冲突，而通常只是不明确的表征和原型的精神档案。弗洛伊德方法的全部原创性在于在无意识中发现了这种冲突性现实：英因为，如果该方法的独创性源于它所放弃的手段，那是因为它为自己保留的手段足以构成一个领域，这个领域的界限定义了其操作的相对性。它的手段是言语的手段，只要言语赋予在个体功能层面上的意义；它的领域是主体的跨个体现实的具体话语领域；它的运作是历史的运作，因为历史构成了真理在现实中的出现。[44]英弗洛伊德建立了真理、历史和矛盾之间的联系，从而提出(就像马克思和黑格尔之前提出的那样)，关于矛盾运动的历史的概念构成了与意识不一致的主体。弗洛伊德将这种矛盾给以实在的地位，指出历史不仅包含了现实（在真实性的意义上）和实在之间的差异，而且也表明了二者的完整重合是不可能的。在实在中出现的真相显然不是关于认知的充分真相，而是社会关系的冲突性真相，因此是一种政治真相。对真相的唤起至关重要，正如马克思的批判对精神分析的意义与他将社会症状作为特定的真相的形成这一发明有关。它也象征了一个结构的概念，这个结构不再是索绪尔式的没有主体的中立差异体系。

索绪尔和政治经济学

英在《普通语言学教程》中，索绪尔在语言学和政治经济学之间作了一个强有力的类比。他的解释方式是：提醒读者，这两个学科都可以被认为是有价值的科学。尽管语言的价值和经济的价值不一样，但索绪尔认为它们有着共同的逻辑背景。价值只能来自于两个符号之间的差异。哪里有差异，哪里就有价值；因此，价值既不能基于与所指的关系，也不能基于商品的性质方面，即其使用价值。这种价值的独立足以反映差异制度的绝对自动性。凭借此，索绪尔为后来对马克思的结构主义解读提供了坚实的基础。能指和交换价值变得难以区分。

英然而，这里出现了一个重要的难题，因为对马克思来说，商品并不是一个简单的概念。《资本论》的第一卷首先关注其复杂性，揭示了其广泛的结构和社会影响的模棱两可。对商品形式的仔细考察表明，商品是一个看似无关紧要的经验主义对象，在使用价值和交换价值上存在分裂。商品在质和量之间的分裂反映在质和形式间的分裂上，或者正如让-克劳德·米尔纳所说的，反映在没有物的质和没有质的物之间的分裂上。[45]米尔纳的规范与现代科学宇宙中物质性新的概念化密切相关，在现代科学中，物质不再指定实证的物品——由经验主义的质的集合（如硬度、广延、连贯性）定义，而是成为几何化随之数学化的抽象。物质的元素是从经验观察中孤立出来的抽象的理论对象。物质的非物质化，其与实证的质的逐渐分离（这仍说明着物体与人类观察者的关系），在量子力学中达到了顶峰。我无意在此处详细描述这一历史发展。[46]这里重要的是，物质和经验主义的质之间的科学区分直接导致了商品的非经验主义的物质性，以及马克思在他对商品形式的分析中分离出来的商品之间的关系。

英我们接着讲商品的分裂（索绪尔实际上将它排除在语言科学之外）。劳动产品的使用价值和经验主义的质可能不那么重要，但这一概念极大地支撑了马克思对商品的模棱两可以及其双重性质所产生的必要幻想的解释。使用价值使所有商品都成为可以通过其质量精确满足需求的对象。这种需求不一定先于商品，而是可以随产品而创造出来。[47]因此，每种商品都是使用价值和交换价值的相互关系，无论生产对象有多么抽象（服务、网站、智能手机应用程序等）。商品至少要与对质量的幻想联系在一起，这代表了生产与对应需求的最小公约数。直接的结论是，需求不是某种准自然和非符号的倾向，而是已经包含了符号中介。即使商品的生产目的不是为了满足人类的需求，而是首先为了支撑交换和刺激消费（这是价值生产的基石之一），它们也必须保持有用和有需求的虚构，无论多么抽象、无用和幻想。正是这种幻象支撑了使用价值和交换价值的结合，没有质的物和没有物的质的结合，这两个异质的和不相关的层次。交换的维度和商品的流通直接表明商品失去了独有和看似明确的解决人类需求（产品和需求之间的充分关系）的特征，生产的另一个方面登上前台——价值的生产，通过它，我们能抵达差异系统的自动性。同时，交易和市场都将商品从独特的对象变成了大规模的产品，这暴露了一种重复，这种重复不能与使用价值的维度相关联，或者更准确地说，使有用性和交易之间的关系复杂化。[48]

英因此，商品包含了双重差异，而不是单单一重差异。除了使用价值和交换价值之间的划分之外，还有交换价值本身的差异。使用价值表现在商品与消费之间的关系上，这使得前者既意味着需求，又意味着心理主体，而需求可以归因于心理主体。然而，从交换价值和商品本身的关系来看，交换价值显然是无主体的。马克思接着指出，事实并非如此，因为在商品世界中，有一种商品构成了例外：劳动力——这是唯一的生产商品的商品。这一例外意味着交换价值并不是无主体的，而只是没有需求的主体（心理的或经验性的主体）。马克思从他的前人（亚当·斯密和李嘉图）那里所吸纳的劳动价值理论现在决定了价值的主体并可被解读为马克思的主体理论。

英因此，马克思关于价值的科学理论的第一个研究成果就已经加倍了：使用价值和交换价值之间的差异揭示了价值的自动性，并将价值定义为与另一种价值的差异。在这一点上，马克思的政治经济学批判似乎与索绪尔有重叠。尽管这一研究成果直接表明：交换价值并非没有主体，只是这个主体与使用价值（需求）的主体并非同一个。交换价值不仅是价值-能指和商品-所指之间的垂直关系，也是交换的主体的象征。交换的主体可以在所有商品中预设，马克思将它与劳动力联系在一起。索绪尔并没有得出这个结论，在这方面，拉康在第一次回到弗洛伊德时就业已从能指逻辑中得出的关于主体的推论，超出了结构语言学严格的认识论框架。

英因此，关于价值的科学在看起来早于交换的非符号的使用价值之层面就已经开始。马克思的批判始于对商品学的政治经济学想法、关于商品的专业知识，而价值的科学构成了这门学科的一个子集。“在市民社会中”，马克思在一个脚注中写道，“流行着这样的合法虚构：每个人作为买家，都对商品有百科全书式的知识”。[49]每个人都带着预设的知识进入市场，就如同经济人一样，他们大概有着关于他/她的私人利益的天然知识，尤其是作为价值科学家的知识。对马克思来说，这种预设的基础并不可靠，因其把每个人都当作认知的主体。经济主体的预设知识首先在人们与商品发生关联的方式上被检验——在商品拜物教中，马克思再次表明，使用价值和交换价值之间的区别意味着两个不相容和异构的主体，其中一个是关于需求、利益和实证知识的中心化主体，另一个是去中心化和非心理的价值的主体。但当务之急是，无论我们论及语言价值还是经济价值，语言交换还是经济交换，知识已经为主体预设好了。这种知识尽管不是必然的反映，但在商品和价值相互联系的方式中起着最明显的作用，也在每个人与商品的关系，在结构的行为以及人的行为中起着作用。

英语言学和政治经济学在讨论价值和商品之间的关系、能指和所指之间的关系时，它们第一次发现了价值的双重特征。还有一个因素使这两种价值科学的问题复杂化。索绪尔指出，语言学和政治经济学具有内在的双重性，不是因为价值的概念包含了一个定性和定量的维度，而是因为定量的维度用时间性标记着它们的科学对象。历史再一次进入了结构之中。价值的场域不断变化，使得价值随时间变化。价值的波动揭示了大他者中的“通货膨胀”——系统中的结构动态和不稳定性。为了说明这一点，索绪尔首先给出了一些科学的例子，其中时间不会对其领域和对象的结构造成特殊的困难。比如天文学，它研究恒星组合方式的变化，借此这些变化的时间性并不需要天文学本身的内在分化；地质学也是如此，它探索不同的地质时代，但很容易转向对不变的情况的描述。时间的变换不会改变研究的对象，这些变化背后的规律被认为是稳定的。

英所有这些科学的处境在语言学和政治经济学的框架中发生变化，对象的转变取决于我们是否认为它具有时间性，即是否与主体有联系。政治经济学和经济史在一门科学中形成了两门独立的学科，静态语言学和演变语言学也是如此。这已经表明，语言模型和经济模型并没有普遍的有效性。它们在历史和地理上总是已经被限制，这是批判性经济学家愿意承认的。[50]经济模型的这种局限性与市场的不稳定性密切相关，同样的结构不稳定也体现在语言领域中，拉康借此特征构建了划斜杠的大他者理论。

英如前所述，内在的分裂在两种价值学科中是由（与交换的社会维度相关的）时间因素导致的：“两种学科都涉及针对不同秩序的等价物的系统——一个是劳动力和工资，另一个是所指和能指。”[51]，这种对应关系并不局限于此。正如政治经济学处理交换价值和使用价值之间的差异一样，索绪尔也引入了语言价值和意义之间的相似的差异。意义仍然以说话者之间的关系为前提，而语言价值则表明了能指自身之间的自主关系。价值关系对说话者和意义的生成是未知的，为了达到语言中这一层面，语言学需要把语言从言语中抽象出来。索绪尔在一篇著名的论文中总结了这一表达：语言学（le langage）的对象是语言（le langage）减去言说（la parole）。只有完成这个操作后，语言才能成为抽象的差异系统。“语言中只有差异”，这意味着我们通常所感受的语言包含两个不同的方面，甚至是两种不同的语言——价值的语言和意义的语言。当人类彼此之间交流时，他们不知不觉地说着价值的语言，这是一种不交流意义的语言。问题是，它也许根本没有交流。能指的自动性代表着语言交流的非交流内核。

英让我们回到索绪尔说明语言价值和经济价值的巧合的例子。索绪尔认为，从价值的角度来看，劳动与工资的关系与所指和能指之间的关系是同源的。在此，值得注意的是，索绪尔对例子的选择并不完全幸运。他忽视了这个对比的问题之处，因为他并没有提及哪怕任何经济关系，而是提到最有问题的商品交换，这使整个政治经济学受到质疑。因此，他选择的例子（对于马克思来说）揭示了劳动力在商品世界和经济交换中的症状地位。索绪尔的类比重犯了马克思对经典政治经济学批判的同样错误：在市场上流通的东西不是一个过程（劳动力），而是一种特定的商品（劳动力）。在此，让我们往后退几步。

英由于时间性不能从价值的领域中完全消除，因此等价系统可以有两个方向。这个等价关系可以是关于此时此地的事物，也可以是关于时间演变中的事物。如果它是关于事物的现状的，它就把市场描绘成一个现有商品的静态罗列；因此，我们把政治经济学当作市场关系的基本原理。然而，如果这个等价关系与事物的时间演变有关，那么它不仅包括交换，还包括生产和生产关系。为了把它和索绪尔的公式联系起来，时间性将言语重新引入了语言。在此，由价值的概念所产生的分裂最终得到了它的全部重要性。索绪尔用两个轴的交点来说明它：同时性轴，它表示共存事物之间的关系，并排除了时间的维度；以及演变轴，“在这条轴上只能同时考虑一件事，但第一条轴上的所有事物以及它们的变化都坐落在它之上”。[52]在语言学中，这种区分是绝对和必要的，因为“语言是一个纯粹价值的系统，决定它的除了其术语的随时排列之外别无他物”。[53]因此，在一个没有外部决定因素或不可能自我解脱的领域中，这种区分是必要的。语言和市场是两个认不出外部的领域。由于这种绝对性，要讨论它们只能将它们分为时间性和非时间性（不受时间影响）的方面。只有当语言和市场与它们的时间性分开时，价值可以成为科学的对象，因为这种时间性表明它们的结构比看起来更矛盾。因为它们没有外在性，所以它们是不完整的。因为它们是不完整的，所以它们内在地被划了斜杠。因此（因为它们被划斜杠了），他们就认不出实证的存在。大他者（语言、市场）不存在。对于语言学来说，有必要通过将语言与时间性分离来构建它的对象（语言）。但同时，这种分离排除了直接来自能指的否定性的语言的有问题的存在。同样，政治经济学必须构建其对象（市场）的领域，市场被假定为实证的存在，即作为建构完全的、自我平衡的秩序，遵循稳定的规律，其功能或多或少地可被预测并且翻译成数学语言。亚当·斯密的“市场看不见的手”将这两个特征结合在一起，这个原始比喻在当代经济学论争中的持久存在证明了大他者存在的假设是行之有效的。对经济的大他者，我们以改革和紧缩措施的形式发出积极的信号，安抚其不稳定和反复无常的特征。对于语言学和政治经济学来说，大他者确实存在，至少在作为这样的观念存在：逻辑上可预测和自我调节的价值体系。[54]

英商品交换与语言、价值与能指在结构和逻辑上的重叠，也基于政治经济学批判的展开。在《资本论》第一章，商品拜物教一节中，马克思通过商品语言的思想论述了交换价值的自动性的认知后果。[55]他在著名的商品人格化中展示了这种语言：英如果商品能说话，他们会说：“我们的使用价值可能会引起人们的兴趣，但它不属于我们。而真正属于我们的是我们的价值。我们自身作为商品的交往证明了这一点。我们互相仅仅通过交换价值产生联系”。[56]英从商品的双重特征来看，似乎语言位于交换价值之中，而使用价值则位于语言之外。商品语言这一概念的主回路，相比之下，在于它在语言中把使用价值和交换价值的结合，从而确定两个语言角度之间的关系：人类语言与商品语言，对应交流与差异的自动性，或者用索绪尔的话讲，对应意义和价值。除了在结构上将交换和语言联系起来之外，马克思还定位了商品分裂的具体结构效应，这直接源于优先于使用价值的交换价值（貌似是价值的内在特征）。在商品发表了它们的文章之后，马克思把这个词留给了政治经济学家。结果表明，实际上在说话的并非经济学家，而是商品，它们通过政治经济学家的嘴巴和政治经济学理论继续言说：英现在让我们来听听这些商品是怎么通过经济学家开口说话的。‘价值（即交换价值）是事物的属性——人的财富（即使用价值）。从这个意义上说，价值必然意味着交换，而财富则不是。’‘财富（使用价值）是人的属性，价值是商品的属性。’一个人或一个社区是富有的，一个珍珠或钻石是有价值的……珍珠或钻石是作为珍珠或钻石才有价值”。[57]英在政治经济学中，一种奇怪的论调正岌岌可危。马克思揭示了商品语言和人类语言之间存在着直接的连续性、模棱两可和不可分性。他引用了英国实用主义哲学家和经济学家塞缪尔·贝利的话，塞缪尔的话表明，商品语言不能被当作一个隐喻；商品的拟人化并不作为修辞性的虚构，而只是行动中的语言。它（商品）说话了（Ca parle）。商品语言显得冗余，因为经济学家只是在重复由交换的自动性生产的表象。因此，价值内在于商品这一表象是交换价值自动性的逻辑结果，同时展示了商品语言与人类语言的结构性重叠：前者是商品之间通过价值互相沟通，后者则是能指在人类交流背后相互关联。当马克思谈到商品拜物教时，他并没有设想一些“普遍的歪曲”，而是落脚于价值的表象和逻辑自动性之间的最小转变。

英人类语言和商品语言的不可分性先于拉康的一句重要格言，“元语言不存在”，换句话说，没有什么标准能限制差异系统的自动性，这意味着能指之间的关系的优先于它们与所指的关系，从而优先于语言的交际维度和参照维度。语言不是意义明确的，而是模棱两可的，不是一种关系，而是非关系的范例。因为不存在所谓元语言，所以也不存在语言。语言体系和经济体系构成的是开放的集合。因此，元语言的不存在（大他者的大他者）和大他者的不存在是完全一致的。

英从人类语言和商品语言的模棱两可和不可分性，以及从经济价值和语言价值（能指作为差异或与其他能指的关系）的结构性重叠出发，马克思演绎出主体性的构造——由“商品恋物癖”这一表达来编码，主体性被赋予了结构性决定的误解。因此，马克思强调了说话者和主体之间的差异，以及由使用价值给出的主体（心理和经验性的认知主体）和交换价值的主体（来自差异系统的自动性，故而是去中心化的和转喻的）之间的差异。因此，马克思对商品拜物教的分析包含了两个要素：作为原因的能指和异化的主体（价值自动性的物质结果）。重申，商品语言的概念意味着商品交换像语言一样结构。马克思对拜物教批判的公开语言学意义在拉康看来是明显的，他在他的早期教学中发现了政治经济学批判与结构主义的亲和力，先于阿尔都塞的结构化马克思主义：英打开《资本论》第一卷，就能够意识到，马克思对商品拜物教特征分析的第一步正是在于他在能指本身的层面上解决了问题，尽管这个词还没被提出来。[58]英马克思从交换的自动性出发，目的是推断出由该自动性不可避免地生产出的主体性的特定形式。这个推断显示出主体对能指的依赖：差异系统、商品交换、商品之间的流通方式，塑造了独立于任何对消费者的参照的主体。这种主体化的隐藏角度随即在商品拜物教上显现出来，商品拜物教是对价值的政治经济学来源之神秘化，它试图分开结构性因果关系的两侧：（剩余）价值的生产和（异化）主体性的生产。根据恋物癖的立场，商品被赋予了内在的价值，尽管这种误解是客观而非主观的。差异系统的自动性必然生产出这样一种表象：价值是物品的实证属性，且它没有主体，更恰当的说，它是它自己的主体。商品拜物教因此进化为资本拜物教，在其中金融的抽象似乎相互产生，而独立于任何否定性的价值主体。资本成为没有否定性的、幽灵般的生活的专有词汇。塞缪尔·贝利的案例只是每个人如何自发地与商品联系在一个例证。每个消费者脑中都有一个政治经济学家，即预先假定的认知主体，为此，人们假设了一种关于商品的百科全书式的知识——经济人，这是价值经济学科的理想主体。最后，这种理想主体的假设使得政治经济学忽视了结构性生产出来的拜物教，正如马克思反复说明的，批判的任务恰恰是去思考价值的生产以及围绕这种生产的幻想的生产。换言之，政治经济学仍然在探寻价值的起源，因此它只能或多或少地制造科学神话。相比之下，对政治经济学的批判放弃了这种探寻，转而关注剥削和拜物教间的相关性。

英商品的言说非常接近索绪尔看待构成语言的符号的方式，其中没有论及时间性。这并不意味着索绪尔与语言的关系是恋物癖式的，但它确实意味着通过（不知情地）重复政治经济学的过失，他将语言学限制在交换的注册上，而语言表征和语言生产的关系没有主题化。由于没有设想到劳动过程和劳动力之间的区别，以及劳动力和其他商品之间的区别，索绪尔将生产置于语言学科之外。对他来说，语言认不出剩余，语言的使用自始至终是交际的和有意义的。这最终成为拉康对索绪尔批判的核心观点：英交流意味着参照。但有一件事是明确的——语言仅仅是科学话语炮制用来说明我所称之为咿呀（lalangue）的东西[59]。语言所服务的目的与交流所服务的目的完全不同……如果交流接近于在咿呀的享乐中发挥作用的东西，那是因为交流意味着回答（对话）。但是，语言是首要服务于对话的吗？正如我之前说过的，没有什么比这更不确定的了。[60]英索绪尔被肯定和否定是因为同一个立场。能指的自动性意味着语言交流维度的限制，因此也意味着语言使用价值（意义/与所指的关系）的限制。拉康在这里所描述的咿呀已经是从索绪尔向马克思转变的结果。语言和咿呀之间的区别现在代替了语言意义和能指自动性之间的差异。咿呀完全站在这种自动性的一边，否定了交流和关系性（对话）的首要地位。在此能指首先作为享乐装置出现。所讨论的自动性——索绪尔发现的核心——为语言通向咿呀提供了必要的基础，但只有当引入了主体和剩余客体，这才得以发生。因此，拉康的第二次回到弗洛伊德运动最终将能指的自主权延伸到了马克思主义对生产方式的怀疑上。

英在索绪尔的理论中，共时性和历时性的引入阐明了语言学（静态语言学和进化语言学）及其对象内部的分裂。语言是既是状态也是运动。在此，语言学面临着一个不可能的困境：如果它针对语言的静态的、临时的方面，它就失去了其对象的一个重要方面——语言价值的生产；如果它关注时间性，它必须承认语言不存在，这意味着它处理的对象是不稳定和矛盾的。在第一种情况下，语言学变成了“对咿呀知识的思考”，[61]如此一来，语言变成了科幻小说——一种语言学知识的构想；在第二种情况下；语言学不能完全解释交流，因为语言（咿呀）的统一性会在“私人”语言（咿呀）的多样性中消失。这种语言和言说的二分法是拉康在索绪尔的语言学中批评的，相反，他努力构建一种语言学，将其重新命名为“癔言学（linguisterie）”，[62]从而“更严肃地”对待语言，考虑语言的“生命”：它的时间以及因果维度。拉康在这里似乎与德勒兹后来的评论有呼应：“语言学做了很多坏事”，[63]特别是当它将语言从生产中分离时，没有考虑到它是能指自动性的一个基本方面。如果没有语言内在的不稳定性，就不会有语言。同样的批判性立场也指导着马克思与政治经济学的关系。

英同样地，政治经济学也揭示了它的缺陷。因为如果没有对商品、货币和资本的隐性拜物教，它就无法解释价值的产生——这是对知识的另一种思考，它将价值归因于商品、货币，以及在最抽象的层面上，归因于虚拟资本的直接生产力。如马克思所言，“能生钱的钱”是对价值自动性的主要拜物教幻想。那么，这种自我生成的幻想处于所有资本主义拜物教的核心，并成为金融化的驱动力就不足为奇了。这种金融生机论只能建立在对否定性排斥的基础上，建立在标志价值主体的分裂的基础上，并通过它贯穿整个商品世界。然而，关键点不仅是将生产重新引入语言，而且要暴露它的双重方面，即否定性主体的生产与原始剩余对象的生产的相互依赖。

英然而，当索绪尔将语言的铭文在同时性和历时性的交叉维度与国际象棋游戏进行比较时，他还是试图对语言的共时性和历时性方面进行理论化。这种比较结合了语言的静态和动态维度，指出特定元素的值取决于它们在棋盘上的位置。它说明了价值和差异之间的联系，索绪尔拒绝了我们可以称之为语言拜物教的东西，它试图将语言视为“关于存在的语言”（海德格尔），换言之，一种试图建立语言价值和意义之间的关系和连续性。

英在哲学史上，我们发现了这种拜物教的两个突出版本，其将哲学关系引导向语言。首先是在《克拉图罗斯》中，柏拉图试图阐明词语和事物之间的模仿关系，从而使语言价值与能指和参考词之间的自然联系相对应：英至于名字，如果我们的立法者真的给我们命名，不应该也知道如何把每个事物真正的自然名字放在声音和音节里，以及为了得到理想的名字，而给它创造所有的名字吗？[64]英这个命名者的神话形象将自然翻译成语言而没有任何损失。整个对话的发展意味着语言处于与自然的和谐模仿关系，因此即使在其基本组成部分——音素中，我们也会遇到对自然的声音、性质和状态的模仿。柏拉图试图提供一个神话般的证明：能指和所指之间的关系是本植根于自然（物理，存在），能指总是已经意味着在其自身中以及来自其自身的东西，它们不可避免地是引用的，语言本质上是沟通（存在的语言），在其中每个字母遵循一个自然的声音，状态或性质。柏拉图在此制定了一个神话式的说法，后来成为充分性的原则，词语和事物之间的充分关系。

英另一个语言拜物教的例子，乃至另一个语言学的创始神话，随着从亚里士多德到哈贝马斯的实用主义传统而出现。虽然这种实用主义没有假定理性与自然（能指与存在）之间有任何天然的或实质性的联系，但它仍然假定语言的本质来自稳定的指称性和标准的交流形式。语言被定义为工具或器官，即使这个概念似乎将语言降格为它在交流中的使用价值，我们再次遇到在柏拉图在理想名称中的神话般的能指的专一性：能指，其自身，支撑了词语（象征的）和事物（实在的）之间的关系。语言里没有剩余；剩余来自其他地方，对于亚里士多德，其来自对语言的诡辩式滥用，对于维特根斯坦，其来自虚假的哲学问题。[65]

英对柏拉图和亚里士多德来说，这里的问题比语言问题更关键。同样的困境也存在于经济中，在紧缩和高利贷可见一斑：在其中，货币成为自己的目的，而为了增殖而增殖是唯一的经济需要。真正的问题是通过能指和价值的自动性对社会联系的变性，以及对“人类社群建基于稳定的社会关系上”这一观点的拒绝。我们如何界定语言和金钱的用处的好坏？我们如何在保证价值和意义的重叠的同时，防止另一种可能的重叠——价值与享乐之间的重叠（否定前者，有可能解除社会联系）？对柏拉图和亚里士多德来说，正确使用语言的范例不单是交流，而更是哲学，比如本体论的语言（如哲学家以及存在本身所说的）。在某种意义上，本体论将自己理解为存在的一个巨大的拟人化产物。因此，语言的理想功能以的最高形式发生，即对智慧的爱（philia），这也是一种友谊的形式，一种社会联系。存在的本体论语言根植于巴门第甸女神所宣称的公理：存在者存在，非存在者不存在，这使得没有否定性的语言成为主要的哲学理想之一。然而，正是这种否定性，是马克思和弗洛伊德在形而上学的另一端遇到的——在拜物教对异化和阉割的不承认中。

英与存在的语言和没有否定性的语言的理想相反，是诡辩家和诗人的语言，在其中，享受、诱惑和含糊性质疑了交流和外部参照的优先性。如果本体论的语言是存在的拟声词，那么诡辩的语言就是享乐的拟声词。能指不再是意义的承载者，而是享乐装置和欺骗的工具。它仍然是工具，但服务于其他用途。能指和所指之间所谓的天然联系被叫停，享乐侵入它们中间，揭示了能指和生产在语言中的自动性。在极端的情况下，这种享乐消解了对话和社会联系，导致了话语的自我废除，就像克拉特罗斯的情况一样，据说他放弃了所有的语言，而只是移动了他的食指。将语言变性为享乐装置理解诡辩家的“人形植物”，[66]但它也使他们说话只是为了说话的乐趣。在诡辩的形象中两个极端重合，一是纯粹的胡说，二是纯粹的沉默，对应着语言的生与死，乔伊斯和克拉特罗斯。

英理财学与金钱的关系正如诡辩术与语言的关系。它将金钱从社会功能中剥离，变成了淫秽的自我复制的实体。[67]交换从社会关系的隐喻变成了享乐的手段。买卖应该反映和实现社会关系的理念。但是诡辩者和高利贷者并不反映或模仿任何东西；在他们行为的背景下，既没有永恒的思想，也没有标准的结构。对语言和经济工具的功能是正常还是病理化的界定是不可能完成的，它需要为这种预设的关系建立幻想的基础。柏拉图和亚里士多德的尝试拒绝拓扑学问题，根据拓扑学，能指和享乐的边界在差异系统既是无处存在，又是无处不在。从对理财学和诡辩术的哲学谴责可以看出，哲学压抑的重点是语言中交流与生产之间的密切联系。为了建立语言（语言作为关于存在的语言）自我平衡的幻象的基础，柏拉图和亚里士多德制造了“理应享受的主体”的幻想。[68]然而，精神分析和对政治经济学批判揭示了能指和价值的自动性不应该被夸大——被假定的享乐的自我中心化和虚拟资本的自我中心化是拉康主义和马克思主义批判的优先目标。这个问题耸人听闻的戏剧性在于误解了能指和价值的自动性，而径直走向了对它们的直接崇拜。关键的问题仍然是交流和享乐之间的差异。如果交流意味着回答，这并不表明这种回答转而意味着一种理想的交际模式，在其上实用主义传统努力建立一种持续调节和稳定的社会关系的幻想。

英通过比较语言和国际象棋，索绪尔努力表明：差异系统只是暂时的，依赖于游戏的不会更改的正式规则。从一个共时性到另一个共时性的过程发生在每一步棋中，它建立了一个新的图形分布和新的关系，从而改变了它们的价值。然而，索绪尔保留了以下意见：英这个对比只有一个缺点：棋手想要带来一个转变，从而对系统施加行动，而语言却什么都不预设。语言的部件的转变（更恰当的说是修改）是自发而偶然的。为了让国际象棋游戏在每一点都像语言的运转，我们只好假设一个无意识或愚钝的棋手（玩家）。[69]英对索绪尔来说，无意识的目的不存在；目的只能与意识相关联，因此只与认知的主体有关。支撑国际象棋和语言的整体重叠的边界正是无意识，但随后就需要引入另一个主体性的形象。在这里，弗洛伊德的发现得到了充分重视。通过索绪尔回到弗洛伊德的唯一可能性，是《梦的解析》给出描绘了严格（在各种意义上）的国际象棋和语言的等价性，从而使能指自动性的含义变得激进。然而，通过预设一个无意识玩家，弗洛伊德彻底挫败了索绪尔，因为无意识在结构的概念中引入了一个巨大难题：它将能指、表征和生产的自动性的两个方面联系起来，以此命名结构关系的不稳定性。问题变得更加复杂，因为无意识在无意识欲望和梦的工作之间分裂了。后者包括所有操纵意识和前意识材料的机制，它与语言活动同源。但这些机制是为了产生满足的客体。弗洛伊德式的无意识玩家展现为一种冲突，这使得预设的目的出现在其不一致性中。为了说明这种分裂，弗洛伊德就提及了政治经济学：英白天的想法完全可以充当梦的企业家；但正如人们所说，有理想和主动性的企业家，若没有资本，什么也做不了；他需要一个能担负费用的资本家。而为梦提供精神预算的资本家总是（无论前一天的想法如何）来自无意识的愿望。[70]英在这段摘录中，弗洛伊德关注的是“无意识欲望”与“白天想法的残留”之间的关系，梦之工作被排除在比喻之外。但是，鉴于《梦的解析》中梦之工作的重要角色，我们可以试探性地声称，弗洛伊德在无意识中遭遇的东西，似乎与资本主义社会联系同源；它正是资本家和劳动者之间的那种矛盾。通过这种区分，弗洛伊德将意图与主体分离。无意识欲望和梦之工作是无主体的意图——我们可以回想一下，弗洛伊德将梦之工作定义为一个不思考、不计算、不判断的过程，简而言之是纯粹的意图。然而，无意识主体是一个无意图的主体，一个去中心化和转喻性的主体，它在语言价值和经济价值那里得到代表。为了预见后续的讨论，我们说，“无意图之主体”是在“被压抑的无意识倾向之能指（S1）”与“梦之工作的操作所发生的地方的所有其它能指（S2）”之间的差异中产生的。分析中主观转变的问题（problem of subjective transformation）需要——在无意图之主体和无主体之意图之间、在无意识的去中心化主体和同样去中心化的无意识劳动之间——建立一个短路。

英正是在这里，晚期拉康对索绪尔的批判的另一个关键方面进入了讨论，这次是关于记号的任意性。通过将能指和所指之间的关系定义为任意的，索绪尔超越了他前辈的语言拜物教。任意性的观念意味着在所指内部没有什么将其与构成能指的一系列声音联系起来。拉康第一次回归弗洛伊德通过将能指从索绪尔的记号中独立出来而激进化了索绪尔，从而揭示了语言的自动性内核。第二次回到弗洛伊德更进一步，在任意性中独立出其真正的逻辑模态——未得到索绪尔充分强调的偶然性：英没有能指能永恒地被生产。毫无疑问，比起任意性，索绪尔本可以用偶然性这一范畴来构想（这样更恰当）。能指拒绝了永恒的范畴，然而奇怪的是，永恒是本质上内在于能指的。这很明显：能指参与了无，采用柏拉图的方法，在这一基础上，某些完全原初之物从虚无中被创造出来，正如神创论所说的。[71]英偶然性是那种参与无的东西。我们可以立即注意到，这种对参与性的颠覆不仅对柏拉图主义，而且对基督教——“无中生有的创造”的宗教——都是一种丑闻。“参与无”引入了柏拉图和神创论的奇怪混合。一方面，它唤起了柏拉图关于现象参与永恒理念的教义。但这一教义的缺陷在于它的结论，即这些理念还参与了至善。柏拉图因此神秘化了“不可穿透的虚空”，[72]即切割的否定性，每一个能指都参与其中。另一方面，偶然性所提出的对参与性的定义用“从无中创造世界”的思想纠正了柏拉图的教义。当然，这并不意味着拉康简单地接受了神创论模型，因为神创论仍然将上帝理解为不仅仅是大他者，而且是“大他者的大他者”（创世的大他者）。因此，神创论无法真正思考创造行为激进的偶然性，后者自在地会推翻“大他者的大他者”的宗教假设，并使创造呈现为非-全的（没有在本体论上完全构成）。从偶然性的视角看，上帝无法是永恒的创世神，而只能跌落在被造物的效果这一边：“上帝是无意识”（《研讨班11》），“上帝完整概括了语言之效果”（《研讨班22》），最后是《研讨班20》中引入的新词dieure，它结合了上帝（dieu）和说（dire）。无神论和唯物主义都位于柏拉图主义和神创论之间。

英将偶然性作为一种“在无中的参与”的引入，是对能指自动性的一个推论，表明了对索绪尔认识论坐标的双重超越：英说能指是任意的，并不简单地意味着，它与其所指的效果没有任何关系，因为前者涉及滑入另一个指涉（reference）。在这种情况下，"指涉”这个词只能基于话语通过连接构成的东西来定位。如果能指本身不是指涉到一个话语，换言之，如果语言不是作为一种连接的运作方式或使用方式，那么能指就无法指涉任何东西。[73]英将能指定位为差异已经提供了社会连接的最小定义，前提是这个定义包含了主体：“能指是向主体提出另一个能指的东西”。能指的偶然性表明，语言运作的模式根本不必建立在这样的背景之上：它保证了语言内在稳定性和与外部参照的关系。没有看不见的手，没有与自然的关系，最后，也没有永恒的创造者——其可以为“无中生有”辩护。从历史上看，柏拉图从自然中解释“能指的创造”的尝试是合理的，因为对于希腊人来说，“无中生有的创造”是无法想象的。此外，“无中生有的创造”的激进性对于基督教来说也并非能完全想象，因为宗教仍然将创造行为归于一个预设的大他者的大他者，它支撑并保证了被创造的大他者（语言、现实）的一致性。无中生有的创造的偶然性——在非常严格的意义上——只有在现代科学的体系中才是可思考的，在其中，能指的自动性不仅被发现，而且被形式化。

英从无中创造出能指，包含着关于语言和社会现实的双重论点，在此我们谈论的是语言作为连接的使用。如果能指与所指没有关系，那么社会连接也不是建立在稳定的基础上，而是内在地断裂的：不存在社会关系。用马克思的语言重新翻译这个公理：一切历史都是阶级斗争的历史，阶级斗争的多样性表明，阶级斗争不是一个跨历史的本质，它不会统一历史运动，也不会使元历史成为世俗化的“大他者的大他者”。

英通过引入任意性，索绪尔只是部分地揭示了语言的内在不稳定性。正是出于这个原因，拉康第二次回归弗洛伊德的公理，“无意识即历史”和“无意识即政治”，也不能在不修改结构这一概念的情况下就与索绪尔的结构主义联系起来。结构主义语言学的使命在于通过结构与生命的对立来思考语言，而不涉及主体，而其对象是通过从语言中减去言语来构建的。通过这一操作，索绪尔将语言学建立在拉康在别处描述为“主体的压抑”的操作之上：语言的科学对待语言时，就好像没有主体会言说它一样。对于语言学来说，否定性不会言说，它的对象更像是一种非物质性存在之语言，没有身体的语言。相反，从能指到社会联系的转变必然意味着一种主体理论：英我们仍然需要在这里指出这个“连接”意味着什么。这个链接……是言说者之间的连接。你立刻就能明白我们的方向——当然，不是任何言说者；而是存在者，我们习惯上用它们来定性何为“活生生的”；而且，或许很难将生命维度从言说者那里排除。但我们立刻意识到，生命维度同时也引入了死亡的维度，从而产生了根本的符号学上的歧义性。[74]英话语不仅仅预设了活生生的身体，它还引入了死亡，随之引入了否定性。通过回到这种生命与否定性的话语性交织，“言说着的身体”与“被划杠的主体”的话语性交织，精神分析与政治经济学批判遭遇了能指自动性的逻辑联系——主体的表征和剩余的生产。

表征和生产

英在1968年之前，马克思并不是拉康教学中的主要参考。他的名字只是偶尔出现，即使出现，也主要与能指的主体相关。所有这些在随着五月风暴发生了变化，在其后的研讨班中，拉康阐述了《资本论》的客体与精神分析的客体之间的同源性。相应的研讨班的标题——“从大他者到小他者”——概述了拉康第二次回到弗洛伊德的潜在方向，即从大他者、语言领域和能指的绝对自动性，到小他者/客体小a/享乐的客体，同时也是与剩余价值在逻辑上相关联的客体。正如研讨班的标题所表明，重点从表征转移到了生产，为能指的理论引入了另一个层面。对表征的强调，仅通过象征的先验主义接近能指，在那里能指似乎被分离于享乐，并造成其禁令。[75]随后的方向逐渐放弃了这一立场，转向了一种能指的概念，即能指不仅仅被享乐所投资，而且能指成为了享乐的特定原因和特定装置。然而，因果关系预设了语言中的一种特定劳动。因此，拉康回到了弗洛伊德理论的革命核心，即他的无意识劳动理论，该理论通过心理过程中的“精神能量”（劳动力）的消费来解释无意识倾向的满足。

英从语言的大他者向享乐的他者的转变，与从索绪尔（表征的代表理论家），向马克思（生产的代表理论家）的转变相重叠。语言的大他者瑞金通过主体之匮乏和客体之剩余的视差来构想，这是话语性生产的两个方面。这不仅仅意味着在这一点上，拉康将重复老生常谈的“大他者不存在”。这一主张不应被轻视，尤其不应从庸俗无神论的角度解读（其宣布上帝是随着科学进步而必然被废除的幻觉）。拉康选择了一个更加严肃的方向：不光是后现代主义意味着更普遍地信仰宗教（从制度化的宗教到各种新时代的蒙昧主义），而且资本的逻辑也成功地推行了马克思通过拜物教概念构想的那种宗教成分。同时，拉康的预言——宗教战胜革命性科学和解放性政治——变成了现实。

英“大他者不存在”这一口号也包含了一个唯物主义教训，它将“大他者不存在”与“能指的因果性”联系起来，同时区分了语言的大他者（语言、话语）和神学及形而上学中的上帝（大他者的大他者）。[76]不存在（除权、非全性）并不妨碍大他者有着实在的后果，宗教的持存源于唯心主义的反击，这种反击致力于将“实在的后果”归因于一个积极的存在：“只要事物被说出来，上帝的假设就会继续存在”。[77]在拜物教的背景下，这意味着市场——作为不稳定和对抗性的价值空间的全球市场——不存在与资本主义抽象物的生命力假设是并行的。[78]这与拉康在金融化初期谈论宗教的胜利相呼应，那正是在美国人废除布雷顿森林体系、结束黄金标准并开启“自由浮动”货币的时代的前几年。宗教胜利在政治经济学中有一个具体的名字：新自由主义。它大胆假设对放松资本管制有利于释放其“创造性潜力”和内在目的论，即市场自发的均衡倾向。[79]

英在大他者理论中，精神分析必然承担了无神论和唯物主义的立场。向小他者的转变将这一立场扩展为与政治经济学批判的逻辑联盟：“我将用与马克思同源的观点推进，以便在今天引入我们需要定位的小客体a的基本功能。”[80]其术语的选择暗含了对弗洛伊德-马克思主义的批评，因为后者仍然停留在隐喻性或比喻性的框架内，没有彻底地将马克思对经济话语的批判和弗洛伊德对力比多经济的阐述——在逻辑上、认识论上乃至政治连续性上——专题化把握。拉康的论点是，“享乐的无意识生产”和“价值的社会生产”具有一致的逻辑，并显露出相同的结构性矛盾、张力和僵局：不是对性、本能和欲望的生产性潜力的压抑，而是的无法满足的生产需求，“为了生产而生产”（马克思语），在其中，被压抑的无意识倾向一直存在。

英其同源性应该是将精神分析的客体（如今被译作剩余享乐）置于话语结构中。这个翻译考据了马克思的剩余价值进行构思，拉康甚至提出了一个德语术语“剩余欲望（Mehrlust）” 。然而，享乐与剩余的结合并非拉康发明的，其在弗洛伊德的作品中已经存在。在弗洛伊德关于笑话的书中，他将无意识满足的分析集中在了他所谓的“快乐收获（Lustgewinn）”上。[81]因此，弗洛伊德已经使用了剩余客体的概念，但并没有在逻辑上和拓扑学上对其进行定位。精神分析随后的阶段抛弃了弗洛伊德洞见的革命性结果，而拉康的干预旨在赋予其与马克思的政治经济学关于剩余价值的争论的同等批判性地位： 英在某种意义上，我在发明了小客体a，就像你可以说马克思的话语发明了某物一样。这意味着什么？马克思发现了剩余价值。当然，这并不意味着在我的话语之前小客体a没有被切近，而是说对它的切近不够充分，正如在马克思的话语使剩余价值被严肃把握之前，剩余价值的定义是不充分的。[82]英因此，是发明而非发现；被发明的不是早在马克思和拉康之前已经被认识的客体，而是揭露客体之生产的隐藏逻辑的方法。在这里，我们再次遇到了唯物主义和逻辑不可分割的联系，因为这两种发明都包含了对话语的理解的转变。这种逻辑的和唯物主义的取向的根本在于：上述关于话语后果和物质原因的概念的争论，现在与能指相关联了。

英拉康明确表示，他所关注的是马克思和弗洛伊德之间逻辑的而非比喻的关系：“说同源性意味着他们的关系不是比喻性的。这是同一件事，也是同一种材料，就它是话语的剪切（trait de ciseau du discours）而言。”[83]这种法式表达直接暗示了《资本论》的第一章，其中商品交换和劳动的双重特性通过裁缝业被反复例证。重要的是具体劳动和抽象劳动之间关系的倒置，因为只有通过它，剩余价值在资本主义生产方式中的位置和功能才能被揭示。马克思对政治经济学进行了一项纠正：承认抽象劳动和具体劳动之间的裂隙的结构性功能，而其取决于商品的双重特性。通过商品形式的社会实现，交换的绝对自动性在主观和社会现实中带来了一系列后果。没有一次切割仅是具体劳动；相反，它是支撑资本主义劳动组织的更广泛的话语逻辑的一部分。这一行动包含了紧邻资本的核心抽象物，即商品在市场上被买卖是它自身生产的。通过这种方式，每一项具体劳动都被带有了导致商品双重特性的矛盾。但是在此，让我们后退几步。

英没有任何逻辑上的缺口能将精神分析的客体与马克思主义批评的客体分离开来，这两者通过物质性内涵联合起来：英如果你不提出比物质性内涵的更多要求的话，只有我的“语言作为无意识结构”的理论才能被认为内含于马克思主义之中……也就是说，不论我的语言理论中是否符合马克思主义，它都是真实的，并且对马克思主义来说是必需的，无论它给马克思主义留下了什么样的缺陷。内含马克思主义逻辑中的语言理论就说这么多。[84]英物质性内涵仅在真相内含了假的东西时才是假的。那就只剩几种选择了：要么马克思的理论是真的，这就意味着拉康的语言理论也是真的；要么马克思的理论是假的，不过仍意味着拉康的语言理论是真的；最后一种可能，马克思和拉康的理论都是假的，但即使在这种情况下，同源性仍然有效，物质性内涵保留了其真相。无论如何，政治经济学批判不仅在历史上，而且在逻辑上、认识论上和政治上都先于并影响了精神分析。

英提到“马克思主义”自然不等同于提到“马克思”。这个引用包含的比看起来更多，因为拉康后来提到了马克思主义在历史上所隐含的语言理论。背景是斯大林对苏联语言学争论的干预。在这场辩论中，他否认了马尔语言学说（苏联语言学家尼古拉·雅科夫列维奇·马尔的学说）的科学地位，后者将语言定义为上层建筑。马尔的理论指出，根基的每一个重大变化都将导致上层建筑的重大变化。这意味着苏联革命本应引入一种新语言，或者给苏联现存的多种语言中带来根本的变革。从经验上看，这自然是错误的且几乎不可能的。语言的发展独立于社会革命，斯大林干预了这场争论，宣布马尔的语言学理论是反马克思主义的，这场争论以他的指示“语言不是上层建筑”收尾。[85]索绪尔在他的讲座中也提出了类似的主张：语言学革命的不可能性源于一个事实：每个主体都个别地参与语言。这种个体化的参与阻止了社会革命给语言运作带来重大变化。然而，对于索绪尔来说，正是个体化参与意味着语言是不断变化的。重申，语言不是一种状态，而是一种运动：它不能被革命化，但其中仍然存在一种永恒革命——更恰当的说，一种持续的发展和非目的论的生成。这种永恒革命位于个体化参与的对立面，这并不意味着是主体有意识地或有目的地改变语言。[86]

英拉康还特别指出了他的语言理论的特征：“你至少可以同意我的语言理论是唯物主义的，这应该会使你感兴趣。能指是自我超越成语言的物质。”[87]这种唯物主义的批判性价值存在于“能指作为自我超越成语言的物质”这一表述里。这种物质当然不同寻常，因为它违背了对物质性的自发理解，但是，现代科学对物质的理解一贯是反直觉和反经验的。能指，以及随之的语言本身，表现为内在超越、物质性内部的扭曲。能指的因果关系因此并不在于这样的简单场景：其中能指从某种预设好的外部介入，而在于自我超越这一举动，通过它，一个自动的差异系统从物质性中浮现出来。

英拉康因此拒绝两种看似对立，却实为反唯物主义的论断：一种是约定论，它认为语言是文化产物（人类的约定，其唯一目的是交流）；另一种是神经语言学，它将语言放在大脑进化的更广阔背景中（在这种观点中，语言仍是一种交流的器官）。语言既不是约定也不是生物学进化的产物，因为这两种简化都忽略了能指的自动性，它是伴随语言产生的一个偶然但实在的结果，没有它，语言将无法被思考。这种自动性使得大脑或文化进化的看似自然或约定俗成的工具被去自然化。因此，语言是一种内在的外在性，是生物体中的异质身体。[88]它的“原子”——即能指——通过解开其与大脑物质性和交流的联系，成为一种原因。在这一点上，使用价值和交换价值的联系再次进入画面中，拉康对能指的唯物主义定义呼应了马克思对商品的描述，即商品是可感觉又超感觉的物，[89]其中有着同样的超越行为，即将物质性（商品）表达为语言（商品性），这是关键的。正如能指的超越产生了一个转喻的主体以及一个无法把握的享乐的客体，商品的超越将劳动转变为劳动力，并将剩余价值定位为资本主义社会联系中的特殊客体-原因。

英能指的唯物主义定义继续探讨了异化的争议性问题。唯心主义者必然会声称主体是构成性地未被异化的，而异化是次生的。同时，一旦我们从能指的优先性出发，异化就成为主体的构成性部分。能指在一个开放的差异系统的表达只能产生一个去中心化的主体性，而马克思在《资本论》第一章中的批判性举措在于区分了被构成的异化（拜物教）——这仍然涉及到对商品的“认知”误解——与构成性异化（作为劳动力的资本主义主体性的生产）。劳动力标志着能指之主体被资本主义占用，它按照商品的形式进行转换。也就是说：英价值代表包含在每个承载价值的客体中的劳动力的东西，但这种代表只在商品交换中实现（也就是说，为了另一个价值而代表）。但劳动力就是主体。这是马克思对主体的称呼。[90]英根据马克思的观点，他的唯物主义前辈，尤其是费尔巴哈，未能理论化异化与结构之间的逻辑联系。简单地颠倒上帝和人类之间的关系，或者宣称上帝是人类欲望的投射（正如弗洛伊德在他的宗教批判中所表述的）这并不足以构成唯物主义。马克思的唯物主义从将异化从想象性投射中摆脱出发，而将其与结构和逻辑相联系，典型例子就是商品语言和人类语言的歧义性。因此，唯物主义取向用对主体的指涉替代了对人类及其先验本质的指涉，这个主体不是自主的意识，而是自动的能指的实在产物。这是马克思《关于费尔巴哈的提纲》的核心观点，它在《资本论》中得到了实现：英迄今为止所有存在过的唯物主义（包括费尔巴哈的在内）的主要缺点是：事物、现实、感性，只是从客体或直观的形式去构想，而不是作为感性的人类活动、实践去主观构想。因此，和唯物主义相反，能动的方面被唯心主义抽象地发展了——当然，唯心主义是不知道实在的、感性的活动本身的……费尔巴哈把宗教本质归结为人类本质。但是，人的本质并不是单个人所固有的抽象物。在其现实性上，它是一切社会关系的总和。[91]英前批判的主体理论一直使用唯心主义的认知词汇（如沉思、意识），将先验的、中心化的主体性作为其首要的参照点，而政治经济学批判则从这个唯心主义主体被压抑的另一面出发：在每个话语行为中都运作着的异化主体。它是政治的逻辑主体。为了抵达它，话语也需要被设想为不仅仅是工具。因此，马克思对劳动的分析的目标不是简单地将活生生的劳动从吸血的资本中解放出来，而是要严格确定资本主义的实际主体——劳动力。对劳动力的废除将引发整个生产方式的结构性转变以及主体的转变，因为自动的差异系统的逻辑主体将因此与资本主义强加的商品形式分离。马克思确实设想了主体的解放，但不是从异化中解放（人道主义马克思主义者仍在坚持这一点），而是从商品形式虚假的普遍主义和其在价值体系中的抽象表征中解放出来。政治经济学以及基于其观念的资本主义政治观，将主体仅视为一种商品（因此是一个客体），而将资本的偏好和资产阶级的私人利益荣封为政治的特许主体。

英米尔纳提议将拉康在引用马克思时阐述的唯物主义取向称为“话语唯物主义”。这个表达可能会被误解为拉康试图构建某种后现代唯物主义：庸俗唯物主义和语言的述行性的结合。然而，这完全取决于我们如何理解拉康的“话语有其后果”这一主张。[92]如果我们在述行性理论的框架内解释这些它们，那么它们仍然停留在象征层面，确证着能指的自动性，从而仅仅涉及被语言学构建的现实的永恒改良。拉康对形式逻辑和数学的反复呼吁超越了述行主义的狭隘框架，揭露了语言中另一种类型的生产，其不仅仅是语言游戏和转喻意义的增殖。当涉及到表征的主体（劳动力/无意识的主体）和生产的客体（剩余价值/剩余享乐）时，这个问题最为明显：它们不仅仅是资本主义话语的述行性效果，而是在社会现实和活生生的身体中结构性因果关系的实在后果。

英拉康经常使用登月的例子来推导话语的后果。这一事件与其说“人类的一大步”，毋宁说与福柯所描述的“人之死”完全符合。真正的事件不是实际的登月，而是它仅属于话语可能性的领域这一事实：“科学话语能推导出登月。在这种登月中，思想成为实在之爆发的见证，凭借数学——使用的不外乎是一个语言装置”。[93]因此，登月是一个由话语生成的事件，这却丝毫不影响它的真实性。作为有其数学基础的事件，由登月所表明的实在的物质性，远远超出了登月的现实性（人类在月球上的经验性存在）。登月作为人类成就的表象掩盖了科学话语通过语言装置生成事件的能力。登月的构想之实现，不需要人类作为其核心推动者，但仍有着作为其效果的主体。在“人类的一大步”背后，是唯心主义式人类本质的最终抹除；这一事件再次说明了人类在资本主义宇宙中的实际地位：作为一个可量化的主体（劳动力），被科学与资本主义之间的通力协作所动员。这意味着人类再次被确证为其废料的地位，而不是一个崇高的类本质。

英当拉康提到马克思主义语言理论在历史部署和逻辑部署之间的不一致性时，他指出马克思主义未能认识到马克思关于商品语言以及使用价值与交换价值之间关系的倒置（交换行为虽抽象但仍具生产性）的观念，其早已超越了索绪尔的语言记号的双重性的规定。拉康对结构主义语言学的纠正——将能指从记号中独立出来，并引入主体——给出了马克思的批判中内含的唯物主义语言理论（在早期的引用片段中拉康两次写道：“我的语言理论”）。相应地，马克思的理论也对政治经济学的劳动的价值理论做了同样的纠正。只有将抽象的政治经济学的私人利益主体替换为作为劳动力的异化之主体，才能发展出批判性和唯物主义的价值理论。在这种情况下，马克思主义也退回到了马克思在其《关于费尔巴哈的提纲》中批评的唯心主义框架。唯心主义主体性的马克思主义式变体是无产阶级阶级意识，这也是元历史的先验主体的另一个版本。[94]马克思主义的一个重要部分（一处但绝非唯一的例外是阿尔都塞理论化的反人道主义）颠倒了马克思的逻辑，它从价值的自动性出发，以得到去中心化的主体性之生产。《资本论》是结构主义的，而不是经验主义或关于认知现实的，这在序言中就已经明确。马克思在序言中写道：英为了避免可能的误解，请允许我这么说：我绝非在用玫瑰色的画笔描绘资本家和地主。但在这里，个体只是作为经济范畴的人格化、特定阶级关系和利益的承载者时才被考虑。从我的立场（在其中，社会经济形态的发展被看作是自然历史的进程）出发，它比其他任何立场都更不可能让个体为那些他仍然是其产物的关系负责，——从社会角度讲——无论他主观上多么超越了它们。[95]英再次强调，马克思并不是打算将政治建立在对资本主义生产关系（它们的功效独立于意识）的认识的基础之上，而是将其建立于唯物主义的主体理论之上，后者将为真正的普遍主义提供基础，同时揭示商品形式的虚假普遍性抓住每个个体和社会整体的本质。拒绝认知的优先地位在以下著名的反转中更是可见一斑，在此，马克思对能指内涵的理解已经超越了索绪尔：英人们将劳动产品以价值的形式彼此联系起来，并不是因为他们把这些劳动产品仅仅看作是同质的人类劳动的物质外壳。实际情况恰恰相反：由于他们在交换中将不同的产品通过价值等同起来，他们也就把不同的劳动形式作为人类劳动等同起来。他们这样做时并没有意识到这一点，但他们确实这样做了。因此，价值并没有在其额头上打上自己的描述；相反地，它将每个产品转变为社会的象形文字。后来，人们试图解读这个象形文字，揭开他们自己的社会产品的秘密：因为有用物作为价值所具有的特征，正如语言一样，是人的社会产物。[96]英由于交换的存在，不同种类的劳动被凝聚成一个抽象物（尽管它仍是物质的）。差异系统转变了劳动，这同样影响了主体。因此，关键不在于解读社会象形文字的内涵，而是在它们的自动性中定位它们所标示的主体的位置。无论在文明中还是在沙漠中，一个象形文字总是意味着另一个象形文字，以及独立于与意识联系之主体。一个象形文字总是已经在社会中的，因为它的上述内涵，而并不因为其被具体的、有意识的个体所使用。

英提及社会象形文字，其实拜物教已经尝试了对它们解释，这种尝试使得商品宇宙的结构不为人知，而生产逻辑被神秘化。通过将具有积极和内在之质的价值归因于商品、货币和资本，拜物教化接近于诠释学解释（就像对柏拉图和海德格尔而言，存在是语言的内在特征，而不是其效果）。相反，唯物主义的解释强调了结构关系的自动性，并将拜物教解释追溯回商品形式的歧义性。斯拉沃热·齐泽克在多个场合提出，应该在“他们不知道，然而他们做了”的基础上补充“他们知道，然而他们做了”：结构关系的效果不受意识的影响，马克思的批判方法不设想对拜物教化的完全废除，而是设想将政治从经济抽象物的统治中脱离出来，这种统治已经因几十年的新自由主义而加强。政治的解放因此意味着与商品形式作为其唯一形式外壳的社会联系的根本性脱离。

英“他们不知道，然而他们做了”这一陈述似乎包含了“意识的知识”与“无意识的行动”之间的分裂，但实际上更根本的分裂存在于知识领域中：一方面是反思的知识，另一方面是未知的知识，后者在思考和行动中都存在。在此，马克思更是弗洛伊德的先驱，他表明废除资本主义抽象物的政治统治的必要前提是系统地将否定性重新引入政治。阶级斗争不是唯一带有政治色彩的能指——而无意识也是。将无意识在逻辑上刻印进政治是拉康同源性理论的中心工作。

英在引入两种剩余之间的同源性时，拉康表达了他的遗憾：没有更早地将马克思引入“他毕竟完全属于的领域”：或者在另一个场景中，“剩余价值（Mehrwert）是马克思的享乐（Marxlust），即马克思的剩余享乐”。[97]这种类似关系在1960年代末可能是显而易见的，但在小客体a的发明之前，这种引入不可能发生。在1968年，小客体a已经是拉康理论中的核心概念，而马克思已成为首要的参照，这有助于揭示“我们需要定位小客体a的基本功能的地方”：同源性立即扩展到同胚性。[98]两种剩余的逻辑同一性致力于定位无意识在社会联系中的具体存在模式，同时也解释了资本主义话语的无意识效果；资本主义对心理装置的殖民。在同源性中，主体性与社会的对立没有容身之地。弗洛伊德已经尝试将精神分析置于这一边界上，拉康的“话语”概念延续这个方向，描述了个体言语中表达的结构以及社会联系的结构。但拉康在一个重要方面与弗洛伊德不同。弗洛伊德的理论相当于原始父亲（享乐的原始主体）的神话，而拉康的基本教诲是不存在享乐的主体，就像在马克思那里不存在剩余价值的主体，除非人们将资本的表象拜物教化，将其视为增殖的生命主体，这在资本主义抽象物的发达形式中是如此，例如金融资本（在商品和货币这种更“直接的”层面上也同样如此）。

英通过回顾马克思与政治经济学最明显的批判性断裂，拉康引入了他对马克思的解读：英马克思从市场的功能出发。他的新颖之处在于他如何定位劳动。他没有说劳动是某种新事物，而是劳动被购买了，亦即存在一个劳动市场。这允许马克思展示他话语中的开创性元素，即所谓剩余价值。[99]英出发点不是政治经济学家的市场（其中所有商品和价值似乎都占据着同一水平，并在等价性中被废除），而是“劳动市场”，在其中劳动力是价值在每个商品中所代表的否定性的转喻常数，它暴露了商品形式和市场本身的悖论。重复一遍，主要的不一致性在于商品的双重性，它奠定了商品与生产商品的商品之间的区别，以及更普遍地，“劳动力在交换价值中的表征”与“在劳动力的消费中剩余价值的生产”之间的差距。政治经济学家将市场视为一个“巨大的商品集合”（马克思语），这是一个封闭系统，其动力学顺应自我调节和稳态的内在趋势。市场呈现出均质性，并建立在稳定和可预测的关系上。类似于之前讨论的索绪尔式比喻，其中只有价值以任意但仍然稳定和适当的方式与商品相关联。与这种田园诗般的情景形成鲜明对比是，市场首先且主要是劳动市场，这一解释揭示了政治经济学的大他者被矛盾所贯穿，因此是不一致的。在资本主义劳动转型的核心，有一个显而易见而影响深远的事实，即劳动力在市场上被买卖，它在其中表现为其它商品中的一种。去说马克思的新颖之处在于劳动的正确定位——而不仅仅是劳动价值理论，后者可能会将他批判性的干预错误地简化——再次论证了没有主体理论的唯物主义价值科学是不可能的，政治经济学劳动理论未能明确这一点。

英拉康将剩余价值和剩余享乐间的同源性建立在他对能指的重新定义：“能指是将主体呈现给另一个能指的东西”。认为这一表述的马克思版本是“价值将劳动力呈现给另一个价值”并不完全正确，因为它会绕过商品形式的双重性。因此，拉康得出了不同的结论。他的旧定义是“从马克思对经济现实的解读中借鉴而来，即交换价值的主体次于使用价值被呈现”。[100]将商品的双重性扩展到能指逻辑上，这意外地暴露了使用价值的模糊地位，其抽象面孔在劳动力消费中逐渐显现。其有用之处确实体现在其他商品的生产，但从资本的角度来看，它的消费旨在榨取剩余价值。[101]

英表征与生产之间的差距无法定位，因为它在劳动过程中既无处不在又无处可寻。没有任何量化行为可以划定这样的界限：使用价值的生产在此停止，剩余价值的生产在此开始（对应地，劳动在此被完全支付，而未支付的剩余劳动在此开始）。问题显然不在于劳动力的价值不够充分，或是劳动力的表征不够精准，而在于劳动力自身是结构性的不充分和不一致的。因此，表征与生产的链接，交换价值与使用价值的链接，意味着一个与单一的内外划分不同的拓扑学。表征与生产相交织的空间，是同时连续的和不连续的，具有莫比乌斯环的核心特征。这就是由同源性所导向的同胚性。

英使拓扑关系以及时间关系变得复杂的关键因素是资本自我增殖的倾向，这种倾向导致使用价值的生产与剩余价值的生产无法区分。马克思写道：英资本家以劳动力的日常价值购买了劳动力。劳动力的使用价值在整个工作日都属于他。由此，他获得了让工人为他工作一整天的权利。但是，怎么定义一个工作日？无论如何，它少于一个自然日。少了多少？资本家对这个极限点有自己的看法——工作日的必要极限。作为资本家，他只是资本的人格化，他的灵魂是资本的灵魂。而资本唯一的驱动力就是自我增殖的驱力——创造剩余价值，使其恒定部分（生产资料）吸收尽可能多的剩余劳动。[102]英资本的结构性趋势和规则将生产整体推向无目的性和不受控制的自动性。通过这个自动机，资本主义劳动组织中享乐的主要特征显现出来，即剩余客体并没有目的。[103]它不实现除了自我增殖驱力之外的其他倾向，以至于劳动的最终目的在于生产更多的劳动。

英拉康将能指翻译为经济现实。这重述了在《资本论》开篇章节中，马克思形式化了两种循环的矛盾。资本主义生产方式的结构在“商品-货币-商品”（C - M - C）和“货币-商品-货币”（M - C - M）的循环上呈现出内在的双重性。这种内在双重性带有“我们面对的是两种不同且独立的循环”之表象，其能被历史地或逻辑地解读，马克思似乎提出了这两种解读。根据历史性的解读，（C - M - C）循环（交换、销售和购买）是历史上最古老的形式，它在历史和逻辑上先于资本主义。更重要的是，它不包含资本主义生产方式的基础性倒错，即仅追求剩余价值的生产、利润的持续增长和资本的绝对自动性（M - M'）——这是虚拟资本的公式，它抛弃了生产借商品劳动力进行的中介。因此，资本主义的起源意味着兼有历史和逻辑的结构性转变，第一次和第二次循环之间的差异似乎概述了从封建主义到资本主义的历史性过渡。马克思在循环（M - C - M）中形式化了这一发展，他随之将其修正为（M - C - M'），其中（M' = M +ΔM，价值的增长），从而最终将剩余价值定位在社会连接中。拉康对能指的定义可以定位于两种循环之中，但在虚拟的无限循环（M - C - M'）中有着完全不同的后果。

英对第一种循环（C - M - C）的历史性解读不可避免地陷入了其唯心主义化的陷阱：对商品交换仍然是直接的、而社会现实没有被无情的利润驱动所腐蚀的美好旧时光的怀旧。将（C - M - C）循环前置于资本循环造成了对经济交换的幻想，仿佛它是社会关系的典型案例，以及另一个幻觉：这种交换曾经是稳态和受调控的，但被资本的不稳定性打乱了；幻想在过去的时候，货币仍然履行其社会功能——使用价值，后者支撑了经济交换，从而支撑了社会关系。马克思当然没有提倡这种过度简化的怀旧视角，因为他提醒我们，一般等价物的悖论已经困扰了亚里士多德。同时，这两种循环都涉及资本主义社会联系的内在不一致性。它们的逻辑式解读表明，马克思实际上分析了表象和结构之间的裂隙。（C - M - C）循环并非更直接的、被之后以利润为导向的（M - C - M'）循环所腐蚀的真实交换，而是（M - C - M'）循环的内在虚构。当然，我们不能武断宣称在资本主义中商品交换是无效的。它之所以有效，正是因为它掩盖了资本的循环，而中和了其直接的淫秽性和剥削倾向。根据逻辑式解读，第一种循环（销售和购买）涉及工人；而第二种循环（购买和销售——它们看起来对称）涉及资本家。当然，马克思形式化的全部批判点在于证明这两种循环是不对称的：工人所出售的与资本家所购买的不是同一个东西，换言之，出卖劳动力的价值与买到它带来的价值是不等的。当资本家购买劳动力时，他得到了同样的一揽子剩余价值：英我们用货币支付劳动，因为我们在市场上。我们根据其在市场上由交换价值作用所定义的真实价格来支付它。但作为劳动成果，其中有没有报酬的价值，因为这种成果的真实价格在于其使用价值。这种无偿劳动——尽管它在与资本主义话语运作下市场一致性相关的公平方式中得到了支付——是剩余价值。[104]英“我们用货币支付劳动”这句话看似稀松平常，但如果我们还记得马克思关于货币的最基本的教益，它就会展示其要点。由于我们面对的是两种不同的循环，货币就像任何其他商品一样，呈现出其双重性：一方面作为使用价值：对交换的物质支撑，所有交换商品表达的同一性的具体化身，另一方面作为资本：交换价值自动性和剩余客体的化身。货币最终揭示了使用价值的幻想性地位，而这对于资本主义机器的运作是必需的。货币除了支撑交换和具象化了价值的自动性外，没有任何使用价值。因此，它成为了至高无上的拜物教对象。但是，社会不平等再次揭示了交换的内在双重性，因为劳动者只将货币作为交换手段，也就是说，劳动力只能通过交换价值来代表。根据交换法则，劳动者得到了“公正”的报酬。然而，资本家将货币当做资本来使用，从这个角度来看，劳动力的使用价值不在于生产商品，而在于生产更多的价值。因此，资本家作为资本的人格化，作为其“私人利益”的社会管理者，倾向于延长工作日并减少生产使用价值所需的时间。劳动者被“公正”地地给予薪酬，但劳动的真相不在于假定的表征充分性，而在于结构性的裂隙，它既分隔又联系着表征与生产。

剩余与丧失的逻辑

英表征与生产之间的裂隙，无疑反映了社会联系内部的断裂，但它也具有一个结构性功能，这一功能的结果众所周知，即推动了资本主义社会关系（的发展）：“正是在这个裂隙中，所谓的剩余价值被生产并降临。主体与自身不一致，因而无法再享乐。所谓剩余享乐便丧失了。”[105]丧失之主体和剩余客体的双重生产伴随着这样一个表象：客体最初属于主体，只是在后来的阶段中丧失了。这种表象是资本主义抽象拜物教的否定性，导致了对工人地位的误解。精神分析对马克思拜物教批判的补充包含在剩余享乐（plus-de-jouir）的同音词中，它既意味着“更多的享乐”（more jouissance），也意味着“不再有享乐”（no more jouissance）。这一表述重申了弗洛伊德的核心论点：享乐不知道“适度”，其生产完全瓦解了稳态模型，后者是亚里士多德伦理学以及经济自由主义得以建立其经济和政治理论的基础。在利己主义者对个人利益的主观追求的和在渺小人类的自恋呈现出多样性的背后（对亚当·斯密以及其他自由主义经济学家来说，稳定的社会关系奇迹般地从中发展出来），存在结构性的丧失，它预先腐蚀了资本主义对幸福的追求及其幻想的“成功学故事”。与政治经济学相反，弗洛伊德将他对力比多经济学的元心理学诠释建立在对稳态模型的拒绝上。在《超越快乐原则》（1920）中，稳态的心理装置视角被彻底废除，其中死亡驱力的概念——作为力比多经济学内在不稳定性的标志——进入了视野。

英拉康在他的幻想公式（$◇a）中探讨了拜物教的两个方面。根据这个公式，拜物教化取决于给定的条件是从主体还是从客体的位置被观察到。在第一种情况下，结构性生成的表象表明主体和客体形成了兼容的两半，可以完美融合成一个整体。在第二种情况下，增殖的主体以资本本身显现，正如资本主义抽象物的拜物教化所表明的那样。无论哪种情况，主体的不一致性被视为是继发的，仿佛可以通过简单地“纠正”使主体进入实存的结构关系来废除。标准的社会民主剧情就是朝这个方向发展的：包括工人中更公正的利润分配，生产资料的集体所有制，金融投机的管制，以及将经济带回实体经济的坚实基础上。更激进的政治实验同样未能成功废除异化：“并不是因为在一个国家的社会主义层面上国有化了生产资料，就废除了剩余价值，如果我们不知道它是什么的话”[106]。国有化并没有造成必要的全球性结构变化，后者将废除劳动市场，从而废除将主体转变为“生产商品的商品”的结构性矛盾。劳动力与剩余价值之间的非关系仍然有效，国有化最终演变成国家资本主义的一种形式。然而，马克思并没有声称对剩余价值的占有会废除资本主义的异化和拜物教形式。这将意味着废除资本家——这些价值增殖的社会狂热分子和资本的人格化身——就能解决问题。马克思的观点毋宁是，资本主义可以在没有资本家的情况下存在，因为资本主义自我增殖的驱力是结构性的、系统的和自动的——但是没有无产阶级就不可能有资本主义[107]。

英异化的关键的唯物主义含义源于能指的自动性，并得出结论：异化就是结构。在不一致性和丧失之前，没有一致性和享乐，因此不存在任何主体的整全性被能指的介入所废除，也不存在直接接触享乐的途径被能指的介入所阻断。这样的立场确实会把精神分析置于对异化的对称理解之中，这与弗洛伊德早期关于性与文化之间关系的描述相呼应，并最终与弗洛伊德-马克思主义相呼应[108]。在马克思批评其前辈的人类本质这一唯心主义观念那里，一致性承担了相同的地位。相反，异化与结构间的等价性无疑表明，剩余的生产的另一面是匮乏的再生产——通过“匮乏”这一真正的“物质”，主体被建构。

英剩余价值和剩余享乐中的“多余”（plus）的歧义性使得拉康得出结论：资本主义的话语结构强加了对享乐的压抑，而不是对享乐的禁令。这种压抑使资本家得以成为现代主人。这个观点并非自明的，尤其是如果我们回想起马克思对原始积累的批判性结论：政治经济学的创世神话。这个神话中，资本家在历史上通过省吃俭用积累了第一笔财富，而无产阶级不加节制地享受，直到他只剩下劳动力。在这个过程中，无产阶级的整个生存被消解为一种无质的劳动，这玷污了他占有的存在。马克思以对自己有利的方式调整了这一异化的主要特征，而推翻了政治经济学的原始积累神话：在资本主义宇宙中，商品不仅仅是另一种私有财产，而是存在的特殊形式。因此，存在的本体论问题必然滞后于并受制于占有的前本体论问题，借此主体的匮乏和客体的剩余之间的不对称性突出了本体论问题的现代坐标。这种努力无疑贯穿了马克思在其《关于费尔巴哈的提纲》中对唯物主义的批判，并决定了其未来的导向。没有对政治经济学的批判是不带有隐含的唯物主义本体论的。

英但让我们回到劳动与享乐的压抑之间的联系。对拉康而言，这并非马克思和弗洛伊德关于劳动概念的真正创新之处。他们的关键贡献在于将这种压抑解释为由统治关系结构性地强加于主体的东西：英与黑格尔所声称/似乎声称的相反，从一开始就恰恰是这种压抑构建了主人，他非常清楚如何使之成为其权力的原则。这里的新意在于，存在一种话语能够表达这种压抑，并使之出现在我称之为剩余享乐的功能之中[109]。英政治经济学中关于压抑的概念在这里得到了更显著的纠正。主人并没有拒绝某种实体性享乐，而是在每个主体那里结构性地强加了压抑。“剩余享乐”中“多余”的歧义性再次昭示出其关键地位。剩余享乐并不是某种会超越另一种享乐的享乐（这意味着存在确定数量的享乐，而更多享乐可以加诸其上），与剩余享乐实际相对应的——由相同的话语性切割所产生的——是享乐的匮乏。因此，对享乐的压抑不仅仅包含了为了纯粹声誉而战斗（这是黑格尔尝试用以切近主奴辩证法的方式）。资本主义的统治关系建立在剩余的双重面貌上。生产与压抑并肩而行，“更多”与“足够了”携手并进：双重结构性命令——剩余的生产和通过压抑产生的匮乏——启动了否定的螺旋，在其中，生产出的剩余总是不够的。资本主义的主人总是要求更多，正如拉康给他的一个研讨班取的著名标题：“再来一次”。马克思则在所谓资本家禁欲理论中举例说明了这一命令：英但是，就他是人格化的资本而言，他的驱动力不是获取使用价值的享受，而是交换价值的获取和增加。他疯狂地致力于价值的增殖；因此他无情地迫使人类为了生产的生产……只有作为资本的化身，资本家才是值得尊敬的。作为这样的人，他与守财奴有一种共同的绝对驱动力，即自我增值（Bereicherungstrieb）。这在守财奴身上表现为个体的狂热，但在资本家那里则是社会机制的效果，他只是当中的一个齿轮[110]。英主人对享乐的压抑在守财奴和资本家之间的差异中，这涉及几个陷阱。最主要的一个是，与资本家相比，守财奴似乎成为了一个“理应享受的主体”。引用的段落给出了庸俗意义上的享受（enjoyment）与拉康的享乐（jouissance）之间概念差异的最好说明。在日常理解中，享受与消费联系在一起，这仍然预设了积极的质和具体的消费（使用价值）。相比之下，守财奴所展现的，不是堕落的享受或者其它东西，而是正应被称为享乐的东西。他不是将财富浪费在个人消费上，而是积累财富，小心地保护他的财富不受世界其他部分的侵犯，首先不受他自己挥霍欲的诱惑。在他的禁欲中，守财奴所做的远不止是简单地放弃消费中的某些即时享受。他对致富的驱力只有在财富的特殊化身（黄金和货币）从其社会流通中分离出来时才达到满足。他整个人因此变成了客体的人质[111]。

英在守财奴和资本家之间的差异中，有两点值得注意，这也揭示了为什么资本家是主人的形象，而守财奴仅仅是其滑稽的模仿。尽管守财奴是社会机制的结果，他的驱力仍然是以他主观的固着和迷恋的形式实现的。而在资本家那里，同样的驱力正是社会联系的结构性要素，是只对生产过程中的价值和享乐感兴趣的系统性命令。资本家抵达了守财奴的真相，并且能够成为守财奴所不能成为的：财富积累的系统性命令的人格化，在如今就是资本——一个不再仅仅包括积累，还包括生产、流通和个人消费的外在化的社会联系。资本家代表了驱力的全球化，其唯一的功能是支持和维护需求狂热的社会贯彻，这种需求可以化约为致富的驱力：价值的不断扩张，增殖的命令，伴随着生产资料的永恒革命以及迫使人口陷入动荡。所有这些都要求压抑、负债和生产匮乏，最终使资本家成为守财奴的翻转：“守财奴精神”的社会转型。守财奴可以说为了只有以财宝形式才可能直接切近享乐的幻觉，放弃了社会关系。因此，放高利贷在历史上一直受到道德谴责，守财奴被拜物教化为享乐的淫秽主体。守财奴诠释了马克思的评论：“一旦我们承认享受是动力之源，而非致富本身，那么资本主义在本质上已经被废除了”[112]。换句话说，守财奴并没有完全贯彻他的尝试，即将财宝从个人享受中分离出来。他将其与每个人（包括他自己）分离，但他并没有将通过这种分离产生的享乐把握为系统的享乐。对于守财奴来说，享乐承担了有限和经验的形式，而对于资本家来说，财宝越是永无止境就越是抽象：从黄金到纸币，从纸币再到虚拟资本，电子货币等等。守财奴计算客体的数目：他的财宝是具身化的。资本家只计数：他的财宝是那个数字。因此，拜物教从具体的物质性转移到了金融抽象物的幽灵般的物质性上。剩余越是变得抽象，它就越属于系统，而系统的淫秽性就越隐蔽。致富本身变成了被社会认可而令人钦佩的抽象概念。

英然而，这种致富包含了其必然的反面：剩余人口的生产。这是“人力资本”的真正意义。“更多”与“够了”之间的歧义设想了这种否定的社会生产：“剩余价值是欲望的成因——某些经济学已经将其作为原则：关于广泛而因此无法满足的享乐之匮乏的生产”；或者另一种变体：“我认为我在今年年初已经充分宣布，剩余享乐是与享乐不同的东西。剩余享乐回应的不是享乐，而是享乐的丧失”[113]。热力学第二定律解释了能量从高温区域流向低温区域的过程，进而引入了熵的概念，这提供了对力比多经济结构和社会经济结构洞察的认识论工具。这个概念已经支撑了马克思对从劳动力的消费中榨取剩余价值的分析[114]。同样的不对称性反映在更广泛的社会背景中：财富的积累伴随着苦难的积累，生产方式的革命关联着剩余人口的生产。资本主义的社会链接就像熵那样被结构起来。

英拉康通过能指的自动性来探讨热力学（能量学），并在熵中设想了一个实在的结构，这为我们理解社会矛盾提供了独特的洞见。在这种认识论解读中，能量被非物质化并且在本体论上被问题化：英能量不是一个实体，会随年份增长而改善或变坏；它是一个物理学家必须在他的计算中找到的数值常数，以便能进行工作……没有这个常数（仅仅是一系列计算的组合）……你就不再有物理学……系统在数学上闭合的条件甚至优先于它在物理是独立的假设[115]。英拉康实际上批评了弗洛伊德关于无意识的能量理论。该理论以为精神分析概念提供实证的科学基础为前提，最终却导向了对自然科学研究对象及弗洛伊德自身探索的实体主义解读。在弗洛伊德的成熟作品中，无意识和驱力确实获得了问题性的地位，开始用以指代一些实证的本体论实体。弗洛伊德不再通过话语因果性去解释它们，而是通过从原生动物到人类力比多的推测性系统发生学来解释。当拉康认真对待弗洛伊德关于语言的无意识本性的早期洞见时，他引导精神分析远离了实证主义和生物学主义。在上面的引文中，拉康将同样的批判性转向自然科学研究，声称他们的发现并非只与一个无关紧要的经验现实有关，而是质疑其本体论基础的稳固性和单义性。这种质疑只有在不再将话语与实在的关系归结为一致的理想条件下才是可能的，[116]在这种理想中（如拉康有时候所言），话语被认为没有任何后果。此外，拉康对现实和实在所作的区分，源于精神分析的结构主义解读向整个科学现代性中的延伸。简而言之，现实和实在之间的差异在于，现实仅仅指对人类观察者来说，实在显现的方式——现实充当了“实在的鬼脸”[117]。而实在（可以说是悖论地），代表了实在向话语自动性“显现”的方式，例如，向数学语言“显现”：英当能指被引入作为享乐装置时，我们不用惊讶于看到与熵相关的东西出现，因为正当我们开始将这个能指装置覆盖在物理世界上时，熵就被定义了[118]。英亚历山大·科伊尔的论点在此回响：现代科学不再像亚里士多德和中世纪科学那样解释经验世界，后者使用数学来“保存表象”[119]。当然，在物理学、精神分析或政治经济学批判中，实在不具有同样的含义。这些学科处理的是不同的现实秩序（物理的、主体的、社会的），而且处理不同版本的话语自动性（形式语言、能指、价值）。然而，将它们统一起来的是逻辑程序。根据这一程序，所有这些话语遭遇了实在，并形式化了相应的实在之结构（它可以用理论把握能量、享乐和剩余价值这样的客体）。另一种定位现实与实在之间差异的方式是，在现实中，蒙太奇或构建的过程是关键的，而实在要求表象的分解和消融。在科学话语中，实在是在这种分解达到底线后，形式化所要把握的剩余物，或者如拉康所说：英实在是在佯装得明晰的科学话语中，制造了一个洞的东西。科学话语在进步，而不关心这是否是在佯装。重要的是它的网络、它的网、它的格子，正如我们所说，让正确的洞在正确的地方出现。它唯一的参照是不可能性，它的推论就意味着这个不可能性。这个不可能性就是实在。我们可以就通过话语装置，在物理学中抵达某种实在，只要这个话语装置（严格地说），遇到了其一致性的极限[120]。英自然科学包含的辩证-思辨和反经验主义的内核，比实证主义认识论远更愿意承认这一点。实在的遭遇发生在话语面对自身的不一致性处，而非某个绝对的、实体性的经验性外部。遭遇实在的实际场所不是在实验中，而在于科学话语尝试解决、废除或减少认识论僵局这一过程的形式化和僵局中。对假设的验证已经是走向规范化的一步，是稳定和重建现实的一个时刻。正如拉康经常重复的，现实是运作的东西——这种运作是“主人”不断要求的——而实在是不运作的东西，它违背或扭曲自动重复和完美循环的话语机制[121]。这是从科伊尔对现代科学革命的解释中可以得出的主要教益之一[122]。因此，科学对实在的遭遇摒弃了将语言之外和语言之内的现实过于简单地区分。这个遭遇发生在话语之内，但却使话语脱节。通过将话语性推向极限（在此处，实在被铭刻入象征），科学暴露了语言的一个维度，在其中，语言卸除了其交流性的、有意义的实用功能。正是在这同一举动中，它摒弃了实在的实体化和象征的先验论，表明实在既非不可接近的“物自体”也非无关紧要的外部性；语言并不是没有围墙、无法逃离的监狱。

英精神分析和政治经济学批判的条件是这一认识论范式。无意识和阶级斗争——主体现实和社会现实中的两个实在的裂缝，在将话语的一致性推向极限时会遭遇。因此，拉康的评论结合了认识论和政治问题，将劳动力的科学发现与剩余价值的经济数学化联系起来，这消除了前现代的神秘化。在背景中，我们可以感知到另一种同源性的轮廓，这次是在科学和资本主义之间。拉康似乎因此接近了海德格尔的悲观视野，即科学被简化为其工具性和技术性的“本质”[123]。这种简化在海德格尔的争议观点达到顶点：科学不思考，它带有拜物教的印记。根据海德格尔的说法，现代科学在技术中的实现，完成了对存在（其对西方形而上学起决定作用）的遗忘的历史过程。随着抽象计算的全球化——这是非思考的典例，将科学和经济的无思想以及因此空洞的理性结合起来——存在本身的遗忘本身也陷入了遗忘：这就是海德格尔所说的“危机”[124]。在这个暗淡的场景中，只有诗意的思考才能呈现存在的本真、原始意义，并克服科学计算和资本主义抽象物的统治。否定的科学拜物教被肯定的诗歌拜物教所补充。而对于海德格尔来说，诗歌是存在之语言。

英然而，拉康从未采纳海德格尔“数学语言大战诗歌语言”的对抗性解读。他似乎支持的观念是，现代科学包含一个本体论丑闻，这个丑闻并不那么代表对存在之问题的遗忘，而是揭示了思考与存在之间、存在与实在之间不可逾越的鸿沟。形式化是思考与实在之间“相同性”的一个例证，但这种相同性的代价是思考从存在之中分离，紧随着思考的去中心化或异化。结构主义项目的激进化取代了存在之问题，转而考察能指的自动性如何使思考在存在中遭遇的不仅仅是存在，即既不是存在也不是非存在，而是“未意识到”的东西。[125]海德格尔从未将弗洛伊德对无意识的哲学重要发现主题化——这不是巧合，而是海德格尔所忽视的悖论性实体的典型例子。悖论性实体既非存在也非不存在，而是在压抑状态下坚持存在，作为“未意识到”在思考中的持存。无需惊讶，拉康在数学中找到了重新思考无意识的本体论地位以及其它与科学相关的实在后果的特殊对应物，从而做出了一个典型的反海德格尔式的举动。

英因此，对弗洛伊德认识论和政治定位的回归将重点从“科学是否思考？”转移到了“现代科学建基于哪种形式的思考？”对拉康而言，这并不是两难的；科学确实思考，并且它的思考挑战了经典哲学理想，即对思考的思考，挑战了以“思考与存在是一回事”为前提的本体论基础：英作为最适合科学话语的语言，数学是没有意识的科学，这是我们善良的老拉拍雷向我们承诺的。面对数学，哲学家只能保持愚蠢：放荡的科学在观察到这一点时感到兴奋，因为它看到了灵魂的毁灭。然而，神经症无疑存活了下来[126]。英现代科学基于自动性的能指，废除了中心化的思考的假设，而这一假设是哲学通过认知主体不断更新的。作为没有意识的科学（典型就是没有认知主体），数学将语言从交流中抽离，将实在从存在中抽离，将思考从它自身中抽离。马克思和弗洛伊德在他们对商品形式和无意识结构（这是两个去中心化思考的具体例子）的分析中重复了这些步骤。灵魂的废除是弗洛伊德关于神经症病因学的必要认识论条件，这是一种源于“能指作为享乐的物质原因”和“思考与存在之间裂隙的物质化”的因果性理论。然而，数学语言的颠覆性潜力正是在商品形式中遭遇其极限——商品形式建立在同样的话语自动性之上。而通过商品形式这个“后门”，资本主义对经济抽象物的拜物教化重新引入了灵魂的假设：商品灵魂以及资本的幽灵性——其能够激发现代宇宙（全球市场）的活力——成为思考的通用形式外壳，从而必然地将现代科学的所有颠覆性潜力导向到生产方式的永恒革命中。

英在后来的一个阶段，拉康区分了思考的科学和被客体化的科学，这立即涉及到它在资本主义框架内的歧义性[127]。这一区分并不一定意味着我们面对的是一种好的革命性科学，其揭露了传统和现代世界观的虚假特征（正如弗洛伊德所声称的那样）；以及一种坏的商品化的科学，它支持资本主义的持续和再生产。相反，这一区分强调了，思考的去中心化——没有意识的科学的革命性维度，与去中心化的具体形式的历史起源是不可分割的：商品形式。但它确实将科学定位为反资本主义斗争的中心领域之一。现代科学伴随着商品形式的认识论条件和绑定在资本主义抽象物上的拜物教化，它为诸如精神分析和政治经济学批判等批判性和冲突性科学的发明提供了必要的条件。

英在他对资本主义劳动转型的分析中，马克思已经遭遇了拉康称之为“物质还原”的本质性科学操作。将劳动浓缩为劳动力——位于市场的绝对化的起源——看似是一种简化了不同形式的具体劳动的生产性抽象，但实际上相当于主体的一个全新的物质性[128]。物质还原在每一次将能指网络置于任何给定现实（无论是物理的、社会的还是主体的）时都在起作用，它同时也关系到整个逻辑史，在其中，能指的自动性和物质性逐渐被独立出来：英物质还原意味着，逻辑在历史上的开端的确切日期，在于当有人懂得用单个字母替换掉语言中按其自然句法运作的某些元素时。这正是逻辑的开端[129]。英我们引入 A 和 B ，而不是说“如果这样那么那样”，似乎并没有带来任何戏剧性的后果。然而，亚里士多德式逻辑仅仅是能指自动性、将能指从属于字母的第一步，这与亚里士多德关于语言的“工具性”概念仍然一致。实际的颠覆发生在现代性中，这时全新的科学基础带来了不同的结果——能指的数学化，揭示了现实与实在之间的区别。这种发展的一个具体案例再次来自于市场的历史性转型——除了劳动的浓缩，它还包括了剩余客体的量化：英在历史的某个节点上，主人话语发生了变化。我们不打算费尽力气弄清楚这到底是因为路德、加尔文，还是热那亚周围、地中海，或任何其他地方的某个不知名的航运路线，因为重点是，在某一天开始，剩余享乐变得可以计算，它可以被计数并被总体化。这就是所谓的资本积累的开端[130]。英数学化向经济现实的扩展，剩余价值的攫取和劳动力的抽离，引发了主人话语的开创性变化。主人话语是一种包含能指逻辑和统治关系的话语结构。在探讨资本主义起源时，重要的是，像热那亚和威尼斯这样的贸易中心的具体转型已经嵌入到更广泛的科学革命运动中，这场革命的最终表现形式是形式化在社会生产领域中的贯彻。在此我们可以改述马克思：商人们并不知道他们在做什么，然而他们确实在做了。革命已经发生了，而早于任何撰写资本主义宣言的尝试之前：主体剩余和社会剩余——古人和基督教将其视为对预设的社会关系规范模型的偏差——早已参与了社会现实的建构。

英马克思的《资本论》提供了对这一认识论-政治革命的首次严谨思考，其涉及一个严格定义的结构概念：“结构因此就是实在。这通常由其向不可能的趋近所规定。正是在这方面，结构是实在的”[131]。在索绪尔的范式内，这样的概念是无法被构想的。然而一旦结构主义与马克思的唯物辩证法相结合，它就变得不可避免了[132]。拉康笔下的马克思是结构主义先驱，后者从话语生产的问题出发，使结构主义得以“再次脚踏实地”。随着唯物主义取向的加强，物质还原也不再仅仅是科学形式化和资本主义商品化的操作。它成为了批判的特殊工具，用于揭露现有生产体制中的僵局和矛盾。通过把握最显著决定了主体之构成的基本话语，政治经济学批判有效地证明了“数学逻辑对于你在实在中的实存是极为重要的，无论你知不知道这一点”[133]。显然，这对于指明政治需要介入的领域以实现主体和社会联系的双重转型至关重要。正是在这一点上，弗洛伊德关于无意识的概念最明确地延续了马克思批判的认识论-政治方向。

←→

CHAPTER 1

'The Unconscious Is Politics':

From Saussure to Marx

STRUCTURE AND HISTORY

中1963 marks a considerable shift in Lacan's teaching. It is the year of the infamous 'excommunication' from the International Psychoanalytic Association. In response Lacan created the Ecole freudienne de Paris, which was meant to make an important institutional and doctrinal break with the official guardians of the Freudian legacy. The school was founded with the objective of constituting an organism:中where a labour is to be accomplished - a labour, which, in the field opened up by Freud, renews its sharp razor of truth, - a labour, which accompanies the original praxis he introduced under the name of psychoanalysis in the task that it has in our world, - a labour, which, through a persistent critique, denounces the deviations and compromises that impede its progress by degrading its use.中Such a foundational act does not conceal its political dimension, which consists notably in the attempt to render the subversive political, philosophical and epistemological dimension of psychoanalysis. The deviations and compromises that traverse the history of psychoanalysis concern particularly the successful combination of its practice with the free market economy, a combination that Lacan already denounced on several other occasions. According to the famous anecdote, Freud supposedly said to Jung during their visit to the United States (1909) that Americans are not aware him and Jung were bringing them the plague. In turn, Freud in his enthusiasm remained ignorant for the fact that American capitalism already possessed an antidote against this continental disease. This antidote was nothing other than the ideology of economic liberalism. Freedom, equality, property and private interest, this efficient ideological junction of political universalities with private egoism, or ‘human narcissism’, as Freud would likely have put it, successfully neutralised the radicality of psychoanalytic insights into the nature of thinking, subjectivity and society. The price for the psychoanalytic success story in the land of opportunities was high and led to the oblivion of the critical truth that Freud revealed in his discovery of the unconscious, the interdependency of subjectivation and alienation.

中According to Lacan's founding act, the main task of the school was to open up the space where labour could finally become a process, in which critique and truth would intertwine. The labour in question is not merely theoretical but even more so the labour that Freud attributed to the unconscious. This form of labour comprises an inquiry into the processes that have determined the subject’s mode of existence and accompany it to the point of transformation. What matters for Lacan is ‘not a long list but determined workers’. He offers his return to Freud as an example of such labour, which may sound pretentious but in fact contains a rejection of any attempt that would want to ground the psychoanalytic institution on transference. The latter may hold the psychoanalytic community together but for the price of transforming it into a Church - hence Lacan's reference to the excommunication of Spinoza.

中There is one crucial reason why transference must be removed from the foundations of the school (and, homologically, from the party). By grounding the institution on the production of positive knowledge rather than on critical truth (the ‘sharp razor’), it displaces the accent from the subject of the unconscious to the subject of cognition. As we know, Lacan's institutional experiment later failed, and various subsequent formations all restored the more orthodox type of institutional politics. In 1980, the school would be ultimately dissolved as it had regressed back to the transference relation, even if Lacan had consistently rejected identification with the position of the master:中Fortunately, I never said I was the Freudian School. . . I do not take myself for the subject of knowledge. The proof lies in the fact . . that I invented the subject supposed to know, so that psychoanalysts would stop believing, I mean identifying with it.中The school not only strived to abolish the difference between Lacan and the analytic community, but even more so between the analysts and the analysands. When analysts are no longer identified with knowledge, they are deprived of their meta-position, which is always-already a position of domination. In this respect, the subject supposed to know is a critical invention, which offers deeper insight into the phenomenon of transference within and without the psychoanalytic context. Transference inevitably contains a moment of fetishisation, through which knowledge is projected onto the other and turned into an intrinsic and positive quality. In distinctive contrast to this scenario, Lacan maintained that, in relation to his audience and to the analytic community, he assumed the position of the analysand, where the opposite figure of knowledge and of the subject is at work: the unconscious and the subject of the signifier. Of course transference cannot be eliminated from this relation, which is why Lacan emphasised the importance of formalisation in the transmission of knowledge and truth. Only logics can successfully mediate in the opposition of two concurrent forms of transmission, the one grounded on philia, transference love, which would be the 'philosophical' transmission, still presupposing the figure of the master; and the other grounded on the autonomy of discourse(e. g. , the formal language of mathematics), which would ideally constitute a community that does not gravitate around a master-figure. The separation of transmission from the speakers position of enunciation prevents the analyst from identifying with the subject of knowledge and believing to possess some substantial knowledge of the unconscious. Transmission through formalisation abolishes the idea of a dogmatic corpus that all the members of the school should uncritically adopt. It designates a labour process, in which Lacan is one among many subjects of labour, a case of the determined worker, whose aim is not to produce knowledge but to support the 'transfer of labour'. Transmission enables determined workers to overcome the frames of their singular case and pass over to universality (community). A case becomes the point from which a universal can be constructed. Such a constructible universal is no pregiven abstraction that subsumes particular cases but a singular universal. It demands labour -hence the 'transfer of labour’, the intimate connection between labour, formalisation and transmission. We can observe more generally here the importance of what Freud already called Durcharbeiten, working through, in the analytic context.

中After the excommunication we can also speak of Lacan's second return to Freud. This return is marked by the change of theoretical alliances and, consequently, by a significant reinterpretation of previous teaching. The first return famously read Freud with structural linguistics and culminated in the claim that Freud’s theories anticipated the Saussurean and Jakobsonian theory of language. Metonymy and metaphor, the two central operations in language, are discovered in the way the unconscious processes manipulate the conscious and the preconscious material. The two linguistic operations translate into condensation and displacement, the main achievements of unconscious labour. The linguistic return to Freud became a synonym for Lacan’s structural psychoanalysis, and the most condensed formula of this early development, ‘The unconscious is structured like a language’, has since turned into a common doxa.

中After the excommunication, Lacan progressively elaborated an alternative reading of the Freudian discovery that found its new privileged alliance in Marx's critique of political economy. The move away from the linguistic paradigm was accomplished immediately after May'68, though these political events were not the only circumstance that contributed to the reorientation of the return to Freud. The move towards the critical paradigm was not unrelated to the limits of structuralism, notably in respect to the theorisation of unconscious production and the growing weight given to the problem of jouissance in Lacan's teaching.

中Nevertheless, Lacan's second return to Freud did not simply deny the importance of the structuralist isolation of the signifier:中With Saussure and the Prague linguistic circle linguistics is constituted on a cut, which is the bar placed between the signifier and the signified in order to expose the difference, on which the signifier is constituted in an absolute way, and through which it effectively obtains its autonomy.中Linguistic structuralism begins with the recognition of the autonomy of the signifier and with the minimalism of structure. Saussure starts from the bar between the signifier and the signified that enables him to isolate both constitutive components of the linguistic sign and expose the arbitrary nature of their relation. We can recall that the bar in question does not aim at the externalrelation between words and things but at the internal consistency of linguistic signs. It thus designates the absence of any substantial, essential or immanent link between the two components, which implies that the relation between the signifier (the series of sounds)and the signified(the associated mental representation)is actually a non-relation: an instable, shifting and groundless link. Saussure thereby exposes the structuring function of the bar and conceives the autonomy of the signifier, independent from its association to the signified and even more so from its relation to the referent, the element of external reality. The underlying thesis of this structural minimalism can also be formulated as follows: the structure is a cut. This reformulation takes into account one of the most famous Saussurean metaphors, where the process of structuration is interpreted as an intervention, which orders the undifferentiated and chaotic flux of sounds and mental images. What is crucial here is that the cut can be considered both a case of difference and something that lies in the very foundation of differentiation.

中The Saussurean signifier is thus constituted in an absolute and autonomous way as a difference to another signifier, and hence as difference in itself. The signifying chain, this most general and formal representation of linguistic structure, contains a repetition of the cut, thereby forming a chain of pure differences or negativities. The revolutionary character of structural linguistics lies in the fact that it no longer theorises language on the assumption of stable and univocal referentiality, be it external or internal, but rather through the cut, pointing towards a non-relation and instability between the two components of the sign. If an encounter between words and things, on the one hand, and between sounds and meanings, on the other, nevertheless takes place, it is inevitably contingent, in the sense that such an encounter always contains a failure and displacement, a distortion of referentiality. To repeat, the implicit thesis of structural linguistics is that language is a non-relation rather than relation, and Lacan’s accent on the autonomy of the signifier pushes this premise in the foreground.

中The bar between the signifier and the signified initiated an epistemological revolution in human sciences, because the structuralist paradigm disrupted the historical predominance of ‘Aristotelianism’ in linguistics and in philosophy of language. Before the emergence of structuralism, language was almost exclusively conceived in reference to Aristotle's notion of organon, which enabled the definition of language as a tool and an organ of communication and of social relation, an abstract convention between autonomous, rational and conscious subjects. Through the lenses of structural linguistics, language turns out to be a far more paradoxical and complex object, a system of differences that resists totalisation, and because it is untotalisable, it is both autonomous and inexistent - hence the Lacanian use of the very same bar that in Saussure separates the signifier from the signified, in order to designate the inexistence of the Other and the split of the subject.

中The psychoanalytic discovery of the unconscious stands in immediate continuity with the autonomy of the signifier. One can speak of the unconscious only under the condition that language constitutes an autonomous register serving more than mere communication and having material consequences that cannot be reduced to cognitive and neurobiological processes. The necessary predisposition for the discovery of the unconscious is thus the rejection of the linguistic Aristotelianism that nowadays lives on in the analytic philosophy of language, Chomsky’s linguistics and normative theories of communication such as Habermas's.

中In psychoanalysis, the autonomy of the signifier obtains a different expression. From the manifestations of the unconscious, which is precisely a concretisation of linguistic autonomy, one cannot eliminate the presence of the body, the site of discursive production that contains two aspects: the production of subjectivity and the production of jouissance. This association of language with production renews the old philosophical problematic of causality, which led Lacan to rank the signifier among material causes-an anti-Aristotelian move within an Aristotelian vocabulary. One crucial aspect of this structural causality was thematised already in the first return to Freud, which defined the subject of the unconscious as an inevitable effect of the signifier. But only the development of the theory of discourses in the late 1960s provided the framework for the whole nexus of problems that had preoccupied psychoanalysis since its beginnings, the issues of the autonomy of the signifier, the subject of the unconscious and jouissance. By recognising the causality of the signifier, Lacan decisively counteracted the pragmatic tradition, which saw in language an unproblematic immaterial and ineffective existence. For psychoanalysis, on the contrary, language is a material and effective inexistence.

中Here the main feature of psychoanalytic materialism can be detected. Language has real consequences only as a disclosed system of negativities (signifiers as pure differences) concretised in speech through which these negativities are inscribed in the living body. Lacan's second return to Freud will designate this disclosed structure of language with the notion of non-all, thereby proposing yet another translation of the Saussurean bar. And, as already mentioned, in the context of structural psychoanalysis the same bar designates the alienation of the subject and the inexistence of the Other. The barred subject that the signifier represents to another signifer and the barred Other, the open system of differences, both explicate the significance of the autonomy of the signifier. But this is also the point where the limit of classical structuralism begins to show.

中Lacan's second return to Freud is not unrelated to the shift that Jakobson introduced in relation to Saussure by extending the autonomy of the signifier to poetic language. In this way, Jakobson showed that the poetisation of the signifier (linguistic equivocity) should be thought in parallel with its formalisation and as an expression of its autonomy. Unlike Heidegger, for whom poetic language unveils the original ‘sense of being’, Jakobson accentuates in poetry the productive dimension of language, which needs to be situated beyond the relation between the signifier and the signified, in the relations between the signifiers. In this sense, Jakobson's poetics echoes Freud’s discovery of the libidinal investment of the signifier. Inspired by Jakobson's developments, Lacan defines the signifier as an apparatus of jouissance, although Jakobson's linguistics does not entirely support this definition, as it restricts discursive production to the equivocity of meaning.

中In his second return to Freud, Lacan did not produce any axiom that could match ‘The unconscious is structured as a language’, but its most fundamental point is nevertheless well encapsulated in an apparently enigmatic statement: ‘The unconscious is politics’. The formulation leaves no doubt that it should be read in pair with the first one. How to understand the shift from the structure of language to politics? Does Lacan simply oppose abstract structure and concrete experience? Not really. The second axiom strives to overcome the opposition of structure and politics, to which their opponents had pushed the representatives of structuralism. This abolition is most unambiguously expressed in Lacan's notorious intervention after Foucault's lecture, ‘What Is an Author?’ (1969). In his response, Lacan firmly rejects the claims that May ’68 negated structuralism, or at least his own notion of structure, which, at this point, significantly differed from the Saussurean system of differences:中Structuralist or not, I would like to remark that the field, which is unclearly marked by this move, does not seem to express the negation of the subject. What is addressed is the subject’s dependency, which is something completely different; and notably, at the level of the return to Freud, the subject’s dependency in relation to something truly elementary, what we tried to isolate with the expression ‘the signifier’ ... I do not think that it is in any way legitimate to write that structures do not descend into the street, for if the May events demonstrate anything, then [they demonstrate] precisely the descent of structures in the street. The fact that this was written at the very site where this descent took place, simply shows us something that is very often, and even most often immanent to what we call the act, namely that it misrecognises itself.中The idea of structures in the street shows that this key structuralist notion neither stands for an unproblematic and invariable system of differences nor designates the transcendentalism of the symbolic order. The descent of structure to the street is marked by an immanent break, contradiction and instability, which place the autonomy of the signifier in a different light. Lacan thus suggests that the possibility of a social change should be thought on this level because only rigorous structural analysis can explain why the revolutionary potential of the social movement, grounded on the alliance of students and workers, ended with a failure and instead contributed to the establishment of a ‘new spirit of capitalism’. The core of Lacan's polemic against the post-’68 critiques of structuralism concerns the notion of the subject. Various forms of subjectivity can certainly be thought, but there is one form that the social structures build on, and that is the subject that is caused by the autonomy of the discursive relations. It is on this basis that the given order determines the thinking and action, and it is also here that the subject comes to think and act against the established regime. The subject’s dependency can be exposed in the way the agents of May ’68 conceived their act, namely through a misunderstanding that is best seen in the graffiti: ‘Structures do not march on the streets’. The agents and the supporters of May '68 opposed structure and the event, or structure and politics, and herein lay one of their key failures. Instead of thinking the events as an outburst of the structural real, they were guided by the fantasy of a pure real outside structure, thereby overlooking the fact that the demanded liberalisation, for instance of education, initiated a more direct commodification of knowledge.

中For Lacan, the political events demonstrated the action of structure within the concrete actions of students; on the one hand, the antagonism between the determination of the subject through structural relations; on the other, the subject’s resistance to the impositions of the system. In this respect, May '68 was indeed an act. This was the case not only because a political subject manifested itself, but also because it contained a minimal shift between the place where the acting subjects - the revolutionary students - saw themselves and the place of their actions in the general transformation of the capitalist system. The descent of structure to the street thus formulates an unambiguous thesis on the link between politics, structure and the unconscious: structural paradoxes highlighted by the logic of the signifier are directly linked to the antagonisms that traverse the established social order. And if the unconscious can be associated with politics, i.e., if political acts contain the subject of the signifier as their internal negativity, then the Freudian concept does not signify a detached and private experience but, on the contrary, provides insight into the same structural dynamic that eventually led to the destabilisation of social links. In short, political events are realisations of structural contradictions and logical formations.

中‘The unconscious is politics’ contains a change in the notion of structure and suggests a specific understanding of the link between psychoanalysis and politics. It insists that the discovery of the unconscious entails a transformation of politics, although not in the sense that it reduces politics to unconscious complexes. Lacan leaves no doubt that ‘the unconscious is politics’ does not mean ‘politics is unconscious’. The latter would indeed imply a psychologisation of politics, its reduction to the content of unconscious complexes. The ‘is’ between unconscious and politics is not reflexive. It rather concerns the formal inclusion of the subject of the unconscious in the field of politics, which, notably after Marx's critique, thinks the constitution of social links through alienation and negativity. It is therefore not surprising that Lacan's second return to Freud was guided by the effort to elaborate a theory of discourses that demonstrated the logical dependence of unconscious mechanisms on the predominant social link. Consequently, the second return to Freud did not simply equate the unconscious with the structure of language but with the structural real, the intertwining of representation and production, the two faces of the causality of the signifier. Thereby Lacan problematises the transcendentalism of the symbolic order that had marked his earlier teaching as well as the entirety of classical structuralism.

中The new materialist orientation, which emphasises the real status of the unconscious, implies two seemingly opposite claims, that the structure of language is the condition of the unconscious and that the unconscious is not entirely reducible to the symbolic structure. Instead, it testifies to an ontological scandal that concerns the autonomy of the signifier as such, an autonomy that turns most real in the breakdown of structural consistency (e.g, traumatism in Freud). The more language withdraws from its relational aspect, the more its real effects become manifest. With this move, Lacan avoids the direct ontologisation and substantialisation of the unconscious, as well as its simple reduction to a single discursive structure, in the given case the capitalist discourse.

中The limits of linguistic structuralism are addressed in yet another reformulation of Lacan's classical axiom:中People make a false opposition between structure, which would be synchronic and therefore outside of history, and dialectic, which would be diachronic, sunken in time. But this is inaccurate. Take, in my book, the text entitled The Rome Discourse and you will be able to estimate the importance I ascribe to history, to the point that it appears to me coextensive with the register of the unconscious. The unconscious is history. The experienced [le vécu] is marked by a first historicity. All this is written, black on white, in my book.中‘Unconscious is history’ rejects two false oppositions: between structure and dialectics, and between unconscious and history. These oppositions are merely variations of a more fundamental opposition, which marked postwar continental philosophy, between structure and genesis. As mentioned earlier, this opposition needs to be substituted with a specific intertwining of structure and historicity, one that does not hide its dialectical pretensions. We can understand why this opposition makes little sense for psychoanalysis. The unconscious is situated in the intersection of synchronicity and diachronicity, which means that it constantly demonstrates transformations and instabilities, on the one hand, and temporary fixations, on the other, In this way the dichotomy of structure and history becomes entirely inoperative and meaningless. For Freud, every mental structure contains movement, in which a psychic conflict can be isolated. Consequently, his idea of structure comes down to this immanent dynamic and not to some ahistorical constellation of rigid relations. The minimum of structural stability can be located in the processes of condensation and displacement, which find their linguistic equivalent in metaphor and metonymy. But to repeat again, these two operations are unthinkable without their diachronic dimension, which introduces temporality in the picture. Diachrony is the necessary condition, which allows Freud to theorise condensation and displacement as specific achievements of unconscious labour.

中Freud provided probably the most passionate, although not unproblematic, vision of the intertwining of structure and history when he compared the unconscious with Rome. In Civilisation and Its Discontents we read that, unlike the actual Rome, whose history is present in the form of ruins and fragments that are impossible to reconstruct, the unconscious Eternal City is comparable to a hologram, in which everything remains intact: all buildings are preserved in all their historic stages, and all of the city's past is constantly present. The unconscious seems to know no time, as far as the essential part of temporality is corruption, change and forgetting, while from another perspective it is nothing but time: history pressing on the present and manifesting in disruptions of discourse, in lapses, dreams and jokes, in interruptions of the 'eternal present’, in which Marx and Engels recognised the most elementary operation of ideology. The main ideological achievement thus lies in the rejection of temporality, in declaring the end of history, in the false eternalisation of the dominating discourse.

中Freud was naturally aware of the limits of his metaphor, which more betrays his personal fascination with Rome than correctly determines the relation between structure and the temporality of the unconscious. There is another, more suitable discussion of their relation in an early writing on screen memories. There, Freud claims that human memory is not simply an archive of unchangeable data but a collection that is subjected to constant modifications. Far from being neutral, these changes express an irreducible conflict between heterogeneous psychic instances and their particular tendencies. What matters here is the conclusion that Freud draws from the way screen memories interpret other, presumably historically more accurate memories:中The falsified memory is the first that we become aware of: the raw material of memory-traces out of which it was forged remains unknown to us in its original form. The recognition of this fact must diminish the distinction we have drawn between screen memories and other memories derived from our childhood. It may indeed be questioned whether we have any memories at all from our childhood: memories relating to our childhood may be all that we possess. Our childhood memories show us our earliest years not as they were but as they appeared at the later periods when the memories were aroused. In these periods of arousal, the childhood memories did not, as people are accustomed to say, emerge; they were formed at that time. And a number of motives, with no concern for historical accuracy, had a part in forming them, as well as in the selection of the memories themselves.中The immediate lesson of this passage leaves no doubt: history does not exist, or, put differently, history is not an objective history of events, just as memory is no archive of neutral facts. Instead, Freud proposes to see it as a series of deformations, displacements, rewritings and, most importantly, conflicts, which nevertheless contain a minimum of structural relations that support the entire movement or simply are a structure in movement. History is structured as a language, and just like language it does not exist but nevertheless has material consequences for the subject.

中What Freud encountered in this representation of history is the retroactive causality, which will mark his subsequent conception of the historicity of the unconscious. Retroaction does more than merely modify the meaning of historical events from the viewpoint of the present. In a certain sense, this very retroactive modification constitutes the history and memories of the past. Retroactivity is envisaged as a form of causality and not as a distortion of objective facts. The formation of memories of early childhood, of the years in which a series of events that determined the subject’s subsequent development took place, plays the main role in the retroactive constitution and transformation of the subject's history.

中We can recall here the most famous example of this retroaction, the traumatic event that triggered illness in the case of the Wolf Man. The event did not simply take place 'objectively' somewhere in the patient's early childhood and repeat itself later in life. It was a real effect of retroactive structural causality, which associated a contingent occurrence or observation from the past with an anxiety dream, in which the patient saw wolves sitting on the tree in front of the family house and immovably staring at him through the bedroom window. Freud's interpretation of the dream content is not crucial here; what matters is the fact that he himself openly acknowledges that it is unimportant what actual event in the past triggered the illness - the retroactive causal link already provides the suficient formal interpretation of the event that has an equally traumatic effect to that which a concrete occurrence in reality could possibly have. Trauma is thus not a singular transcendental event, which stretches into the present, but a real effect of the temporal relation, through which the present retroactively alters the past, which, in turn, determines the present. For Freud, structure and history are inseparable, even the same, and the concept that overcomes their simple opposition is nothing other than retroactivity (Nachträglichkeit).

中In his interview for Le Figaro litteraire, Lacan evokes the following crucial passage from his Rome discourse, which addresses the relation between the unconscious and history: ‘The unconscious is the chapter of my history that is marked by a blank or occupied by a lie: it is the censored chapter. But the truth can be refound; most often it has already been written elsewhere’. First, the truth is written on the subject's body, as the materiality of alienation and of discursive production. The unconscious is marked by an antagonism and contradiction, whose witnesses are censorship and lie, these specific features of the Freudian unconscious, in comparison to others, which contain no structural conflict but most often merely a mental archive of unclear representations and archetypes. The entire originality of the Freudian method depends on the discovery of this conflictual reality in the unconscious:中For if the originality of the method derives from the means it foregoes, it is because the means that it reserves for itself suffice to constitute a domain whose limits define the relativity of its operations. Its means are those of speech, insofar as speech confers a meaning on the functions of the individual; its domain is that of concrete discourse qua field of the subject's transindividual reality; and its operations are those of history, insofar as history constitutes the emergence of truth in the real.中Freud establishes the link between truth, history and contradiction, thereby proposing, just as Marx and Hegel had before him, a conception of history in terms of the movement of contradiction that constitutes the subject in the discrepancy with consciousness. Freud attributes to this contradiction a real status, indicating that history not only contains a difference between reality (in the sense of factuality) and the real but also manifests the impossibility of their integral overlapping. The truth that emerges in the real is clearly not the relational and adequate truth of cognition but the conflictual truth of social relations, and therefore a political truth. The evocation of truth is crucial, as the significance of Marx’s critique for psychoanalysis will be associated with his invention of the social symptom as a specific truth-formation. It also indicates a notion of structure that is no longer Saussure's neutral system of differences without a subject.

SAUSSURE AND POLITICAL ECONOMY

中In his Course in General Linguistics, Saussure draws a strong analogy between linguistics and political economy. He justifies it by reminding the reader that both disciplines can be considered sciences of value. And though linguistic value is not the same as economic value, Saussure suggests that they share a common logical background. Value can only emerge from the difference between two signs. Where there is difference, there is value; the latter therefore can neither be grounded in the relation to the signified nor in the qualitative aspect of a commodity, its use-value. This isolation of value already reflects the absolute autonomy of the system of differences. With it, Saussure provided a strong foundation for the later structuralist readings of Marx. The signifier and exchange-value become indistinguishable.

中Yet an important complication emerges here, since for Marx commodity is not a simple notion. The first volume of Capital begins precisely by focusing on its complexity, which reveals an equivocity that has wide-reaching structural and social implications. The close examination of the commodity form shows that commodity, a seemingly unproblematic empirical object, is divided on use-value and exchange-value. This split within the commodity on the qualitative and the quantitative aspect is reflected in the split between qualities and form, or as Jean-Claude Milner rephrased it, between qualities without matter and matter without qualities. Milner's specification is intimately linked with the new conceptualisation of materiality in the universe of modern science, where matter no longer designates a positive substance, defined by a collection of empirical qualities (such as solidity, extension, consistency) but becomes a geometrised and subsequently mathematised abstraction. An element of matter is an abstract theoretical object isolated from empirical observation. The dematerialisation of matter, its progressive detachment from positive qualities, which still imply a relation of the object to the human observer, reaches its peak in quantum mechanics. But this is no place to go in a detailed account of this historical development. What is important here is that the scientific distinction between matter and empirical qualities leads directly to the non-empirical materiality of commodities and of the relations between commodities that Marx isolates in his analysis of commodity form.

中Let us continue with the split of the commodity that Saussure actually excludes from the linguistic science of values. Use-value and the empirical qualities of the products of labour may be of lesser importance, but this notion significantly supports Marx's account of the equivocity of commodities and the necessary illusions that result from their double character. Use-value makes every commodity appear as an object that can satisfy a need precisely through its qualities. This need does not necessarily precede a commodity but can also be fabricated together with the product. Consequently, every commodity is an articulation of use-value and exchange-value, no matter how abstract the produced object (services, websites, smartphone apps and so on). Commodity has to be tied at least to a fantasy of quality, which represents the minimal ground for the production of a corresponding need. The immediate conclusion is that the need is not some quasi-natural and non-symbolic tendency but already comprises symbolic mediation. Even if commodities are not produced with the aim of satisfying human needs but first and foremost to support exchange and stimulate consumption, one of the cornerstones of production of value, they have to maintain the fiction of usefulness and need, no matter how abstract, futile and fantasmatic. It is precisely the fantasy that supports the union of use-value and exchange-value, matter without qualities and qualities without matter, two heterogeneous and unrelated levels. The dimension of exchange and the circulation of commodities immediately imply that commodities lose the exclusive and seemingly univocal feature of addressing human needs (adequate relation between products and needs) and that another aspect of production steps into the foreground, the production of value, through which one finally enters the autonomy of the system of differences. Simultaneously, both exchange and the market turn commodity from a unique object into a mass product, thereby exposing a repetition, that cannot be associated with the dimension of use-value or, more precisely, that complicates the relation between the usefulness and the exchange.

中A commodity thus contains a double and not a single difference. Besides the split between use-value and exchange-value, there is also the difference that is exchange-value as such. Use-value manifests in the relation between commodity and consumption, making of the former both the sign of a need and the sign of a psychological subject, to whom the need can be attributed. Exchange-value, however, concerns the relation between commodities themselves and is apparently without a subject. Marx then shows that this is not the case because in the world of commodities there is one commodity that forms an exception: labour-power, the only commodity producing commodity. This exception means that exchange-value is not without any subject whatsoever but only without a subject of need (psychological or empirical subject). The labour theory of value that Marx adopts from his predecessors (Smith and Ricardo) now determines the subject of value and can be read as Marx's theory of the subject.

中The first lesson of Marx's science of value is thus already doubled: the difference between use-value and exchange-value uncovers the autonomy of value and defines value as difference to another value. At this point, Marx's critique of political economy seems to overlap with Saussure. Although this lesson implies an immediate corollary: exchange-value is not without a subject, but this subject is not the same as the subject of use-value (need). Exchange-value is not merely a vertical relation between value-signifier and commodity-signified but also a representation of the subject of exchange, which can be presupposed in all commodities and which Marx associates with labour-power. Saussure does not draw this conclusion, and in this respect Lacan's deduction of the subject from the logic of the signifier already in the first return to Freud exceeded the strict epistemological frames of structural linguistics.

中The science of value thus begins already at the level of the non-symbolic use-value that seemingly precedes exchange. Marx's critique starts from the political-economic idea of Warenkunde, expertise-knowledge of commodities, and the science of values is supposed to form a subset of this discipline. ‘In bourgeois society’, Marx writes in a footnote, ‘the legal fiction prevails that each person, as a buyer, has an encyclopaedic knowledge of commodities’. Everyone enters the market with a presupposed knowledge, precisely as homo oeconomicus, who presumably possesses spontaneous knowledge of his/her private interests, and above all as a value-scientist. For Marx, this presupposition is built on shaky ground, because it treats everyone as subjects of cognition. The presupposed knowledge of economic subjects is first tested in the way people relate to commodities, in commodity fetishism, where Marx again shows that the difference between use-value and exchange-value implies two incompatible and heterogeneous subjects, of which one is the centralised subject of need, interest and positive knowledge, and the other the decentralised and non-psychological subject of value. But what matters for now is that, whether we speak of linguistic or economic values, linguistic exchange or economic exchange, knowledge is already presupposed for the subject. This knowledge is not necessarily reflected but is most certainly at work in the way commodities and values relate to one other, and also in the way everyone relates to commodities, in the action of structure as well as in the actions of men.

中Linguistics and political economy enter these relations between values and commodities, between signifiers and signified, where they first encounter the double character of their values. An additional factor complicates the matter for both sciences of values. Saussure notes that linguistics and political economy are internally doubled, not because the notion of value contains a qualitative and a quantitative dimension but because the quantitative dimension marks their scientific object with temporality. History re-enters the structure. The field of value is stained with constant change that makes values vary over time. The oscillation of value reveals 'inflation' in the Other, a structural dynamic and instability in the system. In order to illustrate this point, Saussure first gives examples of sciences in which time does not cause particular complications in the structure of their field and of their object. Such is the case with astronomy, which investigates changes in the composition of stars, whereby the temporality of these changes does not call for an inner differentiation of astronomy as such; the same goes for geology, which explores different geological epochs but can easily switch to the description of unchangeable states. The temporal shift does not alter the object of research and the laws behind the changes are considered stable.

中All these conditions of scientificity change in the framework of linguistics and political economy, where the object transforms depending on whether we think it within or without temporality, meaning also within or without the relation to the subject. Political economy and economic history form two separate disciplines within one science, and the same goes for static linguistics and evolutionary linguistics. This already indicates that linguistic and economic models do not have universal validity. They are always-already historically and geographically limited, something that critical economists will willingly admit. This limitation of economic models is closely related to the instability of the market, the same structural instability that marks the field of language, a feature on which Lacan will build his theory of the barred Other.

中As previously mentioned, the immanent split in both sciences of value is caused by the temporal factor that is associated with the social dimension of exchange: ‘Both sciences are concerned with a system for equating things of different orders - labour and wages in one and a signified and signifier in the other.’ The parallelism does not stop here. Just as political economy handles the difference between exchange-value and use-value, Saussure introduces an analogical difference between linguistic value and meaning. Meaning still presupposes a relation between speakers, whereas linguistic value implies an autonomous relation between signifiers themselves. Value relations go unbeknownst to the speaker and to the production of meaning, and in order to attain this level of language linguistics needs to abstract language from speech. Saussure summarises this gesture in the famous thesis that the object of linguistics, la langue, is le langage (language) minus la parole (speech). Only once this operation has been made can language appear as an abstract system of differences. To say that in language there are only differences means that what we normally experience as language contains two heterogeneous aspects and even two different languages, the language of values and the language of meaning. When humans communicate among themselves they unknowingly speak the language of values, a language that does not communicate meaning, and the question is whether it communicates at all. The autonomy of the signifier stands for a noncommunicative kernel of linguistic communication.

中Let us return to Saussure's example, which serves to illustrate the coincidence of linguistic and economic value. Saussure claims that from the perspective of value the relation of labour to wage is homological to the relation between the signified and the signifier. At this point, we can already note that Saussure was not exactly fortunate in his choice of example. He overlooked the problematic character of this comparison, as he did not refer to just any economic relation but to the most problematic commodity exchange that puts the entirety of political economy into question. He thus chose an example that, for Marx, reveals the symptomatic status of labour-power in the commodity universe and in economic exchange. Saussure's analogy repeats the same mistake that Marx criticised in classical political economy: what is bought and sold on the market is not a process (labour) but a specific commodity (labour-power). But let us take a few steps back here.

中Because temporality cannot be entirely eliminated from the field of value, the system of equivalences can take two directions. The equation can concern things here and now, as well as things in temporal succession. If it concerns the present state of things, it pictures the market as a static constellation of actually existing commodities; we are, then, dealing with political economy as the grammar of market relations. If, however, the equation relates to the temporal succession of things, it comprises not only exchange but also production and relations of production. Or, to link it back to Saussure's formula, temporality reintroduces speech into language. Here, the split produced by the notion of value finally receives its full weight. Saussure illustrates it with the intersection of two axes: the axis of simultaneity, which designates the relations between coexisting things and from which the dimension of time is excluded; and the axis of succession, 'on which only one thing can be considered at a time but upon which all the things on the first axis together with their changes are located’. In linguistics, this distinction is absolute and imperative, for ‘language is a system of pure values, which are determined by nothing except the momentary arrangement of its terms’. This distinction is therefore necessary in a field that has no external determination or from which it is impossible to extricate oneself. Language and the market are two fields that know no Outside. Because of this absoluteness, discussion of them is only possible by splitting them into their temporal and atemporal aspects. Value can become a scientific object only if language and market are separated from their temporality, for this temporality reveals that their structure is more paradoxical than it may appear. Because they have no exteriority, they are not whole. Because they are not whole, they are internally barred. And, consequently, because they are barred, they do not know positive existence. The Other (Language, Market) does not exist. For linguistics, it is necessary to construct its object, language, by separating it from temporality, but, simultaneously, this separation excludes the problematic existence of language that follows directly from the negativity of the signifier. Similarly, political economy has to construct the field of its object, the market, which is presupposed in its positive existence, that is, as a fully constituted and homeostatic order that follows stable laws and whose functioning is more or less predictable and translatable into mathematical language. Adam Smith's ‘invisible hand of the market’ brings together both features, whereby the persistence of this originary metaphor in contemporary economic debates testifies that the hypothesis of the Other's existence is aliveand well. To the economic Other we send positive signals, in the form of reforms and austerity measures that should calm its instable and capricious character. For linguistics and for political economy, the Other does exist, at least as the idea of a logically predictable and self-regulating system of values.

中The structural and logical overlapping of commodity exchange and language, value and signifier, also stands at the very unfolding of the critique of political economy. In the section on commodity fetishism, which concludes the first chapter of Capital, Marx addresses the cognitive consequences of the autonomy of exchange-value through the idea of commodity language. He demonstrates this language at work in the well-known prosopopoeia of commodities: 中If commodities could speak, they would say this: our use-value may interest men, but does not belong to us as objects. What does belong to us as objects, however, is our value. Our own intercourse as commodities proves it. We relate to each other merely as exchange-values.中From the double character of commodities it seemingly follows that language is situated in exchange-value, while use-value stands outside language. The critical axis of the idea of commodity language, by contrast, consists in the fact that it places the couple of use-value and exchange-value in language, thereby determining the relation between two linguistic levels, human language and commodity language, communication and autonomous difference, or, to put it with Saussure, meaning and value. Besides structurally linking exchange and language, Marx also situates the specific structural effect of the commodity split, which immediately follows from the primacy of exchange-value over use-value: the seemingly intrinsic character of value. After commodities have said their piece, Marx leaves the word to political economists, where it turns out that economists are actually not the ones who speak but, rather, it is commodities, which continue their parole through the mouths of political economists and the theories of political economy:中Now listen how those commodities speak through the mouth of the economist. ‘Value’ (i.e., exchange-value) is a property of things, riches (i.e., use-value) of man. Value, in this sense, necessarily implies exchanges, riches do not’. ‘Riches (use-value) are the attribute of men, value is the attribute of commodities. A man or a community is rich, a pearl or a diamond is valuable ... A pearl or a diamond is valuable as a pearl or a diamond’.中A strange ventriloquism is at stake in political economy. Marx unveils that there is an immediate continuity, equivocity, inseparability between commodity language and human language. He quotes the British utilitarian philosopher and economist Samuel Bailey, whose words demonstrate that the commodity language is not to be taken as a metaphor; the prosopopoeia of commodities does not assume the status of a rhetorical fiction but simply is language in action. Ca parle: it, the commodity, speaks. Commodity language turns out to be a pleonasm, for the economists simply repeat the appearance that is produced by the autonomy of exchange. The appearance of value being intrinsic to commodities is thus a logical consequence of the autonomy of exchange-value and demonstrates the structural overlapping of commodity language, the way commodities communicate among themselves through values, and human language, the way signifiers relate to one another behind human communication. When Marx speaks of commodity fetishism, he does not envisage some ‘generalised perversion’ but a minimal shift between the appearance and the logical autonomy of value.

中The inseparability of human language and commodity language anticipates an important Lacanian axiom, ‘There is no such thing as a metalanguage’, or, put differently, there is no criterion that would delimit the autonomy of the system of differences, which implies the primacy of the relation between signifiers over their relation to the signified, and thereby over the communicative and referential dimension of language. Language is not univocity but equivocity, not a relation but the paradigmatic example of non-relation. And because there is no such thing as metalanguage, there is no language either. The linguistic and the economic system form an open set. Consequently, the inexistence of a metalanguage (the Other of the Other) and the inexistence of the Other are one and the same.

中From the equivocity and the inseparability of human language and commodity language and from the structural overlapping of economic and linguistic value, which is the signifier as difference or relation to another signifier, Marx deduces the constitution of subjectivity that is coded under the expression ‘commodity fetishism’, a subjectivity that is marked by a structurally determined misunderstanding. Thus, Marx accentuates the difference between the speaker and the subject, between the subject implied by use-value (the psychological and empirical subject of cognition) and the subject of exchange-value, whose place is in the autonomy of the system of differences and which is therefore decentralised and metonymic. Marx's analysis of commodity fetishism thus contains two elements, the signifier-as-cause and the alienated subject, the material consequence of the autonomy of value. To reiterate, the idea of a commodity language implies that commodity exchange is structured like a language. This openly linguistic meaning of Marx's critique of fetishism was apparent for Lacan, who detected the affinity of the critique of political economy with structuralism already in his early teaching, anticipating Althusser's structural Marxism:中It is enough to open the first volume of Capital in order to become aware that the first step of Marx's analysis of the fetish character of commodity consists precisely in the fact that he addresses the problem on the level of the signifer as such, even if the term itself remains unpronounced.中Marx starts from the autonomy of exchange in order to deduce the specific form of subjectivity that this autonomy inevitably produces. This deduction demonstrates the dependency of the subject on the signifier: the system of differences, commodity exchange, the way in which commodities communicate among themselves, shapes the subject independently from every reference to the consumer. This hidden aspect of subjectivation is then exemplified in commodity fetishism, the political-economic mystification of the source of value, which strives to hold apart both flip sides of structural causality: production of (surplus) value and production of (alienated) subjectivity. According to the fetishist position commodities are endowed with intrinsic value, although this misunderstanding is objective and not subjective. The autonomy of the system of differences necessarily produces the appearance that value is a positive quality of things and that it is without a subject, or, better, that it is its own subject. Commodity fetishism consequently evolves into the fetishisation of capital, in which financial abstractions seemingly engender each other independently from any negative subject of value. Capital becomes the privileged description for a spectral life without negativity. The case of Samuel Bailey is merely an exemplification of how each individual spontaneously relates to commodities. In each consumer there is a political economist, the presupposed subject of cognition, for which one assumes an encyclopaedic knowledge of commodities - homo oeconomicus, this ideal subject of the economic science of value. In the end, the hypothesis of this ideal subjectivity makes political economy blind for the structurally generated fetishisations -and the task of critique, as Marx repeatedly demonstrates, is precisely to think the production of value together with the production of fantasies of production of value. Differently put, political economy still engages in the quest for the origin of value, in relation to which it can only produce more or less scientific myths. Critique of political economy, in contrast, abolishes this quest and focuses instead on the interdependency of exploitation and fetishisation.

中The speech of commodities comes suspiciously close to the way Saussure treats the signs that compose language, without the reference to temporality. This does not mean that Saussure's relation to language is fetishist, but it does mean that by (unknowingly) repeating the political-economic lapsus, he restricts linguistics to the register of exchange, leaving the connection between linguistic representation and linguistic production unthematised. By failing to envisage the difference between labour-process and labour-power, as well as between labour-power and other commodities, Saussure situates production outside the science of language. For him, language knows no surplus and the use of language remains throughout communicative and meaningful. This will eventually become the central point of Lacan's critique of Saussure:中Communication implies reference. But one thing is clear - language is merely what scientific discourse elaborates to account for what I call lalangue. Language serves purposes that are altogether different from that of communication . . . If communication approaches what is effectively at work in the jouissance of lalanguage, it is because communication implies a reply, in other words, dialogue. But does lalanguage serve, first and foremost, to dialogue? As I have said before, nothing is less certain.中Saussure is affirmed and negated in one and the same gesture. The autonomy of the signifer as such implies a restriction of the communicative dimension of language, and hence of the linguistic use-value (meaning, relation to the signified). What Lacan here describes as lalanguage is already the result ofa shift from Saussure to Marx. The distinction between language and lalanguage now covers the difference between linguistic meaning and the autonomy of the signifier. Lalangue stands entirely on the side of this autonomy, negating the primacy of communication and relationality (dialogue). The signifier appears here first and foremost an apparatus of jouissance. The autonomy in question, the kernel of Saussure's discovery, provides the necessary ground for the passage from language to lalanguage, but this cannot take place without introducing the subject and the surplus-object. Lacan's second return to Freud thus ends up extending the autonomy of the signifier to the Marxist problematic of the mode of production.

中In Saussure, the introduction of synchronicity and diachronicity articulated the split within linguistics(static linguistics and evolutionary linguistics) and within its object. Language is both state and movement. Linguistics confronts here an impossible dilemma: if it aims at the static, atemporal aspect of language, it loses an important aspect of its object, the production of linguistic value; and if it focuses on temporality, it has to admit that language does not exist, meaning that it deals with an unstable and paradoxical object. In the first case, linguistics becomes a ‘pondering of knowledge on lalanguage’, whereby language turns out to be a scientific fiction, a construct of linguistic knowledge; in the second case; linguistics cannot fully account for communication since the unity of language (lalangue) dissolves in the multiplicity of ‘private’ languages (lalangue). This dichotomy of language and speech is what Lacan criticised in Saussurean linguistics and instead strived to construct a linguistics, renamed linguisterie, that would take language ‘more seriously’, considering the ‘life’ of language, its temporal as well as causal dimension. Lacan here seems to be in accord with Deleuze's later remark that linguistics has done a lot of harm’, notably when it separated language from production, not seeing that it was an essential aspect of the autonomy of the signifier. One cannot have language without its inherent instability. The same critical position directs Marx's relation to political economy.

中Political economy, too, reveals its insuficiency because it cannot account for the production of value without the implicit fetishisation of commodities, money and capital - another pondering of knowledge, which ascribes value to commodities, to money and, at the most abstract level, to the immediate productivity of fictitious capital. Geld heckendes Geld, money-breeding money, as Marx writes, is the main fetishist fantasy that emerges from the autonomy of value, and it is therefore not a surprise that this fantasy of self-engendering stands in the core of all capitalist fetishisms and becomes a driving force of financialisation. This financial vitalism can only be supported on the basis of the foreclosure of negativity, of the split that marks the subject of value and through it the entire commodity universe. However, the critical point is not simply to reintroduce production into language but to expose its double aspect, the mutual dependency of production of the negative subject and the primitive surplus-object.

中Saussure nevertheless tried to theorise the temporal and the atemporal aspect of language when he compared the inscription of language in the intersection of synchronicity and diachronicity with a chess game. This comparison combines the static and the dynamic dimension of language, showing that the value of particular elements depends on their position on the chessboard. It illustrates the link between value and difference, and with it Saussure rejects something that we might call linguistic fetishism, an attempt to conceive language as a ‘language of being’ (Heidegger) or, put differently, an endeavour to establish a relation and continuity between linguistic value and meaning.

中In the history of philosophy, we find two prominent versions of such fetishism, which oriented the philosophical relation to language. First in Cratylus, in which Plato strived to illustrate the mimetic relation between words and things, and thus to theorise linguistic value in correspondence to the natural connection between the signifier and the reference:中Then, as to names, ought not our legislator also to know how to put the true natural name of each thing into sounds and syllables, and to make and give all names with a view to the ideal name, if he is to be a namer in any true sense?中The mythic figure of the namer translates physis into language without any loss. The development of the entire dialogue amounts to the idea that language stands in a harmonious mimetic relation to nature, so that even in its basic components, the phonemes, we encounter an imitation of natural sounds, qualities and states. Plato tries to provide a mythical proof that the relation between the signifier and the signified is as such rooted in nature (physis, being), and that signifiers always-already mean something in and from themselves, that they are necessarily referential and that language is essentially communication, language of being, in which every letter follows from a natural sound, state or quality. Plato hereby formulated a mythical version of what would later become the doctrine of adaequatio, adequate relation between words and things.

中Another case of linguistic fetishism, and even another founding myth of linguistics, emerges with the pragmatic tradition stretching from Aristotle to Habermas. Although this pragmatism does not postulate any natural or substantial link between logos and physis, the signifier and being, it nevertheless continues to presuppose that the nature of language consists in stable referentiality and a normative form of communication. Language is defined as organon (tool, organ), and even if this conception seems to reduce language to its communicational use-value, we again come across the same hypothesis as in Plato's mythical rootedness of the signifier in the ideal name: the signifier, in itself, supports a relation between the words and the things, the symbolic and the real. There is no surplus in language; the former comes from elsewhere, for Aristotle from the sophistic misuse of language, for Wittgenstein from false philosophical problems.

中For both Plato and Aristotle, there is more at stake here than the problem of language. The same dilemma is encountered in economy through chrematistics and usury, where money becomes its own telos and enrichment for enrichment’s sake the only economic imperative. The true issue concerns the denaturalisation of social links through the autonomy of the signifier and value, and the rejection of the idea that the human community is grounded on a stable social relation. How do we delimit the good and the bad use of language and money? How do we guarantee the overlapping of value and meaning and simultaneously prevent another possible overlapping, the one between value and jouissance, which negates the former and threatens to dissolve the social link? For Plato and Aristotle, the paradigmatic case of the good use of language is communication but even more so philosophy, the language of ontology, spoken by philosophers and moreover by being as such. In a certain sense ontology understands itself as one immense prosopopoeia of being. The ideal functioning of language consequently takes place in the highest form of philia, the love of wisdom, which is also a form of friendship, a social link. The ontological language of being is rooted on the axiom professed by the Parmenidian Goddess: being is, non-being is not, which makes of language without negativity one of the main philosophicalideals. Precisely this negativity, however, is what Marx and Freud encounter at the other end of metaphysics in the fetishist disavowal of alienation and of castration.

中In contradistinction to the language of being and to the ideal of a language without negativity stands the language of the sophists and poets, where enjoyment, seduction and equivocity question the primacy of communication and external referentiality. If the language of ontology is a prosopopoeia of being, then the language of sophistry is a prosopopoeia of jouissance. The signifier is no longer the bearer of meaning but an apparatus of jouissance and a tool of deception. It remains an organon but serves other purposes. The supposedly natural link between the signifier and the signified is suspended, and jouissance invades their intermediate space, uncovering the autonomy of the signifier and production in language. In the extreme case, this jouissance dissolves the dialogue and the social link, leading to a discursive self-abolition, as in the case of Cratylus, who is said to have abandoned all language and merely moved his index finger. The denaturation of language into an apparatus of jouissance makes of sophists ‘human plants’, but it also makes them speak only for the pleasure in speaking. In the figure of the sophist two extremes coincide, pure babbling, on the one hand, and pure silence, on the other, the life and the death of language, Joyce and Cratylus.

中What sophistry is in relation to language, chrematistics is in relation to money. It detaches money from its social function, turning it into an obscene self-reproducing entity. Exchange turns from the metaphor of social relation into a means of jouissance. Buying and selling should reflect and realise the idea of social relation. But the sophist and the usurer do not reflect or imitate anything; at the background of their actions there is neither eternal idea nor normative structure. The delimitation of the normal and the pathological functioning of linguistic and economic apparatus is an impossible task that calls for a fantasmatic foundation of the presupposed relation. Plato and Aristotle’s attempt rejects the topological problem, according to which the border between the signifier and jouissance is both nowhere and everywhere in the system of differences. From the philosophical condemnation of chrematistics and sophistry, it follows that the main point of philosophical repression is the intimate connection between communication and production in language. In order to ground the homeostatic vision of language (language as a language of being), Plato and Aristotle produce the fantasy of a 'subject supposed to enjoy'. Psychoanalysis and the critique of political economy, however, reveal that the autonomy of the signifier and of value should not be exaggerated - the presumed autism of jouissance in language and the autism of fictitious capital are the privileged targets of both the Lacanian and Marxian critiques. A sensationalist dramatisation of the problem misinterprets the autonomy of the signifer and of value and walks straight into their immediate fetishisation. The key problem remains the discrepancy between communication and jouissance. If communication implies a response, this does not suggest that this response in turn implies an ideal communicative model, on which the pragmatic tradition strives to ground the fantasy of a consistently regulated and stable social relation.

中By comparing language with chess, Saussure strived to show that the system of differences is merely temporary and depends on the formal rules of the game, which remain unaltered. The passage from one synchronicity to another takes place with each move, establishing a new distribution of figures and new relations, thereby changing their values. However, Saussure expresses the following reservation:中At only one point is the comparison weak: the chess player intends to bring about a shift and thereby to exert an action on the system, whereas language premeditates nothing. The pieces of language are shifted - or rather modified - spontaneously and fortuitously. . . In order to make the game of chess seem at every point like the functioning of language, we would have to presuppose an unconscious or unintelligent player.中For Saussure, there is no unconscious intention; intentions can only be associated to consciousness, hence to the subject of cognition. The border that would support the integral overlapping of chess and language is nothing other than the unconscious, but then another figure of subjectivity would have to be introduced. Here Freud's discoveries receive their full weight. Returning to Freud through Saussure is possible only under the condition that the Interpretation of Dreams drew a strict equivalence, in all points, between chess and language, thereby making the move that radicalised the implications of the autonomy of the signifier. Yet, in presupposing an unconscious player, Freud also checkmated Saussure, as the unconscious introduces a serious complication in the conception of structure: it names the instability of structural relations, by connecting both aspects of the autonomy of the signifier, representation and production. The issue is additionally complicated by the fact that the unconscious is split between unconscious desire and the dream work. The latter comprises all the mechanisms that manipulate the conscious and preconscious material and are homologous to linguistic operations. But these mechanisms serve to produce the object of satisfaction. The Freudian unconscious player turns out to be marked by a conflict, which makes the presupposed intention appear in its inconsistency. In order to illustrate this split, Freud will refer to nothing other than political economy:中A daytime thought may very well play the part of entrepreneur for a dream; but the entrepreneur, who, as people say, has the idea and the initiative to carry it out, can do nothing without the capital; he needs a capitalist who can afford the outlay, and the capitalist who provides the psychical outlay for the dream is invariably and indisputably, whatever maybe the thoughts of the previous day, a wish from the unconscious.中In this excerpt, Freud focuses on the relation between unconscious desire and the day's remains, the dream work being excluded from the comparison. But, given the substantial role of the dream work in Interpretation of Dreams, we can tentatively claim that what Freud encounters in the unconscious appears to be homologous to the capitalist social link; it is the same contradiction as that between the capitalist and the labourer. With this distinction, Freud separates the intention from the subject. Unconscious desire and dream work are intentions without a subject - and we can recall at this point that Freud defines dream work as a process that neither thinks, calculates, nor judges, in short as pure intention. The subject of the unconscious, however, is a subject without intention, a decentralised and metonymic subject that is represented in the relation between linguistic and economic values. To anticipate later discussions, the subject without intention is produced in the difference between the repressed signifier of unconscious tendency (S1) and all other signifiers among which the operations of the dream work take place (S2). The problem of subjective transformation in analysis calls for a short circuit between the subject without intention and the intention without subject, between the decentralised subject of unconscious and the no less decentralised unconscious labour.

中It is here that another crucial aspect of Lacan's later critique of Saussure enters the picture, this time regarding the arbitrariness of the sign. By defining the relation between the signifier and the signified as arbitrary, Saussure moved beyond the linguistic fetishism of his predecessors. The idea of arbitrariness implies that nothing within the signified unites it to the series of sounds that constitute the signifier. Lacan's first return to Freud radicalised Saussure by isolating the signifier from the Saussurean sign and thereby exposed the kernel of linguistic autonomy. The second return to Freud took a step further by isolating in arbitrariness its true logical modality, which Saussure did not accentuate sufficiently, namely contingency:中For no signifier is produced as eternal. That is no doubt what, rather than qualifying it as arbitrary, Saussure could have formulated - it would have been better to qualify the signifier with the category of contingency. The signifier repudiates the category of the eternal and, nevertheless, oddly enough, it is intrinsically. Isn't it clear to you that it participates, to employ a Platonic approach, in that nothing on the basis of which something entirely original was made ex nihilo, as creationism tells us?中Contingent is what participates in nothing. We can immediately note the scandal this subversion of participation has not only for Platonism but also for Christianity, the religion of the creatio ex nihilo. Participation in nothing introduces a strange hybrid of Plato and creationism. On the one hand, it evokes Plato's doctrine of the participation of appearances in eternal ideas. But the weakness of this doctrine consists in the conclusion that these ideas again participate in the highest Good. Plato thereby mystified the 'impenetrable void', the negativity of the cut, in which every signifier participates. On the other hand, the proposed definition of contingency corrects Plato's doctrine of participation with the idea of creation of the world out of nothing. Of course, this does not suggest that Lacan simply accepts the creationist model, since creationism still understands God, not simply as the Other but as the Other of the Other (the Other of Creation). For this reason, creationism is incapable of really thinking the radical contingency of the act of creation, which would in itself have to undermine the religious hypothesis of the Other of the Other and make creation appear as non-whole, or not thoroughly constituted ontologically. From the viewpoint of contingency, God cannot be the eternal Creator but falls on the side of the effects of the created: ‘God is unconscious' (Seminar XI), 'God comprises the integrity of the effects of language' (Seminar XXII), and finally the neologism dieure introduced in Seminar XX, which brings together God (dieu) and saying (dire). Both atheism and materialism are situated between Plato and creationism.

中The introduction of contingency as a participation in nothing is a corollary to the autonomy of the signifier and indicates a double move beyond Saussurean epistemic coordinates:中To say that the signifier is arbitrary does not have the same range as to simply say that it bears no relation to its effect of the signifed, for the former involves slipping into another reference. The word ‘reference’, in this case, can only be situated on the basis of what discourse constitutes by way of a link. The signifier as such refers to nothing if not to a discourse, in other words, a mode of functioning or a utilisation of language qua link.中Situating the signifier as difference already provides the minimal definition of the social link, under the condition that this definition includes the subject: ‘The signifier is what represents a subject to another signifier’. The contingency of the signifier demonstrates that the mode in which language functions is in no way grounded on a necessary background that would guarantee its immanent stability and relation to an external reference. No invisible hand, no relation to nature, and finally no eternal creator, to whom we could ascribe creatio ex nihilo. Historically it makes sense that Plato tried to explain the creation of signifiers out of physis, since for Greeks creatio ex nihilo was unthinkable. Moreover, the radicality of creatio ex nihilo is not entirely thinkable for Christianity either, insofar as religion still ascribes the act of creation to a presupposed Other of the Other, which supports and guarantees the consistency of the created Other(language, reality). Creatio ex nihilo, contingency in the entirety of its rigour, only becomes thinkable in the universe of modern science, where the autonomy of the signifier is not only discovered but also formalised.

中The creation of the signifier out of nothing contains a twofold thesis on anguage and on social reality, for we are speaking of the use of language as a link. If the signifier bears no relation to the signified, then the social link, too, is not grounded on a stable background but is internally broken: there is no social relation. Or, to retranslate this axiom into Marx's language, all history is history of class struggles, whereby the plurality of class struggles specifies that the class struggle is not a transhistoric essence that would unify the historic movement and make of History a secularised Other of the Other.

中With the introduction of arbitrariness, Saussure only partially uncovered the immanent instability of language. It is precisely for this reason too that the axioms of Lacan's second return to Freud, ‘The unconscious is history’ and ‘The unconscious is politics’, cannot be associated to Saussurean structuralism without modifying the very notion of structure. The imperative of structural linguistics consists in thinking language through the opposition of structure and life, without reference to the subject, while its object is constructed through the subtraction of language from speech. With this operation, Saussure grounded linguistics on an operation that Lacan will elsewhere describe as 'repression of the subject’: the science of language treats the latter as if no subject would speak it. For linguistics, negativity does not speak, and its object is more like a language of immaterial beings, language without a body. On the contrary, the move from the signifier to the social link necessarily implies a theory of the subject:中We must still indicate here what this link means. The link. . . is a link between those who speak. You can immediately see where we are headed it's not just anyone who speaks, of course; it's beings, beings we are used to qualifying as living, and it would, perhaps, be rather difficult to exclude the dimension of life from those who speak. But we immediately realise that this dimension simultaneously brings in that of death, and that a radical signifying ambiguity results from this.中Discourse does not only presuppose living bodies, it also introduces death, and hence negativity. By returning to this discursive intertwining of life and negativity, of the speaking body and the barred subject, psychoanalysis and the critique of political economy encounter the logical nexus of the autonomy of the signifier - the representation of the subject and the production of surplus.

REPRESENTATION AND PRODUCTION

中Before 1968, Marx is not a major reference in Lacans teaching. His name appears only sporadically, and mainly in relation to the subject of the signifier. All this changes in the seminar following the May ’68 events, in which Lacan elaborates the homology between the object of Capital and the object of psychoanalysis. The title of the corresponding seminar resumes the underlying orientation of Lacan's second return to Freud, D’un Autre a l’autre: from the big Other, the field of language and the absolute autonomy of the signifier, to the small other, object a, the object of jouissance, but also the object that is logically associated with surplus-value. As the seminar's title already indicates, the accent is displaced from representation to production, introducing another level to the theory of the signifier. The emphasis on representation only approaches the signifier through the transcendentalism of the symbolic, where the signifier seems to be separated from jouissance and to entail its prohibition. Subsequent orientation progressively abolishes this position and moves towards a conception of the signifier that is not simply invested with jouissance but becomes its privileged cause and apparatus. However, the causal relation presupposes a specific labour within language. Lacan thereby returns to the revolutionary kernel of Freud's theories, his labour theory of the unconscious, which explains the satisfaction of the unconscious tendency by the consumption of ‘psychic energy’ (labour-power) in the mental process.

中The move from the Other of language to the other of jouissance overlaps with the shift from Saussure, the privileged theoretician of representation, to Marx, the key theoretician of production. The linguistic Other is now envisaged through the parallax of the subjective lack and the objective surplus, the two faces of discursive production. It is more than indicative that from this point on Lacan will repeat the well-known slogan ‘The Other does not exist’. The claim should not be taken too lightly, notably not in the sense of vulgar atheism, which declares God an illusion that the progress of science necessarily abolishes. Lacan chooses a more sobering direction. Not only was the postmodern marked by an increase in religious belief, from institutionalised religions to various new-age obscurantisms, but the logic of capital, too, successfully imposes its religious component that Marx envisaged through the notion of fetishism. Lacan’s prognosis of a triumph of religion over revolutionary science and emancipatory politics meanwhile became reality.

中‘The Other does not exist’ also contains a materialist lesson, which links inexistence of the Other and causality of the signifier, while distinguishing the linguistic Other (language, discourse) from the theological and metaphysical God (the 'Other of the Other'). While inexistence (disclosure, incompleteness) does not prevent the Other from having real consequences, the persistence of religion consists in the idealist counter-offensive, which strives to attribute the consequences in question to a positive being: as long as things are said, the God hypothesis will persist. In the context of fetishism, this means that the inexistence of the Market (the global market as an instable and antagonistic space of values) goes hand in hand with the hypothesis of the vital forces of capitalist abstractions. It is no coincidence that Lacan speaks of the triumph of religion at the dawn of financialisation, only a couple of years after the American abolition of the Breton-Woods system that terminated the gold standard and inaugurated the era of 'free-floating' currencies. The triumph of religion has a concrete name in political economy, neoliberalism, with its wild hypothesis that the deregulation of capital liberates its ‘creative potentials’ and immanent teleology, the spontaneous tendency of the market towards equilibrium.

中In its theory of the Other, psychoanalysis cannot but assume the position of atheism and materialism. The move to the small other extends this positioning in a logical alliance with the critique of political economy: ‘I will proceed with a homological outlook based on Marx in order to introduce today the place where we need to situate the essential function of object a’. The choice of terms contains an implicit criticism of Freudo-Marxism for remaining in a metaphorical or analogical framework, without exhaustively thematising the logical, epistemological and finally political continuity of Marx's critique of economic discourse and Freuds elaboration of libidinal economy. The thesis is that the unconscious production of jouissance and the social production of value follow the same logic and display the same structural contradictions, tensions and deadlocks: not repression of productive potentials of sexuality, drives and desires but the insatiable demand for production, ‘production for the sake of production’ (Marx), from which the repressed unconscious tendencies cannot be excepted.

中The homology in question is supposed to situate the object of psychoanalysis, now translated as surplus-jouissance, in the discursive structure. This translation is coined according to Marx's surplus-value, Mehrwert, and Lacan even proposes a German term, Mehrlust. The coupling of jouissance and surplus, however, is not Lacan's invention but is already present in Freud, who, in his book on jokes, centred his analysis of unconscious satisfaction on what he called Lustgewinn, pleasure gain. Freud thus already used the notion of the surplus-object but did not situate it logically and topologically. Subsequent development in psychoanalysis abolished the revolutionary consequences of the Freudian insight, so that Lacan's intervention aims at the same critical status as Marx with regard to the political-economic debates regarding surplus-value:中This object a, in a certain sense I invented it, just as one can say that Marx's discourse invented something. What does this mean?Marx's discovery is surplus-value. It is not that object a was not approached before my discourse, of course, but it was approached in an insufficient way, as insufficient as the definition of surplus-value was before Marx's discourse made it appear in all its rigour.中Inventions and not discoveries, then; and what is invented is not objects, which were already known before Marx and Lacan, but a method that exposes the hidden logic of their production. Here we again come across the inseparability of materialism and logic, as both inventions contain a turn in the understanding of discourse. At the root of this logical and materialist orientation stand the aforementioned quarrel regarding discursive consequences and the notion of material cause, now associated with the signifier.

中Lacan leaves no doubt that his concern is solely the logical and not the analogical relation between Marx and Freud: ‘To say homology means that their relation is not analogical. It is the same thing and the same stuff, as far as it is the discursive scissor cut (trait de ciseau du discours)’. The French phrasing alludes directly to the first chapter of Capital, where the commodity exchange and the double character of labour are repeatedly exemplified through tailoring. What matters is the inversion of the relation between concrete labour and abstract labour, since only through this inversion can the place and the function of surplus-value in the capitalist mode ofproduction be unveiled. One of Marx's corrections of political economy resides in acknowledging the structural function of the gap between abstract and concrete labour, which depends on the double character of commodity. Through the social implementation of the commodity form, the absolute autonomy of exchange introduces a set of consequences in the subjective and the social reality. No cut is merely concrete labour; rather, it is part of a broader discursive logic that supports the capitalist organisation of labour. The action contains the central abstraction next to capital, the commodity-producing commodity that is bought and sold on the market. In this way, every concrete labour is stamped by the contradiction that leads back to the double character of commodity. But let us here take a few steps back.

中Without any logical gap that would separate the object of psychoanalysis from the object of the Marxist critique, both endeavours are joined by material implication:中Only my theory of language as structure of the unconscious can be said to be implied by Marxism, if, that is, you are not more demanding than the material implication. . . that is, that my theory of language is true whatever be the adequacy of Marxism, and that it is needed by it, whatever be the defect that it leaves Marxism with. So much for the theory of language implied logically by Marxism.中A material implication is false only when truth implies something false. Then there are only a few options left: either Marx's theory is true, which implies Lacan's theory of language as something true; or Marx's theory is false, which nevertheless implies that Lacan's theory of language is true; or, finally, both Marx's and Lacan's theories are false, but even in this case the homology remains valid and the material implication conserves its truth value. In any case, the critique of political economy precedes and conditions psychoanalysis not merely historically but above all logically, epistemologically and politically.

中To say 'Marxism' naturally does not mean the same as to say 'Marx’. The quote contains more than it seems, for Lacan later alludes to the theory of language that Marxism implied historically. In the background stands Stalin's intervention into the Soviet linguistic debates, in which he negated the scientific status of Marrism, the theories of the Soviet linguist Nikolay Yakovlevich Marr, who defined language as a superstructure. Marr's theory implied that every major change in the base should lead to a major change in the superstructure. This would then mean that the Soviet revolution should have introduced a new language, or produced radical changes in the actually existing multiplicity of languages in the Soviet Union. Empirically this was naturally false and practically impossible. The development of language takes place independently from social revolutions, and Stalin's intervention into the debate consisted in declaring Marr's theory of language anti-Marxist, ending the debate with the order that ‘language is not a superstructure’. Saussure claimed something similar in his lectures: the impossibility of a linguistic revolution comes from the fact that each subject participates in language individually. This individual participation prevents social revolutions from introducing major changes into the functioning of language. However, for Saussure, the same individual participation implies that language is subject to constant change. To repeat, language is not a state but a movement: it cannot be revolutionised, but there is nevertheless a permanent revolution, or better, a constant development and non-teleological becoming in language. This permanent revolution is located opposite individual participation, and does not mean that it is the subjects who consciously or intentionally change language.

中Lacan additionally specifies the characteristics of his theory of language: ‘The least you can accord me concerning my theory of language is, should it interest you, that it is materialist. The signifier is matter transcending itself into language.’ The critical value of this materialism is contained in the description of the signifier as matter transcending itself into language. An unusual matter, of course, since it violates the spontaneous understanding of materiality, but, then again, the modern scientific understanding of matter is consistently counterintuitive and counter-empirical. The signifier, and consequently language as such, appears as transcendence within immanence, torsion within materiality. The causality of the signifier then does not consist in the simple scenario, where the signifier intervenes from some presupposed Outside but in the act of self-transcending, through which an autonomous system of differences emerges from materiality.

中Lacan thereby rejects two seemingly opposite but nonetheless anti-materialist readings: conventionalism, for which language is a cultural product (human convention with the exclusive aim of communication), and neurolinguistics, which places language in the broader context of cerebral evolution(and for which language is no less an organ of communication). Neither a convention nor a biological product of evolution, since both reductions exclude the autonomy of the signifier, a contingent but no less real consequence that accompanies the emergence of language and without which language is unthinkable. This autonomy denaturalises the apparently natural or conventional tool of cerebral or cultural evolution. Language is therefore an internal exteriority, a foreign body in the biological body. Its ‘atom', the signifier, becomes a cause by loosening its ties both to cerebral materiality and to communication. At this point, the relation between use-value and exchange-value re-enters the picture and Lacan's materialist definition of the signifier echoes Marx's description of commodity as a sinnlich übersinnliches Ding, sensual suprasensual thing, where the same act of transcendence, articulation of materiality (commodities) into (commodity) language, is at stake. And just as the transcendence of the signifier produces a metonymic subject and an ungraspable object of jouissance, the transcendence of commodities transforms labour into labour-power and situates surplus-value as the privileged object-cause in the capitalist social link.

中The materialist definition of the signifier pursues the quarrel regarding alienation. An idealist would necessarily claim that the subject is constitutively unalienated and that alienation is secondary. At the same time, as soon as one starts from the primacy of the signifier, alienation turns out to be constitutive of the subject. The articulation of the signifier into an open system of differences can only produce a decentralised subjectivity, and Marx's critical move in the first chapter of Capital consists in differentiating constituted alienation, fetishism, which still concerns the ‘cognitive' misperception of commodities, from constitutive alienation, production of capitalist subjectivity qua labour-power. Labour-power designates the capitalist appropriation of the subject of the signifier, its transformation in accordance with the commodity form. In other words:中Value represents what of labour-power is contained in each object that carries value, but it can only represent it in commodity exchange, that is, for another value. But labour-power is simply the subject. It is Marx's name for the subject.中According to Marx, his materialist predecessors, notably Feuerbach, failed to theorise the logical connection between alienation and structure. It is not materialist enough to simply reverse the relations between God and Man, or to proclaim that God is a projection of Man's desires, something that Freud formulated in his critique of religion. Marx founded materialism on the detachment of alienation from imaginary projection, associating it instead with structure and logics, the paradigmatic example here being the equivocity of commodity language and human language. The materialist orientation consequently substituted the reference to Man and to its transcendental essence with the reference to the subject, understood not as an autonomous consciousness but as a real consequence of the autonomous signifier. This is the essential point of Marx's Theses on Feuerbach, which is actualised in Capital:中The chief defect of all hitherto existing materialism (that of Feuerbach included) is that the thing, reality, sensuousness, is conceived only in the form of the object or of contemplation, but not as sensuous human activity, practice, not subjectively. Hence, in contradistinction to materialism, the active side was developed abstractly by idealism - which, of course, does not know real, sensuous activity as such. . . Feuerbach resolves the religious essence into the human essence. But the human essence is no abstraction inherent in each single individual. In its reality it is the ensemble of the social relations.中Pre-critical theories of the subject continue to use the idealist vocabulary of cognition (contemplation, consciousness), keeping as their ultimate reference transcendental and centralised subjectivity, while the critique of political economy departs from the repressed flip side of this idealist subject, the alienated subject at work in every discursive action. This is the logical subject of politics. In order to achieve this, discourse, too, needs to be envisaged as more than mere organon. The aim of Marx's analysis of labour therefore cannot be the simple liberation of living labour from blood-sucking capital but a rigorous determination of the actual subject of capitalism, labour-power, whose abolition would initiate a structural transformation of the entire mode of production and a transformation of the subject, since the logical subject of the autonomous system of differences would thereby be separated from the commodified form imposed by capitalism. Marx did envisage a liberation of the subject, not from alienation, as the humanist Marxists continue to claim, but from the false universalism of commodity form and from its abstract representation in the regime of values. Political economy, and the capitalist vision of politics that is grounded on its concepts, sees in the subject a mere commodity, hence an object, while enthroning the tendencies of capital and the private interests of the capitalist class as the privileged subject of politics.

中Milner proposed to call the materialist orientation that Lacan elaborated in his reference to Marx ‘discursive materialism’. The expression risks falsely suggesting that Lacan was atempting to construct some sort of postmodern materialism, a combination of vulgar materialism and thelinguistic performative. Yet it all comes down to how we understand Lacan's claim that discourse has consequences. If we interpret them within the framework of performative theory, then they remain within the symbolic, confirm the autonomy of the signifier and address merely the permanent modifications of linguistically constructed reality. Lacan's recurrent appeal to formal logic and mathematics goes beyond these narrow frameworks of performativism and exposes another kind of production in language from the mere proliferation of language games and metonymic meaning. The issue is most evidently at stake when it comes to the subject of representation (labour-power, the subject of the unconscious) and the object of production (surplus-value, surplus-jouissance): they are not simply performative effects of the capitalist discourse but real consequences of the structural causality in social reality and in the living body.

中Lacan often uses the example of the moon landing in his attempts to theorise discursive consequences. This event was not so much a ‘giant leap for mankind’ but rather an event in perfect accordance with what Foucault described as the ‘death of Man’. The true event is not the actual moon landing but the fact that it lies within the realm of discursive possibilities alone: 'scientific discourse was able to bring about the moon landing, where thought becomes witness to an eruption of the real, and with mathematics using nothing other than a linguistic apparatus.’ The moon landing is thus a discursively generated event, which does not make it in any way less real. Only that the materiality of the real demonstrated by the moon landing, as an event that has its mathematical foundations, goes much further than the reality of the moon landing, the empirical presence of Man on the moon. The appearance of the moon landing being an achievement of Man conceals the capacity of scientific discourse to produce an event by means of the linguistic apparatus, without Man as its central agent but not without a subject as its effect. Behind the ‘giant leap for Mankind' there lies the final erasure of the idealist human essence; the event once again demonstrated Man's actual status in the capitalist universe as a quantifiable subject (labour-power) mobilised by a successful cooperation between science and capitalism, meaning that Man was again confirmed in his status of waste material rather than a sublime generic essence.

中When Lacan points out the discrepancy between the historical and the logical deployments of the Marxist theory of language, he indicates that Marxism failed to recognise that Marx's idea of commodity language and the inversion of the relation between use-value and exchange-value (exchange as an abstract but nonetheless productive action) already made it further than the Saussurean determination of the double character of linguistic signs. Lacan's correction of structural linguistics - the isolation of the signifier from the sign and the introduction of the subject - provides the materialist theory of language indicated in Marx's critique (in the earlier quoted excerpts Lacan writes twice: 'my theory of language’ ). In turn, Marx’s theory makes the same correction in relation to the political-economic labour theory of value. A critical and materialist theory of value can be elaborated only under the condition that the abstract political-economic subject of private interest is replaced with the alienated subject qua labour-power. In this case as well, Marxism regressed back to the idealist framework that Marx criticised in his Theses on Feuerbach. The Marxist variant of idealist subjectivity is proletarian class-consciousness, yet another version of the transcendental subject of History. A significant part of Marxism (one but surely not the only exception being Althusser's theoretical anti-humanism) inverted Marx's logic, which begins with the autonomy of value in order to arrive at the production of decentralised subjectivity. That Capital is about structural and not empirical or cognitive reality is made explicit in the very preface, where Marx writes:中To prevent possible misunderstanding, let me say this. I do not by any means depict the capitalist and the landowner in rosy colours. But individuals are dealt with here only in so far as they are the personifications of economic categories, the bearers of particular class-relations and interests. My standpoint, from which the development of the economic formation of society is viewed as a process of natural history, can less than any other make the individual responsible for relations whose creature he remains, socially speaking, however much he may subjectively raise himself above them.中Again, Marx does not aim to ground politics on the cognition of the capitalist relations of production, whose efficiency is independent from consciousness, but on a materialist theory of the subject, which is supposed to give ground to an actual universalism while also demonstrating the root at which the false universality of commodity form grabs each individual and society as a whole. The rejection of the primacy of cognition is further expressed in the following well-known reversal, where Marx's implicit understanding of the signifier already surpasses Saussure:中Men do not therefore bring the products of their labour into relation with each other as values because they see these objects merely as the material integuments of homogeneous human labour. The reverse is true: by equating their different products to each other in exchange as values, they equate their different kinds of labour as human labour. They do not know it, nevertheless they do it. Value, therefore, does not have its description branded on its forehead; it rather transforms every product into a social hieroglyphic. Later on, men try to decipher the hieroglyphic, to get behind the secret of their own social product: for the characteristic which objects of utility have of being values is as much men's social product as is their language.中Because there is exchange, different kinds of labour are condensed into an abstraction, which is nonetheless material. The system of differences transforms labour, which does not leave the subject unaffected. Hence the question is not in deciphering the hidden meaning of social hieroglyphs but in situating the subject they signal in their autonomy. For whether in civilisation or in the desert, a hieroglyph always implies another hieroglyph and the subject of the relation independently of consciousness. A hieroglyph is always-already social because of this implication and not because of its use by concrete and conscious individuals.

中When it comes to social hieroglyphs, fetishism is already an attempt at their interpretation, which leaves the structure of the commodity universe unknown and the logic of production mystified. By ascribing to commodities, money and capital, the value of having a positive and intrinsic quality, fetishisation comes rather close to hermeneutic interpretation (just as for Plato and Heidegger being was an immanent feature oflanguage and not its effect). On the contrary, a materialist interpretation highlights the autonomy of structural relations and traces the fetishist interpretation back to the equivocity of commodity form. Slavoj Zizek has suggested on several occasions that ‘they do not know it, nevertheless they do it' should be supplemented with ‘they know it, nevertheless they do it’. The efficiency of structural relations being immune to consciousness, Marx's critical method cannot envisage an overall abolition of fetishisation but the detachment of politics from the reign of economic abstractions, which has been intensified by decades of neoliberalism. The liberation of politics consequently means the same as the abolition of the rootedness of social links in the commodity form as their unique formal envelope.

中The statement ‘they do not know it, nevertheless they do it' seems to contain the division between conscious knowledge and unconscious action, but the actual and more fundamental division exists in the regime of knowledge: between reflected knowledge, on the one hand, and unknown knowledge, contained in both thinking and action, on the other. Marx is here even more Freud's predecessor, showing that the necessary precondition for abolishing the political reign of capitalist abstractions resides in a systematic reintroduction of negativity into politics. Class struggle is not the sole politically charged signifier - the unconscious is one as well. To demonstrate the logical inscription of the unconscious into politics was the central effort of Lacan's homology.

中When introducing the homology between both surpluses, Lacan expresses his regret that he did not introduce Marx earlier into ‘the field in which he is, after all, entirelyat home', or on another occasion, 'Mehrwert is Marxlust, Marx's surplus-jouissance’. As evident as this affinity may appear in the late 1960s, this introduction could not have happened before the invention of object a. In 1968, the object a is already the central Lacanian concept, and Marx can now become the privileged reference, which helps to uncover ‘the place where we need to situate the essential function of object a': the homology immediately extends into homotopy. The logical identity of both surpluses strives to situate the specific mode of existence of the unconscious in the social link while also accounting for the unconscious effects of the capitalist discourse; the capitalist colonisation of the mental apparatus. In homology there is no place for the opposition of the subjective and the social. Freud already tried to place psychoanalysis on this border, and Lacan's notion of discourse pursues this direction, describing both the structure articulated in individual speech and the structure of the social link. But Lacan differs from Freud in one important respect. While Freud's theories amounted to the myth of the primordial father, the originary subject of jouissance, the fundamental Lacanian lesson is that there is no such thing as a subject of jouissance, just as for Marx there is no subject of surplus-value, unless one fetishises the appearance of capital as the vital subject of valorisation, as is the case in the developed forms of capitalist abstractions such as financial capital (but also on the more 'immediate' level of commodities and money).

中Lacan introduces his reading of Marx by recalling the most evident feature of his critical break with political economy:中Marx departs from the function of the market. His novelty is the place where he situates labour. It is not that labour is something new but that it is bought, that there is a market of labour. This is what allows Marx to demonstrate what is inaugural in his discourse and what is called surplus-value.中The departure is not the market of political economists, where all commodities and values seem to occupy the same level and are abolished in equivalence, but a 'market of labour’, where labour-power is the negative metonymic constant that value represents in every commodity and that exposes the paradoxes of commodity form and of the market as such. To repeat, the main inconsistency resides in the double character of commodity, which grounds the difference between commodities and commodity-producing commodity, and more generally the gap between representation of labour-power in terms of exchange-value and production of surplus-value in the consumption of labour-power. The political economists see the market as an ‘immense collection of commodities' (Marx), a closed system, whose dynamic does not necessarily contradict the immanent tendencies to self-regulation and homeostasis. The market appears homogeneous and structured on stable and predictable relations, similarly as in the previously discussed Saussurean analogy, in which there are only values that relate to commodities in an arbitrary but nevertheless stable and adequate way. In the sharpest possible contrast to this idyllic scenario, the consequent interpretation of the market as being first and foremost a market of labour exposes that this political-economic Other is traversed by contradictions and is therefore inconsistent. At the very heart of the capitalist transformation of labour stands the strikingly banal and yet wide-reaching fact that labour is bought and sold on the market, where it appears as a commodity among others. To say that Marx's novelty lies in the correct situation of labour - and not simply in the labour theory of value, to which his critical interventions could mistakenly be reduced - again argues that a materialist science of value is not possible without a theory of the subject that the political-economic labour theory failed to articulate.

中Lacan grounds the homology between surplus-value and surplus-jouissance on a reformulation of his definition of the signifier: 'the signifier is what represents a subject to another signifier’. Saying that Marx's version would be ‘value represents labour-power for another value' would not be entirely correct because it would bypass the double character of the commodity form. Lacan therefore draws a different conclusion. His old definition is ‘copied from the fact that, in what Marx deciphered, namely the economic reality, the subject of exchange-value is represented next to the use-value’. The extension of the double character of commodity to the logic of the signifier additionally exposes the ambiguous status of use-value, whose abstract face becomes apparent in the consumption of labour-power. Its usefulness indeed consists in the production of other commodities, but from the perspective of capital its consumption aims at the extraction of surplus-value.

中The gap between representation and production cannot be localised because it is everywhere and nowhere in the labour process. No quantification can draw a limit, where the production of use-values ceases and the production of surplus-value begins, and correspondingly, where labour is paid and where unpaid surplus labour begins. The problem clearly does not lie in the fact that the value of labour-power would be inadequate or that a more accurate representation of labour-power should be sought, but that labour-power is already produced as structurally inadequate and nonidentical. Consequently, the articulation of representation with production, exchange-value with use-value, presupposes a different topology from the univocal division of inside and outside. The space, in which representation and production intertwine, is simultaneously continuous and discontinuous, displaying the main feature of the Möbius strip. This is the homotopy that the homology leads to.

中The crucial factor that complicates the topological but also the temporal relations is the tendency of capital towards self-valorisation, which makes the production of use-values indistinguishable from the production of surplus-value. Marx writes:中The capitalist has bought the labour-power at its daily value. The use-value of the labour-power belongs to him throughout one working day. He has thus acquired the right to make the worker work for him during one day. But, what is a working day? At all events, it is less than a natural day. How much less? The capitalist has his own views of this point of no return, the necessary limit of the working day. As a capitalist, he is only capital personified. His soul is the soul of capital. But capital has one sole driving force, the drive to valorize itself, to create surplus-value, to make its constant part, the means of production, absorb the greatest possible amount of surplus labour.中The structural tendencies and imperatives of capital push the entirety of production towards purposelessness and compulsive automatism. Through this automaton the main feature of jouissance emerges in the capitalist organisation of labour, the fact that the surplus-object ‘serves no purpose’. It does not satisfy another tendency except the drive for self-valorisation, so that the ultimate aim of labour consists in producing more labour.

中Lacan's translation of the signifer into economic reality recapitulates the contradiction of the two circulations that Marx formalises in the introductory chapters of Capital. The structure of the capitalist mode of production is internally doubled on the circulation ‘commodity - money - commodity' (C-M-C) and ‘money-commodity-money' (M-C-M). This internal doubling is not without the appearance that we are dealing with two different and independent circulations, which can be read historically or logically, and Marx seems to propose both readings. According to the historic one, the (C-M-C) circulation (exchange, selling and buying)would be the oldest form that historically and logically precedes capitalism and that, more importantly, does not contain the perversion that grounds the capitalist mode of production, whose aim is exclusively the production of surplus-value, the constant growth of profit and absolute autonomy of capital (M-M'), the formula of fictitious capital that abolishes the mediation of production through commodity labour-power. The genesis of capitalism thus implies a structural shift that is both historical and logical, and the difference between the first and the second circulation seems to recapitulate the historical passage from feudalism to capitalism. Marx formalises this development in the circulation(M-C-M), which he immediately corrects into (M-C -M'), where (M'=M+△M, increase of value)and thereby finally situates surplus-value in the social link. Lacan's definition of the signifier can be situated in both circulations but has entirely different consequences in the virtually infinite circulation (M-C-M').

中The historical reading of the first circulation inevitably falls into the trap of its idealisation: the nostalgia for those good old days when commodity exchange was still immediate and when social reality was not corrupted by the merciless drive for profit. Placing (C-M-C) before the circulation of capital thus produces a fantasy of economic exchange as the paradigmatic case of social relation and the illusion that this exchange was once homeostatic and regulated but was thrown out of joint by the instabilities of capital; an illusion of the past, in which money still fulfilled its social function, its use-value, which consisted in supporting economic exchange and thereby the social relation. Marx certainly does not promote this oversimplifying nostalgic vision, since he recalls that the paradoxes of the general equivalent already troubled Aristotle. At the same time, both circulations address the inner inconsistency of the capitalist social link. Their logical reading shows that Marx in fact analyses the gap between appearance and structure. (C-M-C) is not more immediate, not an authentic exchange that is later corrupted by profit-oriented (M-C-M') but an inner fiction of the circulation (M-C-M'). Of course, we cannot simply claim that in capitalism commodity exchange is inoperative. It is operative precisely as far as it masks the circulation of capital and neutralises its immediate obscenity and exploitative tendencies. According to the logical reading, the first circulation, selling and buying, concerns the worker, and the second, apparently symmetrical one, buying and selling, the capitalist. Of course, the whole critical point of Marx's formalisation is to prove that both circulations are asymmetrical: that what the worker is selling is not the same thing as what the capitalist is buying, or put differently, that the value for which the labour is sold is not the same as the value for which it is bought. When the capitalist buys labour-power he gets in one and the same package surplus-value:中We pay labour with money, because we are on the market. We pay it according to its true price, as it is defined on the market by the function of exchange-value. But there is unpaid value in what appears as the fruit of labour, because the true price of this fruit is in its use-value. This unpaid labour, which is nevertheless paid in a just way in relation to the consistency of the market in the functioning of capitalist discourse, is surplus-value.中The apparently banal remark that we pay labour with money demonstrates its point if we remember the most basic Marxian lesson regarding money. Since we are dealing with two different circulations, money, just like any other commodity, appears in its double character: once as use-value, a material support of exchange, a concrete embodiment of that sameness that is expressed by all exchanged commodities, and once as capital, the embodiment of the autonomy of exchange-value and ofthe surplus-object. Money finally reveals the fantasmatic status of use-value, which is nevertheless necessary for the functioning of the capitalist machinery. Money has no use-value except that it supports exchange and embodies the autonomy of value. For this reason it becomes the fetishist object par excellence. But social inequality again reveals the immanent doubling of exchange, since the labourer only deals with money as means of exchange, that is, labourpower can only be represented through exchange-value, and according to the law of exchange the labourer receives a 'just' payment. The capitalist, however, deals with money as capital, and from this perspective the use-value of labour-power does not consist in producing commodities but in producing more value. For this reason, the capitalist as the personification of capital and as a social administrator of its ‘private interest' tends to extend the working day and to reduce the time needed for the production of use-values. The labourer gets paid 'justly, yet the truth of labour is not in the presumed adequacy of representation but in the structural gap that both separates and links it to production.

THE LOGIC OF SURPLUS AND LOSS

中The gap between representation and production certainly reflects an inner break in the social link, but it also has a structuring function that amounts to the well-known result that drives capitalist social relations: ‘It is in this gap that what is called surplus-value is produced and falls. Non-identical to itself, the subject no longer enjoys. Something called surplus-jouissance is lost’. The double production of the subject of loss and the surplus-object is accompanied by the appearance that the object originally belonged to the subject and was only lost at a later stage. This appearance is the negative correlate to the fetishisation of capitalist abstractions and motivates a misinterpretation of the worker's position. The psychoanalytic supplement to the Marxist critique of fetishism is contained in the very homophony of plus in plus-de-jouir, which means both ‘more jouissance’ and ‘no more jouissance’. The formulation resumes the central Freudian thesis that jouissance knows no right measure and that its production entirely undermines the homeostatic model, on which, for instance, Aristotelian ethics as well as economic liberalism built their economic and political theories. Behind the subjective pursuit of egoistic private interest, the multiplicity of small human narcissisms, from which, for Adam Smith and other liberal economists, somewhat miraculously grows a stable social relation, there is a structural loss, which in advance corrupts the capitalist pursuit of happiness and its fantastic success stories. In opposition to political economy, Freud grounded his metapsychological account of libidinal economy on the rejection of the homeostatic model. The homeostatic vision of the mental apparatus is definitively abolished in Beyond the Pleasure Principle (1920), where the notion of the death drive, the emblem of the constitutive instabilities of libidinal economy, enters the picture.

中The two aspects of fetishism are addressed in Lacan's formula of fantasy ($◇a), according to which the fetishisation varies depending on whether the given conditions are observed from the position of the subject or of the object. In the first case, the structurally generated appearance suggests that the subject and the object form two compatible halves that could be fused together in a non-problematic totality. In the second, the subject of valorisation appears to be capital itself, as the fetishisation of capitalist abstractions suggests. In any case, the subject's non-identity is perceived as secondary and as something that could be abolished simply by ‘correcting’ the structural relations that brought the subject into existence. The standard social-democratic scenario moves in this direction: including the workers in a more just distribution of profit, collective ownership of the means of production, regulating financial speculation and bringing the economy down to the solid ground of the real sector. More radical political experiments were equally unsuccessful in abolishing alienation: ‘It's not because one nationalises the means of production at the level of socialism in one country that one has thereby done away with surplus-value, if one doesn't know what it is’. Nationalisation does not produce the necessary global structural change, which would abolish the market of labour and thereby the structural contradiction that transforms the subject into a commodity-producing commodity. The non-relation between labour-power and surplus-value remains operative, and nationalisation in the last instance evolves into a form of state capitalism. Marx, however, did not claim that the appropriation of surplus-value would abolish the capitalist forms of alienation and fetishisation. This would suggest that the abolition of capitalists, these social fanatics of the valorisation of value and personifications of capital, would already solve the problem. Marx's point is rather that capitalism can exist without capitalists because the capitalist drive to self-valorisation is structural, systemic and autonomous-but there cannot be any capitalism without the proletariat.

中The critical and materialist signification of alienation departs from the autonomy of the signifier and leads to the conclusion that alienation is structure. No identity or jouissance precedes non-identity and loss, and, consequently, no subjective wholeness is abolished and no immediate access to jouissance is made impossible by the intervention of the signifier. Such a position would indeed place psychoanalysis in the symmetrical understanding of alienation, which echoes in Freud’s earlier accounts of the relation between sexuality and culture and eventually in Freudo-Marxism. Identity assumes the same status as the idealist notion of human essence that Marx criticised in his predecessors. The equivalence between alienation and structure, by contrast, leaves no doubt that the flip side of the production of surplus is the reproduction of lack - the true ‘matter’ by which the subject is constituted.

中The equivocity of the plus in surplus-value and surplus-jouissance allows Lacan to conclude that the discursive structure of capitalism imposes the renunciation of jouissance rather than its prohibition. This renunciation is what makes of the capitalist a modern master. The point is not necessarily self-evident, notably if we recall the conclusion of Marx’s critique of primitive accumulation, the founding myth of political economy, according to which the capitalist historically accumulated the first wealth through saving, while the proletarian enjoyed beyond his limits, until he was left solely with his labour-power. In this process, his entire existence was reduced to a labour without qualities, which stained his being with having. Marx mobilises this main feature of alienation to his own advantage, under the abolition of the political-economic myth of primitive accumulation. In the capitalist universe, commodity is not simply yet another private property but the privileged form of being. The ontological question of being is thus necessarily preceded and conditioned by the pre-ontological question of having, whereby the asymmetry between the subjective lack and objective surplus highlights the modern coordinates of the ontological problematic. This effort implicitly traverses Marx’s critique of materialism in his Theses on Feuerbach and determines its future orientation. There is no critique of political economy without an implicit materialist ontology.

中But let us return here to the link between labour and the renunciation of jouissance. According to Lacan, this is not the actual novelty of Marx and Freud’s concept of labour. Their critical contribution is in explaining this renunciation as something that is structurally imposed on the subject by the relations of domination:中From the very start, contrary to what Hegel claims or seems to claim, it is precisely this renunciation that constitutes the master, who knows very well how to make it the principle of his power. What is new here is that there is a discourse that articulates this renunciation and makes it appear within something that I will call the function of surplus-jouissance.中The correction of the political-economic idea of renunciation becomes more evident here. The master does not renounce some substantial jouissance but instead structurally imposes the renunciation on every subject. The equivocity of plus in surplus-jouissance again turns out to be crucial. Surplus-jouissance is not some jouissance that would reach beyond another jouissance, in the sense that there would be a certain quantity of jouissance to which something more is added. The actual correlate to the surplus-jouissance, produced by the same discursive cut, is the lack of jouissance. The renunciation of jouissance therefore contains more than the battle for pure prestige through which Hegel seems to approach the master-slave dialectic. The capitalist relations of domination build on this double face of the surplus. Production goes hand in hand with renunciation, the ‘more’ with the ‘no more’. The double structural imperative-production of surplus and production of lack through renunciation - initiates a negative spiral, in which no produced surplus is surplus enough. The capitalist master constantly demands more, the famous encore that Lacan placed in the title of one of his seminars. Marx in his turn exemplified this imperative in the so-called abstinence theory of the capitalist:中But, in so far as he is capital personified, his motivating force is not the acquisition of enjoyment of use-values, but the acquisition and augmentation of exchange-values. He is fanatically intent on the valorisation of value; consequently he ruthlessly forces the human race to produce for production’s sake . . . Only as personification of capital is the capitalist respectable. As such, he shares with the miser an absolute drive toward self-enrichment [Bereicherungstrieb]. But what appears in the miser as the mania of an individual is in the capitalist the effect of a social mechanism in which he is merely a cog.中The master’s renunciation of jouissance lies in the difference between the miser and the capitalist, which entails several traps, the main one being that the miser can appear, in comparison to the capitalist, as a subject supposed to enjoy. The quoted passage contains the best description of the difference between enjoyment in the vulgar sense and what Lacan’s concept of jouissance aims at. In everyday understanding, enjoyment is linked to consumption, which still presupposes positive qualities and concrete consumption (use-value). The miser, by contrast, displays, not some other or perverse enjoyment but that which should be properly called jouissance. Instead of wasting his wealth on private consumption, he accumulates, jealously protecting his treasure from the rest of the world, first and foremost from his own temptation to waste it. In his abstinence, the miser does much more than simply renounce some immediate enjoyment in consumption. His drive for enrichment can reach satisfaction only in detaching the privileged embodiments of wealth (gold and money) from their social circulation. His entire persona thereby becomes a hostage of the object.

中Two things are worth noticing in the difference between the miser and the capitalist, which also reveal why the capitalist is a figure of the master, while the miser is merely its comical caricature. Despite being a consequence of the social mechanism, the miser’s drive is still actualised in the form of his subjective fixation and obsession, while in the capitalist the same drive is the structuring element of the social link, a systemic imperative that is interested solely in values and jouissance in the production process. The capitalist actualises the truth of the miser and can become what the miser cannot: the personification of the systemic imperative of accumulation of wealth, now transformed into capital, that is, into an externalised social link that no longer includes merely accumulation but also production, circulation and individual consumption. The capitalist stands for a globalisation of the drive, its sole function is to support and preserve the social implementation of the fanaticism of the demand, to which the drive for enrichment is reducible: the constant expansion of value, the imperative of growth, accompanied by the permanent revolution of the means of production and the forcing of populations into precarity. All this demands renunciation, indebting and production of lack, which finally makes of the capitalist an inversion of the miser, the social transformation of the ‘spirit of the miser’. The miser so to speak renounced social relations for the sake of the illusion that the immediate access to jouissance is possible only in the form of treasure. For this reason, usury has been morally condemned throughout history, and the miser fetishised as an obscene subject of jouissance. The miser illustrates Marx's remark that ‘capitalism is already essentially abolished once we assume that it is enjoyment that is the driving motive and not enrichment itself’. To rephrase, the miser does not entirely follow through on his attempt to detach the treasure from personal enjoyment. He detaches it from everyone, including himself, but he does not make the jouissance produced through this very detachment appear as the jouissance of the system. For the miser, jouissance assumes the finite and empirical form, while for the capitalist treasure is the more endless the more it is abstract: from gold to paper money, from paper money to fictitious capital, electronic money and so on. The miser counts objects: his treasure is embodied. The capitalist merely counts: his treasure is the number. Consequently, fetishisation is displaced from concrete materiality to the ghostly materiality of financial abstractions. The more surplus is turned into an abstraction, the more it pertains to the system, and the less the systemic obscenity is visible. The enrichment itself becomes a socially acceptable and admirable abstraction.

中But this enrichment contains its inevitable flip side, the production of surplus populations, the true signification of ‘human capital’. The equivocity between ‘more’ and ‘no more’ envisages this negative social production: ‘Surplus-value is the cause of desire, which a certain economy has made its principle: that of the extensive and therefore insatiable production of a lack-of-jouissance’; or another variation: 'I think I have sufficiently announced from the beginning of this year that surplus-jouissance is something other than jouissance. Surplus-jouissance responds, not to jouissance, but to the loss of jouissance'. The epistemological tool that provides an insight into the structure of the libidinal and the social economy is the second law of thermodynamics, which explains the flow of energy from regions with higher temperature to regions with lower temperature, thereby introducing the notion of entropy. The notion already supported Marx's analysis of the extraction of surplus-value from the consumption of labour-power. The same asymmetry is reflected in the broader social context: the accumulation of wealth accompanied by the accumulation of misery, the revolution of the means of production combined with the production of a surplus population. The capitalist social link is structured like entropy.

中Lacan approaches energetics through the autonomy of the signifier and envisages in entropy a real structure, which provides privileged insight into social contradictions. In this epistemological reading, energy is desubstantialised and ontologically problematised:中Energy is not a substance, which, for example, improves or goes sour with age; it’s a numerical constant that a physicist has to find in his calculations, so as to be able to work ... Without this constant, which is merely a combination of calculations ... you have no more physics. . . the condition that the system be mathematically closed prevails even over the assumption that it is physically isolated.中Lacan in fact criticises Freud’s energetic theory of the unconscious, which, under the pretention to provide positive scientific foundations for psychoanalytic concepts, ended up in a substantialist reading both of the objects of natural sciences and of his own inquiries. In Freud's mature work, the unconscious and the drive indeed obtained a problematic status, beginning to designate positive ontological entities that Freud no longer strived to explain through discursive causality but rather through the speculative phylogenetic development stretching from protozoa to the human libido. When Lacan took Freud’s early insight on the linguistic nature of the unconscious seriously, he directed psychoanalysis away from positivism and biologism. In the above quote, Lacan extends the same critical move to the natural sciences, claiming that their discoveries do not simply relate to an unproblematic empirical reality but instead question the solidity and univocity of its ontological foundations. Such an interrogation is possible only under the condition that the relation between discourse and the real is no longer subsumed under the ideal of adaequatio, in which discourse, as Lacan occasionally remarks, is considered to have no consequences whatsoever. The Lacanian distinction between reality and the real, moreover, results from this extension of the structural reading of psychoanalysis to the entire scientific modernity. In short, the difference between the two orders consists in the fact that reality designates merely the way the real appears to the human observer -reality as a ‘grimace of the real’ - while the real, to put it paradoxically, stands for the way the real ‘appears’ to the autonomy of the discourse, e.g., to mathematical language:中When the signifier is introduced as an apparatus of jouissance, we should thus not be surprised to see something related to entropy appear, since entropy is defined precisely once one has started to lay this apparatus of signifiers over the physical world.中We can hear the echo of Alexandre Koyré’s thesis that modern science no longer explains the empirical world, in opposition to the Aristotelian and medieval science, which uses mathematics in order to ‘save the appearances’. Of course, the real cannot be the same in physics, psychoanalysis or critique of political economy, which deal with different orders of reality (physical, subjective, social) but also with different versions of discursive autonomy (formal language, the signifier, value). What does unite them, however, is the logical procedure, according to which all these discourses encounter and formalise the respective structure of the real,in which objects like energy, jouissance and surplus-value can be theorised. Another way to situate the difference between reality and the real would be that in reality the process of montage or construction is at stake, while the real demands decomposition and dissolution of appearances. In scientific discourse, the real is what remains for formalisation to grasp once this decomposition has reached its bottom line, or as Lacan puts it:中The real is what makes a hole in this articulated semblant that is the scientific discourse. Scientific discourse progresses, without being preoccupied with the question of whether it is a semblant or not. What is important is that its network, its web, its lattice, as we say, makes the right holes appear in the right place. Its sole reference is the impossible, to which its deductions amount. This impossible is the real. We can reach something real in physics precisely through the discursive apparatus, as far as it, in its rigour, encounters the limits of its consistency.中In this respect natural sciences contain a much more dialectical-speculative and anti-empiricist kernel than the positivist epistemologies are willing to acknowledge. The encounter of the real takes place when the discourse faces its own inconsistency and not some absolute and substantial empirical Outside. The actual site of the encounter is not in experimentation but in formalisation and in the deadlocks that accompany the scientific discourse on the path that leads to the resolution, abolition or reduction of an epistemological deadlock. Verification of a hypothesis is already a step towards normalisation, a moment of stabilisation and reconstruction of reality. As Lacan often repeats, reality is what functions-and the functioning is what the ‘master’ constantly demands - whereas the real is what does not function, something that violates or distorts the automatic repetition and flawless circulation of a discursive mechanism. This is one of the main lessons that can be drawn from Koyrés interpretation of modern scientific revolution. The scientific encounter of the real therefore rejects the all too simple distinction between extra-linguistic and intra-linguistic reality. It takes place within discourse but throws it out of joint. Pushing discursivity to its limits, where the real is inscribed into the symbolic, science exposes a dimension of language that is freed of its communicative, meaningful and pragmatic function. In the same move, it rejects the substantialisation of the real and the transcendentalism of the symbolic, showing that the real is neither an unattainable ‘thing in itself’ nor an unproblematic exteriority; and language is no prison without walls, from which it is impossible to escape.

中Psychoanalysis and the critique of political economy are conditioned by this epistemological paradigm. The unconscious and class struggle, two real cracks in the social and the subjective reality, can be encountered by pushing the discursive consistency to its limits. Lacan’s comments thus combine the epistemological and the political problematic that correlates the scientific discovery of labour-power to the economic mathematisation of surplus-value, which abolished its premodern mystification. In the background we can perceive an outline of another homology, this time between science and capitalism. It may appear that Lacan thereby came close to Heidegger’s pessimistic vision, in which science is reduced to its instrumental and technological ‘essence’. This reduction, culminating in the controversial Heideggerian remark that science does not think, bears the mark of fetishisation. According to Heidegger, the realisation of modern science in technology accomplishes the historical process of the oblivion of being that determined Western metaphysics. With the globalisation of abstract calculation, the paradigmatic case of non-thinking, which unites the scientific and the economic thoughtless and therefore empty reason, the oblivion of being itself fell into oblivion: this is what Heidegger calls ‘the danger’. In this dark scenario, only poetic thinking can render the authentic, originary sense of being and overcome the domination of scientific calculus and capitalist abstractions. The negative fetishisation of science is supplemented by the positive fetishisation of poetry, which is for Heidegger the language of being.

中Yet Lacan never adopted Heidegger’s antagonistic reading of mathematical language versus poetic language. What he did seem to endorse is the idea that modern science contains an ontological scandal that does not stand so much for the oblivion of the question of being but instead reveals an unbridgeable gap between thinking and being, as well as between being and the real. Formalisation is an exemplification of a concurrent ‘sameness’ concerning thinking and the real, but the price for this sameness is the separation of thinking from being and consequently the decentralisation, or alienation, of thinking. The radicalisation of the structuralist project replaces the question of being with the examination of the ways in which the autonomy of the signifier enables thinking to encounter within being more than being, something that is neither being nor non-being but ‘non-realised’. It is no coincidence that Heidegger never thematised the philosophical importance of Freud’s discovery of the unconscious, this paradigmatic example of a paradoxical entity that neither is nor is not but insists in the state of repression, as the persistence of the non-realised in thinking. It is also not surprising that Lacan found in mathematics the privileged correspondent in rethinking the ontological status of the unconscious and other real consequences linked to science, thereby making an anti-Heideggerian move par excellence.

中The epistemological and political orientation of the return to Freud thus displaces the accent from ‘Does science think’ to ‘What form of thinking does modern science ground in?’ For Lacan there is no dilemma; science thinks and its thinking challenges the classical philosophical ideal of the thinking of thinking, as well as the foundation of ontology on the postulate of the sameness of thinking and being:中As a language that fits the scientific discourse best mathematics is science without consciousness, the one that our good old Rabelais promised us and in face of which a philosopher can only remain stupid: gay science is thrilled when it observes in this the ruin of the soul. But of course neurosis survived it.中The modern foundation of science on the autonomous signifier abolished the hypothesis of a centralised thinking that philosophy nevertheless renewed through the subject of cognition. As science without consciousness (without the subject of cognition as its central instance) mathematics detaches language from communication, the real from being, and thinking from itself. Marx and Freud repeat these moves in their analyses of the commodity form and unconscious formations, two concrete examples of decentralised thought. The abolition of the soul was the necessary epistemological condition for Freud’s aetiology of neuroses, a theory of causality that departs from the signifier as the material cause of jouissance and a materialisation of the gap between thinking and being. Yet the subversive potential of mathematical language encounters its limit precisely in the commodity form, which builds on the same discursive autonomy and through which the capitalist fetishisation of economic abstractions reintroduces the hypothesis of the soul through the backdoor: the commodity soul and the spectrality of capital that vitalises the modern universe (the global market) becomes the general formal envelope of thinking, thereby necessarily channelling all the subversive potential of modern science into the permanent revolution of the means of production.

中At a later point, Lacan distinguished between thinking science and objectified science, which immediately addresses its ambiguity in the capitalist framework. The distinction does not necessarily suggest that we are dealing with a good revolutionary science, which unmasks the illusory character of traditional and modern worldviews, as Freud claimed, and the bad commodified science that supports the perpetuation and reproduction of capitalism. Rather, the distinction insists that the decentralisation of thinking, the revolutionary dimension of science without consciousness, is inseparable from the historic genesis of a specific form of this decentralisation: the commodity form. But it does situate science as one of the central terrains of struggle against capitalism. Together with the epistemological conditions of the commodity form and the fetishisation tied to capitalist abstractions, modern science provides the necessary conditions for the invention of critical and conflictual sciences such as psychoanalysis and the critique of political economy.

中In his analysis of the capitalist transformation of labour, Marx already encountered an essential scientific operation that Lacan named réduction de materiel, material reduction. The condensation of labour into labour-power, which stands at the origin of the absolutisation of the market, is a productive abstraction that seemingly reduces different forms of concrete labour but in fact amounts to a new materiality of the subject. Material reduction is at work in every placement of the network of signifiers over a given reality, be it physical, social or subjective, but it also concerns the entire history of logic, in which the autonomy and the materiality of the signifier is progressively isolated:中The material reduction means that logic begins at a precise date in history when someone who had an understanding of this substituted certain elements of language that function in their natural syntax with a simple letter. And this is what inaugurates logic.中Introducing A and B instead of saying ‘if this then that’ does not seem to have any dramatic consequences. However, Aristotelian logic is merely the first step towards the autonomy of the signifier, the subordination of the signifier to the letter, which is still consistent with Aristotle’s ‘organonic’ notion of language. The actual subversion takes place in modernity, when the new foundation of science brings about a different result, the mathematisation of the signifier, uncovering the distinction between reality and the real. A concrete case of this development is again offered by the historical transformation of the market, which, besides the condensation of labour, consisted in the quantification of surplus-object:中Something changed in the master’s discourse at a certain point in history. We are not going to break our backs finding out if it was because of Luther, or Calvin, or some unknown traffic of ships around Genoa, or in the Mediterranean Sea, or anywhere else, for the important point is that on a certain day surplus-jouissance became calculable, could be counted, totalised. This is where what is called the accumulation of capital begins.中The extension of mathematisation to economic reality, the capture of surplus-value and the isolation of labour-power, initiated a groundbreaking change in the master’s discourse, the discursive structure that comprises both the logic of the signifier and the relations of domination. What matters in approaching the origins of capitalism is that concrete transformations in trade centres like Genoa and Venice were already embedded in a broader movement of scientific revolution, which found its ultimate expression in the implementation of formalisation in the sphere of social production. We could paraphrase Marx here: the merchants did not know what they were doing, nevertheless they were doing it. The revolution was initiated before any attempt in writing a capitalist manifesto was undertaken: the subjective and the social surplus that antiquity and Christianity treated as a deviation from a presupposed normative model of social relations was integrated into the constitution of social reality.

中Marx’s Capital provides the first rigorous thought of this epistemopolitical revolution, which implies a strictly determined notion of structure: ‘Structure is therefore the real. This is in general determined by its convergence towards the impossible. Precisely in this the structure is real.’ Within the Saussurean paradigm, such a conception could not have been formulated, yet it is inevitable once structuralism is coupled to Marx’s materialist dialectics. Lacan’s Marx is a structuralist avant la lettre, someone who enabled structuralism to ‘walk on its feet again’ by departing from the problem of discursive production. With the reinforced materialist orientation, material reduction, too, becomes more than an operation of scientific formalisation and of capitalist commodification. It becomes the privileged tool of critique for exposing the deadlocks and contradictions in the given regime of production. By grasping discourse at the root where it most effectively determines the constitution of the subject, the critique of political economy effectively demonstrates that ‘mathematical logic is highly essential for your existence in the real, whether you know it or not’. Evidently it is essential for pointing out the terrain, where politics needs to intervene in order to bring about the double transformation of the subject and of the social link. It is at this point that the Freudian notion of the unconscious most decisively continues the epistemo-political orientation of Marx’s critique.

第二章

资本主义无意识：

回归弗洛伊德

世界观

英当谈到弗洛伊德与政治的关系，特别是与马克思主义的关系时，我们不能忽视他自称的那种对政治事务漠不关心的态度。然而，一旦我们阅读了他关于文化和宗教的著作，我们就会发现这种冷漠以一种相当不寻常的方式表达了出来。弗洛伊德并不是简单地回避政治问题。相反，他提出了一种新的形式，它通过扭曲和置换来解决这些问题，这是一种与精神分析的方法及其对象的性质相对应的形式。因此，将无意识视为从社会撤退到一个严格的私人生活领域并将其视为与社会现实完全没有关联的想法将会是错误的。同样错误的是预设集体无意识（一个包含普遍文化造物和原型的容器）的实存。弗洛伊德的无意识显然更为复杂。它废除了主观的与社会的、私人的与公共的划分，尽管不是在“个人即政治”这一口号的意义上，而是在这个意义上：无意识的实存和其形式机制依赖于同一个结构，这个结构使得社会联结得以正常运作。

英拉康的名言“无意识是像语言一样被结构起来的”，以及他后来的说法，即无意识仅在话语中“向外-存在”，这些都强调了无意识在社会结构中的独特地位。这意味着无意识主体——即依赖于能指而非认识的主体——就是政治主体。无论是作为权利之抽象主体的“法人”、作为政治经济学之抽象主体的“经济人”，还是作为“公民”等等，精神分析都将政治主体从这些意识形态的虚构中隔离了出来。有了这一区分，社会之构成的另一面被揭示了出来：无意识话语的向外-存在，它作为内在的话语性后果的那种持存（insistence），揭示了一点，即社会秩序规定了主体性之生产，并且命名了这一秩序中的不稳定性，而解放性的或革命性的政治活动为了创造社会变革，不可避免地需要背离这一点。正如我们将在下一节中看到的，马克思将无产阶级规定为社会症状的主要观点，体现了资本主义社会中一种普遍的主体性所处的那个位置，而正是这一点给资本主义生产方式的废除带来了唯一的可能性。因此，马克思和弗洛伊德共享的座右铭将是：“非个人的即是政治的”——个人的内核是非个人的。

英在这些问题上，弗洛伊德和拉康之间的差异仍然是显著的。拉康从不回避与资本逻辑的论战性对峙，但弗洛伊德几乎不在严格意义上提及资本主义。相反，他更倾向于谈论文化，从而使讨论具有一种表面上中立的、科学的和社会学的基调。另一个例子是意识形态。在他的作品中，弗洛伊德无疑发展了对意识形态的批判，但这是在世界观的掩护概念下进行的，这个表达涵盖了从哲学、政治到艺术、宗教的一切，指代了现实之构成、其总体化和意义框架的特定倾向。弗洛伊德对马克思主义的讨论将在这一视角内、在更广泛的认识论框架内进行——这一框架区分了世界观知识和科学知识。弗洛伊德的全部出版作品中包含了对马克思主义的一次反思，即使这次反思的结果相当令人失望，因为弗洛伊德以最大可能的保留态度切近马克思。弗洛伊德表达了自己在讨论马克思主义的各种流派方面的无能，而且他只关注所谓的世界观马克思主义，这使他能够设想马克思主义和宗教之间的逻辑相似性。当然，大多数马克思主义者会对这一想法感到震惊。但在做出任何判断之前，值得看看弗洛伊德对一般世界观机制的看法的广泛语境。

英我们在弗洛伊德的《精神分析新论》的结尾章节中发现了这些发展。这部作品发表于一个戏剧性的历史时刻，1933年，经济崩溃的四年后，也是希特勒当选为德国总理的同一年；同样是难以忽视的苏联革命因斯大林主义的主导而戏剧性失败的时刻。这个讲座涉及一个虚构的观众，并修订了弗洛伊德的元心理学理论。关于世界观的章节在认识论和批判性上都形成了一个例外，因为在讨论科学与宗教之间的对抗之后，弗洛伊德同时发表了他对已经广泛传播的弗洛伊德-马克思主义的批判性回应，这个弗洛伊德-马克思主义的“熊孩子”不是别人，正是威尔海姆·赖希。

英当弗洛伊德坚持认为应尽一切努力将精神分析纳入现代科学范式时，他隐含地谴责了在他更广泛的圈子中，有人致力于按照现实存在的政治世界观来塑造精神分析。当然，有人可能会争辩说，对精神分析的政治性解读与弗洛伊德关于社会机制的讨论并非无关，这些讨论已经产生了某种自发的政治哲学。面对《群体心理学与自我分析》这样的作品，法兰克福学派后来基于它发展了对总体主义人格的批判，或者《文明及其不满》，这引导了马尔库塞对社会压抑的批判，但更令人惊讶的是，弗洛伊德的结论是，不仅没有“精神分析的世界观”这样的东西，甚至应该立即避免将精神分析直接应用于政治。这种谨慎来自何处？

英答案在于世界观的逻辑，正如他的讲座所勾勒的。弗洛伊德通过列举和讨论每种世界观的一般特征开始他的批判。他的定义从一开始就听起来很经典：英在我看来，世界观是一种智性构造，它基于一个至高无上的假设，统一地解决了我们实存的所有问题，相应地，没有留下任何未解答的问题，并且我们感兴趣的一切都找到了它的固定位置。不难理解，拥有这种世界观是人类最理想的愿望之一[134]。英因此，世界观的主要成就在于总体化现实，并由此提供其有意义的解释。它不留下任何开放性问题，并将人类利益的多样性置于一个一般假设之下。乍一看，这个定义似乎并没有为理解世界观机制带来任何新意。然而，这种新颖性就在于结论。一个统一的世界观与无意识欲望处于特定的关系之中，它的现实通过给定世界观的构造而显现自身。因此，世界观表面上看起来是对世界的中立解释，是对现实的构造，但在这种解释背后，弗洛伊德揭示了一种机制，它建立了欲望获得满足的条件，一种支撑着欲望不受干扰地获得满足的装置。

英在这一方面，对世界观机制的批判回顾了精神分析关于“通过象征性构造的生产来满足无意识倾向”的那种机制的最早发现。弗洛伊德在这里特别关注梦，梦不亚于一种智性构造，它编码了对满足的需要，因此他将他早期的愿望-实现理论扩展到话语机制构建主体间现实的方式。更准确地说，通过他的世界观批判，弗洛伊德指出了无意识应该被定位的地方。欲望不仅仅是一种简单的心理学构造，而是一种特定的结构动力学的名称，它需要被放置在连接主观现实和社会现实的那条线上。欲望是边界，严格来说，边界之外没有其他现实：相同的结构和相同的形式机制在无意识中起作用，并且在社会联系中起作用。因此，弗洛伊德的世界观批判不应该被拒绝为又一种心理学主义。

英世界观因此提出了一个弗洛伊德通过解释工作来切近的逻辑问题，这相当于对现实的总体化。因此，他引用了海涅（Heine）的著名诗句，在其中诗人讽刺哲学：英生活和世界于我太支离破碎！
一个德国教授能给我钥匙。
他以高超技巧使生活井然有序，
构建一个理性系统，不论好坏；
用睡和晨衣的零碎材料，
他缝合了宇宙的破洞[135]。英弗洛伊德在《梦的解析》中已经使用了完全相同的参考来说明“梦的工作”的主要成就之一，即二次加工，通过这一过程，无意识劳动将松散连接的“梦的材料”结合成一个整体的叙事结构。因此，哲学家可以比作无意识的劳动者，其主要任务是创造无意识欲望的实现条件，解释现实以便它能支持满足（显然，这不是对哲学的非常恭维的看法）。一种解释越是总体化，它生产的意义越多，被构造的现实就越是成功地掩盖了无意识的需要。欲望与世界观的联系意味着无意识幻想在现实中被实施，它支撑着现实的构造作为一个一致的和被框架好的整体。弗洛伊德批评哲学本体论和认识论，因为它们对幻想的结构性功能视而不见：没有幻想的支撑，就没有现实；因此，没有无意识就没有话语。同样地，弗洛伊德驳斥了弗洛伊德-马克思主义关于社会机制的“完全压迫特性”的假设：社会现实不仅仅压抑或抑制欲望、驱力和性的创造潜力；相反，前者是后者的特权性表达和一致性。欲望不是生产者——它本身就是被生产的，而生产者位于别处。弗洛伊德如何确切地处理欲望和生产性无意识劳动之间的关系将在下文中进一步考察；现在重要的是，对弗洛伊德来说，没有任何现实是完全客观的，每一个世界观，每一个意识形态构造，都包含一个“愿望-实现”。

英弗洛伊德在世界观中所遇到的欲望与解释之间的逻辑联系，解释了他为什么明确拒绝构建精神分析的世界观的每一次尝试。精神分析介于不同的层面之间。它的功能不是提供满足的条件，而是揭示在特定的满足装置中表达无意识欲望的机制，从而揭示出，这种欲望与社会现实之间表面的冲突背后，欲望与解释之间存在某种共谋。因此，精神分析并不是去“解放欲望”。它通过解释，转化了满足的形式机制，引导主体朝向无意识生产模式的问题核心。这是著名的弗洛伊德公式“Wo Es war soll Ich werden”(译注：本我所在的地方，自我应当在那里生成，这是我的义务）的主要观点：似乎存在一个自动的生产机制的地方，也就是无意识享乐模式的地方，那里应该是主体被揭示的位置，一个主体化可以发生的地方。而这种主体化涉及整个机制的转变。精神分析的任务因此与世界观形成了鲜明的对比。它不是通过赋予更多的意义来解释现实——而是创造条件，使主体能够生产转变性行动。这种改变似乎因为压抑而变得不可能，事实确实是这样的，尽管弗洛伊德式的压抑概念与压制或压迫有显著的不同。对于弗洛伊德来说，压抑机制对无意识倾向来说是构成性的，如果我们想要将“生产性潜力”归因于无意识，那么它不是与被压抑的欲望有关，而是与压抑本身有关，在压抑中弗洛伊德认识到了生产性无意识劳动。

英弗洛伊德对于构建精神分析世界观的尝试的回应令人困惑：“作为一种专业科学，心理学的一个分支——深层心理学或无意识心理学——[精神分析]完全不适合构建自己的世界观：它必须承担科学的世界观”[136]。精神分析师应该避免发明一种世界观，因为精神分析和世界观倾向之间存在潜在的不兼容性，这使得精神分析看起来像是一个破坏者。因此，分析师不能揭示支持无意识倾向满足的潜在机制，并且为其持续满足提供条件。精神分析和意识形态倾向之间的矛盾最为尖锐。但弗洛伊德从这种对比中得出的结论是，即使是分析师也无法完全摆脱世界观，所以他们应该简单地效仿精神分析的父亲，他采纳了科学的世界观。弗洛伊德对精神分析的科学地位的坚持，表面上看似中立。实际上，它包含了一种科学的世界观，是弗洛伊德的“认识论”欲望的实现。

英表面看来，形成一个稳固的世界观是不合适的，但其背后有一个更根本的不可能性。精神分析无法总体化现实，也无法预测心理生活中的未来事件，最终，它揭示了即使是过去也受到回溯性修改的影响。过去不是一种状态，而是一种运动。这些限制将精神分析与其他实证科学区别开来，特别是物理学、医学和生物学——弗洛伊德希望在其上构建他的创见之科学性——它们都面向未来，并且可能基于已经获得的知识去预测事件。精神分析的局限性在逻辑上来自于无意识的地位，无意识远非一个本体论的实体或一个积极的实体。它完全取决于偶然和不可预测的创伤性事件以及语言结构的动力学，以至于没有特定的案例足够普遍到能够支持未来发展的预测，而这最终是世界观成就的重要部分：从现实、生活和思维中排除偶然性。无意识可能被标记为时间的缺失，甚至矛盾的缺席，正如弗洛伊德偶尔所声称的，但这种缺席是误导性的。它并不自动意味着无意识是不可改变的；它反而证明了其对实际存在的社会条件的依赖，因此也依赖于统治意识形态的“永恒”。正如阿尔都塞所论证的，时间的缺席和社会对抗的缺席是意识形态的两个中心特征，因此意识形态表现为中性的，并且与现实共存。但是，当阿尔都塞宣称每一个主体都是意识形态的想象性效果时，拉康在能指主体中认识到了核心话语后果，这一后果是精神分析与科学和世界观的差异所在。如果精神分析想要加入实证科学，它必须放弃无意识主体的假设：这就是弗洛伊德试图将精神分析建立在热力学、神经学和生物学基础上的风险之所在。如果它想要产生一个一致的世界观，那么它必须重新中心化主体：自我应该支配本我，这是弗洛伊德的许多继承者对“Wo Es war soll Ich werden”的解释（译注：拉康式解释见上文译注）。自我心理学和各种形式的心理治疗仍然处于资本主义意识形态框架内，甚至公开采纳经济自由主义的中心化主体性——即一个围绕自我利益的利己追求而巩固的主体性，正如在认知的背景下，主体围绕自我透明的意识或意向性而巩固。

英一个更普遍的问题涉及到科学世界观的概念。谈论这样的世界观有任何意义吗？它指的是什么？科学家的个人信念，他们的“自发哲学”[137]吗？如果坚持弗洛伊德的定义，那么科学世界观不应该是例外。（译注：上文说弗洛伊德认为精神分析不是世界观，但却是科学世界观）为了与哲学或宗教展开严肃竞争，它必须解决人类生存的所有问题，提供对现实的有意义的解释，并最终阐述社会生活指导原则。简而言之，它必须产生知识、信仰和伦理。现代科学仅仅满足了第一个条件。可能接近科学世界观的是启蒙理想。让我们回顾一下它们的康德式总结：英启蒙就是人类从自我-招致的不成熟中涌现。不成熟是缺乏不依赖他人指导而使用自己理智的能力。如果其原因不是缺乏理解，而是缺乏决心和勇气在没有他人指导的情况下使用它，那么这种不成熟就是自我-招致的。因此，启蒙的座右铭是：Sapere aude! 要有勇气使用你自己的理智！[138]英一个科学世界观是否意味着对知识的勇敢的普遍化，即一种假定的认识论欲望的社会实施，它将使主体从无知中觉醒？“Acheronta movebo”，弗洛伊德在《梦的解析》开头引用维吉尔的话，宣告他的出版物将转移至地下发行，重复精神生活中的哥白尼革命，可以与康德式的“Sapere aude”（敢于认识）一起阅读。弗洛伊德在《幻想的未来》中最明显地对启蒙表示热情，这是他与宗教最明确的对峙，他预测科学知识将战胜“宗教幻想”。同样地，《精神分析新论》表达了一个希望，即“智性——科学精神，理性——可能最终在人类的精神生活中逐渐建立独裁统治”[139]。因此，对弗洛伊德来说，在精神生活中，理性的那种由科学所支撑的独裁，是精神分析的政治理想。只不过这个理性，这个精神分析的我思，是无意识的，以至于理性的独裁将是一个不可能的独裁，由能指的去中心化主体之独裁取代当前资本主义的“强自我”之独裁（拉康称之为我-政体，Je-cratie, 1-cracy）。理性的独裁是精神分析对无产阶级专政的回答吗？——这也许甚至只是无产阶级专政的一个夸张的名字。这样的话，弗洛伊德离拉康将无产阶级与无意识主体等同起来只有一步之遥。

英在其他场合，弗洛伊德声称现代科学伤害了人类的自恋，从而毫无疑问地表明科学知识并不满足任何欲望。形成科学世界观的主要条件消失了。再次回顾，弗洛伊德提到了三种科学侮辱：物理学中宇宙的去中心化，它废除了有限、中心化、和谐的宇宙古老观念，取而代之的是无限和偶然的宇宙；然后是生物学中生命的去中心化，它废除了以人类为形而上学特权王冠的存在者等级制；最后是精神分析中思考的去中心化，它质疑了意识的首要地位，并明确拒绝了形而上学灵魂的假设。相较于世界观机制，现代科学范式产生了完全相反的效果。它不是将外部和内部现实总体化和稳定化，而是剥夺了它们的中心；它不是将它们建立在必然性和秩序上，而是暴露了它们的偶然性和不稳定性；最后，它不是生产对它们的有意义的解释，而是将它们简化为无意义的形式机制。因此，科学世界观遵循了一种完全不同的逻辑：产生可证伪的（不确定的、临时的）知识，去-总体化并排除意义。

英弗洛伊德使用了一个含糊的表达“annehmen”来规定精神分析与科学世界观的关系。这可以意味着科学世界观已经存在，精神分析只是需要伸出手去接受它；或者，这也可以暗示这样的世界观仅仅是被预设的，这将意味着实证科学本身承担了“假定知道的主体”的位置，而弗洛伊德确实经常以这种方式对待实证科学。最后，“Annahme”，即假设/承担——弗洛伊德在与科学世界观的关系中谈论它——也可以作一种形式上的理解，作为对将要破坏既定的世界观-形式的那种并存的解释机制的宣告。这似乎是弗洛伊德关于革命性科学的观点所要解决的。现存的世界观满足了“人类自恋”，而科学的去中心化造成了伤害，因为一种并存的、本质上是唯物主义的世界观至少在逻辑层面上宣告了自己。科学与宗教之间的斗争首先和最重要的是两种并存的思维形式之间的冲突。科学世界观并没有从提供对人类问题确定答案的倾向出发，而是重新构建了这些问题本身。它也不满足欲望，而是改变了主体与欲望的关系。与世界观解释的断裂是形式化的问题，因为只有在这里，才能接近一种并存的解释机制。

英然而，弗洛伊德在认识论上的乐观主义被随之而来的重要转变所标记。弗洛伊德在《超越快乐原则》和《文明及其不满》等著作中表现出了悲观转向，遭遇了一个新问题。这个问题不是讨论科学与宗教之间的历史冲突，而是转向了现代文化，特别是资本主义，在这里，现代科学革命的政治潜力遇到了更具挑战性的界限，这再次涉及到一种特定的思考形式——商品形式。现代世界观在这些形式限制内运作，在这方面，科学革命的主要失败在于无法将思考从普遍的商品化中分离出来；甚至更糟的是，它与资本主义的共谋，将科学知识嵌入到资本主义的永恒革命中。弗洛伊德的悲观主义转向与一个事实紧密相关：商品形式的普遍性成功地将科学知识整合到了资本主义生产方式及其对欲望的表达中。马克思所描述的商品拜物教，首先代表在并通过资本主义世界观在社会和主观现实中的实施过程中，欲望的一种特定转变。这一世界观的四个基石（自由、平等、财产和私人利益）构成了一个抽象的坐标系统，在其中，革命性科学的锐利性预先就被中和了。

英在这一点上，我们可以转向弗洛伊德在他的《世界观》讲座中对马克思主义世界观的探讨。在表达了自己讨论马克思主义的能力不足之后，他总结了自己的保留意见：英理论上的马克思主义，如在俄国的布尔什维主义中所实现的那样，已经获得了一种世界观的能量和自足且排他的特性，但同时它与其所反对的东西有着一种令人不安的相似性。尽管它最初是科学的一部分，并且其实施上建立在科学和技术之上，但它创造了一种思想的禁忌，这与过去宗教的禁忌一样无情[140]。英弗洛伊德继续讨论了对马克思主义的批判性对峙是如何被禁止的，以及苏联政权如何制造了对马克思著作的拜物化，这种拜物化与宗教文本的拜物化相当，等等。弗洛伊德对马克思主义世界观的批判似乎类似于典型的右翼道德主义，然而他的不满中有些症状性的东西，这些东西超越了他言论的道德化语调，并且关注苏联革命的实际产物：将马克思的批判转变为教条主义，将马克思的主体理论重新中心化。弗洛伊德不是在谈论马克思，而是在谈论科学社会主义；革命的产物不是列宁，而是斯大林；是官僚，而不是革命家。

英然而，列宁在宣布马克思主义的世界观倾向时写道：“马克思的理论是无所不能的，因为它是真实的。它是全面的、和谐的，它给人们提供了一个统一的世界观”[141]。拉康在多个场合回顾这段话，以声称弗洛伊德的精神分析发明与全能和真理之间有同样的联系，而且很典型的是，引用这段话时常常省略了列宁对这种全能和真理的具体说明。世界观马克思主义是走向教条主义的必要步骤，其中导向政治经济学批判的辩证唯物主义方法被三个非辩证的世界观成就所取代。拉康也设想了这种逆转，当时他表达了他的惊愕，即大多数马克思主义者从特定的主体性形态的首要地位出发，这种主体性只是在商品形式中、在生产过程中和在历史运动中被异化，而马克思的批判性项目则公开地从价值的自动性出发，因而帮助他发现了政治的去中心化主体，即劳动力，及其在社会中的特权体现——无产阶级[142]。将马克思主义基础作为一种世界观，这要求废除马克思理论的批判性基础：英无产阶级究竟意味着什么？它意味着劳动力被激进化为纯粹的、简单的商品层面，这也将劳动者同样简化为价格。一旦劳动者通过理论认识到，他自己就是这样的，我们可以说这一步向他展示了通向——随你怎么称呼——一个科学家的地位的道路。他不再是一个本质上的自在的（an sich）无产阶级，如果我可以这么说的话，他不再是纯粹和简单的真理，但他是为了自身（fur sich），我们称之为阶级意识。他甚至可以成为党的阶级意识，在那里人们不再言说真理[143]。英共产党的失败最终在于，归根结底，是世界观形态规定了政治组织，并破坏了创造一种新的党派形态的尝试，而不是反过来。这种政治上的失败伴随着一整套认识论上的退步，这些已经被提及过。

英马克思对无产阶级的解释与世界观马克思主义之间存在差异，这些差异与真理和知识之间的差异相重叠。马克思将无产阶级视为劳动之真理的社会具身-人格化（embodiment-personification），而世界观马克思主义承诺废除异化并构成一个革命的认知主体。苏联政权用一个特定的知识的社会具身化——党，作为集体的知识之主体和元历史之主体的占位符，取代了真理的社会具身化，即作为真正革命政治主体的无产阶级[144]。再次强调，政治经济学批判的运动正是沿着相反的方向进行的，从知识的经济形式到价值主体的递进演变，在这里可能的转变的视野被勾勒出来，尽管没有对未来社会秩序的前瞻性洞察：这也是马克思采纳了弗洛伊德所说的科学世界观的地方。世界观马克思主义从这一批判性视角退化，通过将资本主义主体还原为知识，将无产阶级变成学者、科学家、认知主体，在这个过程中，无产阶级以知识认识自身。出发点不再是异化和结构的同一性，这最终规定了认知主体和政治主体之间的裂隙。这种批判性的出发点现在被一个中心化的、未被异化的元历史主体的假设所取代，该主体据说通过党达到了自我意识的最高形式，党是另一个“假定知道的主体”。问题不在于党的引入，而在于党成为预设的历史知识的特权性具身化，而不是一个开辟了空间的组织，在其中具身化在工人阶级和剩余人口中的那种历史和政治真理可以被传递。党表现为拉康通过学派之理念所努力建立的那种学派的完美对立面，该学派基于更新弗洛伊德式真理的利刃的命令，坚持知识与真理之间的裂隙，并坚持大他者的不存在，这代表了最终废除异化的不可能性[145]。

英通过将认知主体通过阶级意识的假设重新引入对政治经济的批判中，世界观马克思主义徒劳地试图消除所有异化的形态并建立本真的主体间关系。这导致它退化回前-批判的框架。党的阶级意识是这一进程的最终结果：人们不再谈论真理，只谈论知识，而知识最忠实地具身化在党的官僚机构中。实证的科学知识——这解释了斯大林倾向于为辩证唯物主义提供本质上是实证主义的基础——成为资本主义主体可能达到自我实现的承诺并超越异化之所在。

英弗洛伊德的主体理论也遇到了类似的情况，后弗洛伊德主义者将主体重新集中在自我上，并从弗洛伊德的“Wo Es war soll Ich werden”的原则中，推导出了规范化和重新整合的命令。拉康对国际精神分析协会——相当于斯大林主义党的精神分析学版本——的政治斗争，该协会认为强大的自我是精神生活中的核心实体，反复围绕着这个含糊的弗洛伊德公理的翻译问题。后弗洛伊德主义者通过认知理论的视角来解读它，并与经济自由主义最为兼容，而拉康则相反，将其作为构成无意识主体的异化的特权公式，并指向实在的政治之主体。

英除了所有的人道主义和道德主义外表，弗洛伊德对世界观的批判使他与马克思对政治经济学的批判性突破异常地接近。在《世界观》的讲座中，包含了对马克思《关于费尔巴哈的提纲》中批判性计划的某种重复，这无疑表明，对马克思而言，政治斗争必然涉及对世界的解释形式，不是通过理论（世界观解释）和实践（政治行动）的过于简单的对立，而是通过实际颠覆解释的实践。马克思和弗洛伊德批判的众多目标之一是哲学，他们宣扬非常成问题且过时的哲学形象。但这个细节不应让我们分心，他们的真正的批评对象是宗教和政治经济学，它们与哲学解释的竞争在资本主义世界中明显处于有利地位，后者被预先贬低为“自我中心”和“无利可图”。哲学和科学在满足欲望方面就是不如宗教和政治经济学成功。

英对于政治经济学批判而言，解释的形式和无产阶级的组织形式同样重要。实际上，解释形式的转变必然需要组织形式的转变。当马克思审视社会形式与商品形式的交织，或者弗洛伊德审视世界观机制与无意识满足机制的交织时，这已经预设了解释形式的倒置，这种倒置在精神分析和政治经济学批判中支撑着他们对幻象的批判，并在商品形式中识别出社会联系的普遍外衣和无意识生产的一般形式。

英再次强调，马克思对表象的批判还有一个至关重要的方面，即是与费尔巴哈式的异化观念的人道主义和本质主义决裂。马克思对拜物教的成熟讨论不再从商品形式扭曲了原本直接的和本真的社会关系的那种错觉出发。在这里，重申构成性异化——即等同于结构的异化——与被构成的异化之间的区别是有意义的——例如商品拜物教，它源自对价值表象与造成这种表象的结构之间关系的误解。异化的双重性并没有阻止它们的混淆，这正是马克思批判费尔巴哈的地方。同时，异化的双重特性揭示了被构成的异化作为构成性异化的面具或神秘化的功能。商品拜物教的另一面是“在背景中似乎存在一个更基本的、未被异化的位置”的表象，从这个位置可以认知到规定着商品拜物教的那种错误——正是未分裂的、无冲突的自我之位置或意识之位置，这是政治经济学、后弗洛伊德精神分析学和科学马克思主义（scientific Marxism）的共同前提。经济人、强大自我和阶级意识是同一尝试的概念变体和意识形态变体，旨在神秘化由话语自动性所生产的主体的分裂。

英与这些试图消除异化的尝试不同——这些尝试其实应该被称为乌托邦——马克思的政治经济学批判包含了一个努力，即思考异化不仅作为生产关系的再生产，而且作为现存的生产方式的结构性转变。我们不能忽视是的，“革命”一词的双重含义在这里的重要性，即科学含义（天体的循环运动）和政治含义（既定社会秩序的颠覆）。同样毫无疑问是的，构成性异化不仅只涉及主体的异化，而且首先涉及大他者的异化：它使大他者以分裂、不完整、矛盾和因此不存在的方式显现出来。这种不存在的对应物是主体的生存/存在（existence），即革命过程的实际能动者（agent），然而，它不占据知识的位置，而是占据真理的位置，正如拉康反复坚持的那样。因为主体正是在大他者的裂缝之中，并通过大他者的裂缝，被生产出来、被带入存在，换句话说，正因为存在一个社会实体，即无产阶级，它以所有人的名义（作为普遍的主观立场的社会具身化）表达了对变革的普遍要求，而这种表达恰恰就将政治建基在非存在、异化和普遍性之间的联系上。

英与此相反，资本主义将其政治立足于对大他者（市场和其他经济抽象概念）的假设性存在，一个虚构经济主体的强大自我（私人利益的自恋）和社会隔离（segregation，译注：种族隔离意义上的那个隔离，这里是在说“他者窃取我的享乐”这一幻想维系对自身种族的认同和对其他种族的排斥）。在有人指出我们在共产主义实验中已经看到了非存在、异化和普遍性在实践中的政治后果之前，让我们回顾一下，20世纪的共产主义政权在所有三项任务上都失败了。他们将自己的政治项目建立在元历史（History）、阶级意识（即使它们并非全部是卢卡奇式的）和同样强烈的隔离形式的三元组之上。一个想要自称为“共产主义”的党派的政治任务，仍然是坚持主体之存在和元历史之不存在之间的相互作用，正如拉康认为他的学派的政治植根于无意识主体之存在和大他者之不存在一样。通过他的批判性行动，马克思奠定了第一个主体理论，它预先彻底废除了两个核心世界观幻想——人类本质和社会稳态，这是资本主义世界观的基础。抽象自由和抽象平等预设了一个同样抽象的人类本质，而私有财产和私人利益则奠定了社会共识，在共识背后，政治普遍性却根本上屈服于资本的特殊利益。无产阶级（主体的社会具身化）和阶级斗争（大他者之不存在的具体显现）代表了对世界观之构造的两种批判性回应，并公开打破了对永无止境的资本主义价值之创造的命令的不受干扰的满足。

英马克思在他经常被引用且几乎同样经常被误解的《关于费尔巴哈的提纲》中，讨论了斗争从对现实的解释——即臭名昭著的“解释之冲突”（conflict of interpretations）——到解释之形式的转移的必要性：“哲学家们只是以各种方式解释了世界；问题在于改变世界”[146]。这个提纲提出了解释与变革、理论与实践、哲学与革命政治之间的对立。在这里，世界观马克思主义从一开始就被排除在外。它可能已经带来了革命性的变革，但它采纳了一种将自身推回到中心化和总体化框架内的历史解释。即使是像海德格尔这样的反动思想家也理解到，马克思的最后一条提纲实际上质疑了思考与行动之间的二分法，以解释之形式的变革为条件限制了世界的实际变化，从而表达了对一种能够描述变革的新的哲学之形式的要求[147]。在理论和实践的表面对立背后，第11条论纲实际上是对两种异质的解释逻辑体系的对立。所有过去的哲学可能都留在了世界观解释的装置内，在那里，变革、历史性运动的冲突性被排除在解释之外，或者在元历史和大写现实（Reality）不知道矛盾的地方[148]。

英回顾哲学的历史，人们当然可以立刻反驳道，很难找到那些仅仅忙于静态解释现实的哲学家，并且没有提出政治性变革的问题：从柏拉图基于希腊城邦危机背景下构想的理想国，通过笛卡尔基于科学现代性带来的变革建立的哲学基础，一直到康德、费希特和黑格尔对法国大革命的热情。哲学家们似乎更忙于思考可能的变革，而不是解释既定的秩序、填补现实的裂隙[149]。但是，正如已经说过的，马克思那里的批判性解释的问题首要地涉及普遍商品化的封闭世界，其中商品形式是其他思维方式的终极视野，并且在其中变革已经是事物的实际状态，即《共产党宣言》提到的永恒革命（permanent revolution）。现实已经包含了变革，但批判性解释所设想（envisages）的是对政治理论和实践的一种阐述，即形式化规定着社会连结的运作的那种结构性矛盾，以及随之而来的对假设的大他者和中心化主体性模型的废除。这些论纲针对的是青年黑格尔派和政治经济学家，而不仅仅针对哲学整体。马克思坚持认为，唯物主义的主体理论将主体视为社会关系的结果，而不是基于抽象人类本质的错误假设，这表明从解释到变革的重点转变也应该被解读为对变革本身的理解的转变。在资本主义-科学主义宇宙中，现实本质上归结为永恒变革，后者失去了其先验的革命特性。能够带来新的社会连结、废除商品形式的抽象普遍性并构建新的政治主体形象的结构性变革，前提是正确解释变革的既定逻辑，即资本主义永恒革命的条件。再次强调，出发点应该是“大他者是匮乏的”（拉康语），从这个观点来看，大部分哲学似乎落入了解释的总体化体制，这并不令人惊讶。

英在对世界观的批判中，弗洛伊德概括了它们的三个核心功能，并以现代科学（知识领域中的革命性变革的发动机）与基督教（历史上最持久且一致的世界观，成功地将其解释形式中的每一个变革整合起来）之间的冲突为例来阐释这些功能：英如果我们想要解释宗教的宏伟本质，我们必须记住它承诺为人类存在做些什么。它为他们提供宇宙的起源以及成为实存的信息，它向他们保证在生活的起伏中得到保护和最终的幸福，并通过它以全部权威制定的规则来指导他们的思想和行为。这样它就满足了三个功能。在第一个功能中，它满足了人类对知识的渴望；它做了科学试图用它的方法去做的事情，在那一点上与科学形成了竞争。它无疑最大部分的影响力来自于它的第二个功能。当科学无法匹敌时，它可以抚慰人们对生活的危险和变迁的恐惧，当它向他们保证有一个快乐的结局，并在不幸中给予他们安慰……在它的第三个功能中，它发布规则、制定禁令和限制，这里宗教与科学的距离最远。因为科学只满足于调查和确立事实，尽管科学确实在其应用中从生活行为中得出了规则和建议[150]。英考虑到科学的认识论革命和不稳定性，世界观的知识比科学更能充分地满足对知识的欲望。此外，世界观还生产意义，这满足了对持续存在（persistent）的欲望；最后，它们产生了秩序，这满足了对安全感的欲望，将变化排除在现实的领域之外。世界观首要的是产生了一个看似运作着的现实，一个没有匮乏或否定性的现实[151]。

英想到这三个成就，马克思的政治经济学批判与世界观马克思主义之间的对比变得更加突出。马克思并没有“基于一个基本假设解决人类实存的所有问题”；相反，他提出了现代政治思想的核心问题：商品形式作为资本主义社会关系的最终界限。统治的意识形态坚称马克思主义是一种世界观，其对象不是“事物如何存在”（the way things are），即“存在之问题”，而是“事物应该如何存在”（the way things should be），即“变革之问题”，不是现在而是未来。然而，马克思的批判既不是世界观也不是乌托邦理论。它更像是一种对不可约化否定性的回收/挽救（reclaiming）——作为思维之对象，作为政治与革命性变革的条件——这种否定性贯穿社会和主观现实，并且无人能够置身事外：不存在原立场，它基于实证知识建立政治，但存在主观立场，它基于冲突性的真理来建立政治。阶级斗争的概念用一个新的、激进化的难题，取代了旧的、不充分的问题和答案，即社会或经济契约：社会不是基于某种神话般的契约、惯例或关系，而是建立在不可约化的斗争和社会非-关系之上。资本主义利用（exploits）这种非-关系，但它只有在通过众多意识形态虚构、幻想和拜物教来神秘化实际的财富之来源的条件下才能这样做。

英在政治经济学中，马克思揭示了与弗洛伊德认为的支撑宗教之功效的相同的三种趋势。这三种趋势归结为致力于将市场建立在稳定和可预测的法则上，使其成为一个实证的大他者，以支撑一个完全运作的社会关系。经济与宗教机制的结合在《哲学的贫困》中以著名的词句得到了最明显的表述，马克思在这里描述了政治经济学的形而上学-神学趋势：英经济学家有一种独特的程序方法。对他们来说，只有两种机构，人造的和自然的。封建制度的机构是人造的，而资产阶级的机构是自然的。在这方面，他们类似于神学家，神学家也区分两种宗教。其他宗教都是人的发明，而他们自己的宗教则是上帝的启示。当经济学家说现今的关系——资产阶级生产关系——是自然的时，他们暗示这些关系是在符合自然法则的条件下创造财富、发展生产力的关系。因此，这些关系本身是独立于时间影响的自然法则。它们是不朽的法则，必须永远统治社会。这样，曾经有历史，但现在不再有。曾经有历史，因为有封建制度的机构，而在这些封建制度的机构中，我们找到与资产阶级社会的生产关系完全不同的关系，经济学家试图将后者说成是自然的，因此是不朽的[152]。英亚当·斯密“无形の大手”的形象一直是政治经济学的形而上学愿景的最佳表达。在市场中，它预设了一种预先给定的理性知识，这使得市场显现为出一个自主的主体。当马克思后来将政治经济学与资本主义抽象物的关系描述为拜物教时，他暗中将这种关系定位在转移的层面（level of transference），而非倒错的层面。要想象这种态度在政治经济学中的持续存在，我们只需回想当代新自由主义改革倡导者的专业术语。随着危机的持续，我们不断被警告说，需要采取激进措施以向市场“发出积极信号”。改革和紧缩措施的作用是“安抚市场”。这些表述不仅仅是修辞手法；它们实际上展示了奥克塔夫·曼诺尼（Octave Mannoni）以著名短语“Je sais bien, mais quand meme”[153]（我深知，但我仍然）所概括的拜物教式的否认（fetishist disavowal）：我非常清楚（市场只是人类的构造和发明），但我仍然（相信它们是自动的和任性的）。这里运作着一个加倍的错误：是的，市场是人类的发明，但它们包含了一个自动的维度，这规定了社会和主观现实，并且这个自动性并没有被正确地定位。原因在于，政治经济学在其表面的合理性和虚假的科学性中，不可避免地包含了上述拜物教的颠倒：“我非常清楚市场是自动的和任性的，但我仍然相信它们只是人类的构造和发明”。

英无论如何，支撑着市场之运作的结构性关系的自动性并没有得到认真对待。政治经济学在同一个动作中将经济抽象物神秘化，视其为自动的实体，并通过退回到传统主义的虚假清醒，相对化了这种自动性中的因果性维度。实际情况是，经济危机并没有动摇对市场的拜物教关系，也没有揭示市场大他者的不存在；相反，危机越是暴露市场的不稳定性，市场就越获得积极存在的剩余（surplus）。然而，变得可以观察到的是，资本主义市场似乎更接近于旧约中的上帝，而不是哲学家和政治经济学家设想的仁慈和抽象的上帝：不是无形之手的中立和自我调节的知识，而是一个欲望着的上帝，要求不断的牺牲，不是一个静态的秩序，而是一个否定性的秩序，其结果具有破坏性。

英此外，将经济改革和紧缩措施强加为不可避免的、类-形而上学的必需品，这让人回想起《资本论》第一卷中阶级斗争的典型表现，其中范式是争取工作日长度的斗争。难道不是吗？如今这场斗争不是在工作日长度的辩论中，而是在工作寿命长度的辩论中被指出。我们可以在这里引用马克思的话：资本家对于工作寿命的最终极限有自己的看法。显然，工作寿命不可能超过生物寿命：工作寿命的最终结束是生物死亡。然而，通过改善生活条件和医疗干预、生物政治等，死亡可以被推迟。延长工作时段的论点归结为这样的论点：即欧洲的预期寿命现在比过去更长，人口正在变老，因此新自由主义改革被认为是不可避免的。工作寿命的每一次延长都比工作日的延长更有效地取消了工人斗争过去的成果。生活与工作变得不可分割；整个生命期被转变为工作中的不稳定生活（precarious life in work）。

无意识的劳动理论

英弗洛伊德对世界观的批判与《梦的解析》的主要结论一脉相承。众所周知，在这部作品中弗洛伊德首次系统化了他的无意识理论，围绕一个看似平凡的论点展开：梦是愿望-实现（wish-fulfilments）。然而，在这种简单性背后，隐藏着一个复杂的结构，揭示了这种“愿望”的成问题的地位。在进入弗洛伊德对梦的解析之前，我们应该回顾一下弗洛伊德式方法相较于他前辈的特殊性和认识论重量。弗洛伊德当然不是第一个赋予梦以理论价值和意义的人。理论传统可以追溯到亚里士多德，在作品的前几节中，弗洛伊德毫无疑问地表明，他在提出过去方法的详尽和详细说明时做了功课，包括心理学、哲学、文学等等。《梦的解析》提出要超越它们的意义，去认识梦之过程的可识别的形式机制，从而隔离它们的满足功能。通过这样做，弗洛伊德发现，在意义、叙事和视觉化的生产背后，还有梦之文本的另一个层面和另一种生产。这里，我想重点讨论弗洛伊德式无意识概念的两个主要特点，即已经提到的生产维度，在意义之生产和满足之生产中内在的双重化，以及无意识劳动在支持无意识倾向满足过程中的核心作用。《梦的解析》中最长的一章涉及Traumarbeit（梦的运作），这一点应该被认真对待。精神分析始于无意识的劳动理论。

英第一个复杂性在术语层面上。在书中，弗洛伊德并没有谈论欲望（Begierde），而是谈论愿望（Wunsch）。这种术语选择使得弗洛伊德关于满足的结构性分析更难以把握，因为在日常生活中，Wunsch指的是针对特定客体的欲望，而Begierde则表现为没有严格确定客体的欲望。正是由于这种细微差别，弗洛伊德在向科学界推广无意识愿望的概念时遇到了困难，因为这种愿望不仅没有客体，而且同时也不针对经验性的、直接的或具体的客体。无意识的欲望既不是Wunsch也不是Begierde，而是某种第三类，它既废除了对象的在场与缺席的二分法，又复杂化了这种二分法，或者更准确地说，它要求我们重新思考什么是客体。

英愿望-实现来自于对心理材料，即“日间残余”（day residues）的操作（manipulation）。这需要消耗能量，这些能量最终可以被量化，因此我们可以从劳动力的角度来理解它。这解释了弗洛伊德对能量学的强烈兴趣，这种兴趣在他后来构建驱力能量学的尝试中变得至关重要，而且这在他早期被放弃了的尝试中已经存在，当时他试图建立一个（实证主义的）科学心理学（1895年）。通过劳动力概念来切近无意识生产的想法，构成了弗洛伊德与他的前辈之间的主要区别，后者将无意识看作不清晰的表征或心理深度，即潜意识。无意识劳动也离不开在资本主义中劳动的双重特性。在英语中，这种划分在语言中被铭刻为“劳作”（work）和“劳动”（labour），它们涵盖了商品的两个方面：使用价值和交换价值。这种语言上的铭刻已经被恩格斯在马克思《资本论》的脚注中指出：“创造使用价值并被定性地规定的劳动被称为“work”，与“labour”相对；创造价值并且只被定量地衡量的是“labour”，与“work”相对立”[154]。恩格斯强调了定性和定量劳动之间、感官的质（sensual qualities）和话语性物质（discursive matter）之间的对立。商品不仅仅消除或解决了两极之间的矛盾，还因此成为了“有质之物”；它只存在于这种分裂中。恩格斯的这一评论与马克思将商品的两个方面与劳动和生产联系起来的下面这个段落相关：英一方面，所有劳动都是人类劳动力的消耗，在生理意义上，正因其均等的、抽象的特性，人类劳动创造并形成了商品的价值。另一方面，所有劳动都是以特定形式和明确目的消耗人类劳动力的，正因其具体的、有用劳动的特性中，人类劳动产生了使用价值[155]。英马克思在这里明确地指出了劳动的分裂：所有劳动同时存在于两个方面；因此，问题不在于商品形式以任何方式侵蚀了劳动，并引入了其不充分的表象。我们所处理的是一种视差结构，根据这种结构，劳动先后在两方面显现，一是作为抽象之物——劳动力，一是作为具体形式——劳动过程。在这一整个过程中，马克思展示了他的成熟的、富有批判性的、唯物主义倾向：一种更精致的、直接地反经验主义式的物质的概念，它将物质性视为一种看似“抽象的”话语——其中劳动力和剩余价值最终是一种实在的话语性的产物——而不是具有误导性的“具体的”经验，后者的产物是一个形式上单一的商品。

英考虑到抽象劳动和具体劳动之间的划分，无意识劳动站在抽象劳动这一边，特别是因为它不能与一个具体的心理主体联系起来。弗洛伊德通过展示无意识生产也不是单义的来进一步复杂化这个问题。它带来了两种成就，并且自身是内在双重的。因此，欲望的满足包含了两种满足，这与商品的双重性质相一致，反映在“愿望”和“欲望”这对概念上。意义与满足之间的最小差异保持了使用价值和价值的划分，就像索绪尔在意义和语言价值之间的情况一样。这种差异在弗洛伊德对梦之工作中的定量因素的强调中是显而易见的，他坚持认为梦的想象性方面不应该诱使我们相信在视觉化背后没有发生逻辑上不同的事情：英梦之思想（dream-thoughts）和梦之文本（dream-content）对我们来说就像是同一主题的两种不同语言版本。或者更恰当地说，梦之文本看起来像是梦之思想翻译成了另一种表达方式，而我们的任务是通过比较“原文”和“译文”来发现这种表达方式的字符和句法规则。梦之思想能够立即被领会，只要我们已经学会了它们。另一方面，梦之内容则像是用象形文字[Bilderschrift]表达的，我们必须将这些字符单独转换成梦之思想的语言。如果我们尝试根据它们的图画价值[pictorial value，Bilderwert]而不是它们的象征关系[symbolic relation，Zeichenbeziehung]来阅读这些字符，我们显然会被引入歧途[156]。英梦就像商品：象形文字之秘密（hieroglyphs）（Bilderschrift的实际意义），其中意义和价值应该区分开来。因此，弗洛伊德坚持认为，我们应该从想象过渡到象征，专注于象征关系（Zeichenbeziehung），即记号之间的关系，并且独立于记号和图像之间的富有意义的、恰当的关系。就像商品一样，梦似乎是一种没有问题的普遍经验，每个人似乎都能够自发地理解它们。随着对它们的形式分析的深入，它们的复杂性变得更加明显，梦的象形文字——即梦的想象方面——与梦的结构之间的鸿沟也越深。同样，就像商品一样，梦汇集了两种语言，不是原文和译文，而是价值的语言和意义的语言（需求、交流），这最终恢复（resume）了同一个语言内部分裂。这两个层面不重叠，它们的互动仅仅是偶然的，但为了理解无意识生产，两者都需要被考虑，正如我们不能简单地从价值生产中省略使用价值，因为那样我们会失去商品形式的全部悖论。如果我们只关注梦的图像序列，那么产品（product）对我们来说似乎毫无意义和价值，而“梦的科学”（正如弗洛伊德的著作最初在法语翻译中所称呼的）只有通过从意义的表象转向价值的逻辑才可能。梦的科学也是价值的科学。通过这一转变，弗洛伊德勾勒出了结构背景，后者支撑着在看似无意义的图像序列中生产意义，同时支撑着为了满足的要求之表达，旨在超越梦之意义，并且这是唯一能够开辟“通往无意识知识的皇家之路”[157]，这标志着拉康对弗洛伊德的第一次回归的能指的自动性。毫无疑问，《梦的解析》将精神分析定位为逻辑而不是无意识的诠释学。

英让我们继续讨论无意识劳动。梦的运作代表了各种形式的操作。弗洛伊德将它们命名为凝缩、移置、表征考量和二次加工。无意识劳动已经隐含在具体劳动与抽象劳动的颠倒关系中，它阻止了将无意识劳动与心理学的主体等同起来。马克思指出了资本主义去中心化劳动的基本成就，他声称，资本主义和生产方式的科学发展并没有使劳动者从劳动中解放出来，而是使劳动从其内容中脱离出来，这意味着劳动首先从经验的劳动者中脱离出来，而反过来，劳动者从劳动中的解放却显得是一项不可能的任务。劳动的脱离使劳动者对劳动的依赖更加彻底，它完成了主体向劳动力的转变，即成为一个商品化主体、一个资本主义式的主体。这种不对称关系背后的意义远不止于这些，即抽象劳动仅仅是成为了所有具体劳动形式的特权代表，或者交换价值从使用价值中抽象出来，从而使劳动本身也变成了一种抽象概念。由于抽象劳动与具体劳动之间的不对称关系，任何回归到更具体、假定更本真的劳动形式的做法都不会废除劳动的异化现象。当然，劳动的异化不是资本主义的结果，就像话语的异化也不是。资本主义所实现的，是在特定商品中对这种异化的客体化。

英从精神分析的视角来看，对这一异化的客体化，其在商品中的物质化，揭示了资本主义的一个核心特征，也就是它将主体置于满足大他者对生产的要求的客体位置，这个客体被大他者消费以获取剩余价值——这恰恰是拉康对倒错的定义。作为劳动力，一种为了生产价值而被消费的商品，主体被剥夺了其主体的位置。劳动的商品化等同于强迫主体处于一种倒错的位置，它要求主体去承担大他者享乐的客体这一位置[158]。马克思的劳动价值论的主要成就在于它重新确立了主体的位置，重新提出了主体在商品世界中的位置，并废除了一个强加于主体的幻想——即认为资本才是价值增值过程中的真正主体。

英在这一点上，我们可以对马克思的劳动价值论补充一点评论，因为我们听说它在金融化和新技术激增的时代失去了重要性。这样的说法有模糊政治经济学劳动理论（亚当·斯密和大卫·李嘉图）和关于它们的马克思主义重新表述之间区别的风险。马克思的价值理论之所以保留“劳动”这个谓词，并不在于如下的简单的观点，即劳动是核心经济范畴和价值的特权来源，尽管古典政治经济学的某个分支似乎声称了这一点——但它是错误的。相反，马克思价值理论的主要成就在于，它认识到在劳动中的这样一个过程，对该过程的分析表明，价值的源泉在于不平等、剥削，因此也在于社会非-关系。然而，为了严格思考价值的源泉，我们还需要承认所有拜物教幻想在这一过程中的参与——这也是马克思劳动价值论的另一个主要成就。价值之逻辑只能与详尽说明的幻想之逻辑同时彻底思考。因此，劳动价值论成为了批判科学的一个组成部分，它反复围绕着剥削和剥削的神秘化之间的相互依存，这两者在资本主义抽象物的拜物教化中都达到了顶峰。马克思的劳动理论在当今的金融资本主义中，无论是在理论上的紧迫性还是实践上的相关性，都从未像现在这样迫切和重要。

英无意识劳动和抽象劳动都缺乏具体的人格化和具身化，因为它们的物质性在于劳动力，而话语装置从活生生的身体那里将劳动力独立了出来，并且能指或价值独立于其与所指的关系来代表劳动力。由于缺乏具体的具身化，所以马克思和弗洛伊德产生了两种“拜物教”：也就是说，他们强制了两种对抽象劳动和无意识劳动的社会性人格化（social personifications）。马克思只能通过将无产阶级和产业后备军拜物教化为资本主义结构矛盾变得经验性的关键点，从而发明社会症状。这当然带来了一个误解，即马克思的批判从形而上学的抽象领域下降到对社会条件的具体分析、下降到具体的男人女人。这里所讨论的拜物教可能重复了商品拜物教的相同操作，但它阐述了可以称之为马克思的假说的东西：受到资本主义影响的个体与构成价值主体的个体是相同的。这显然颠覆了拜物教的假说，即资本主义的主体是资本本身[159]。产业无产阶级和价值主体的同一性意味着，在一个给定的历史时刻，即工业革命时，产业工人具身化了劳动之主体的分裂，具身化了资本主义生产组织所引入的那种异化。他们的假定同一性并不与如下事实相矛盾：价值主体指代了对具身化了它的那一主体的彻底异化。

英对于弗洛伊德来说，在特定的历史时刻，同样的特权也赋予了癔症患者，从《癔症研究》（1895年）开始，癔症承担了与马克思笔下的无产阶级相同的功能。癔症不仅仅具身化症状；对于医学知识来说，她还是一个认识论症状和社会性症状，因为医学知识将她视为伪病（pseudo-illness）、装病（simulation）和忧郁症（hypochondria），或者是一个无法解释的谜团，围绕这个谜团，整个景观（spectacle）被组织起来：夏尔科在巴黎医院对“拉萨尔佩特里埃”（La Salpetriere）的病例展示具有戏剧表演的地位，不仅吸引了其他科学家，也吸引了普通大众。在19世纪，癔症是科学话语的极限，是医学知识优先权被悬置的点，因为癔症症状的病因不能完全追溯到解剖学起源。只有弗洛伊德成功地将癔症理论化为一个社会症状，这在认识论层面上引入了从“医学凝视[160]”范式到“分析聆听”范式的转变，换句话说，从视觉和观察的优先到言语和倾听的优先的转变，最后，从庸俗唯物主义到批判唯物主义的转变。的确,癔症是弗洛伊德的无产阶级。

英梦的运作这一概念，旨在解释逻辑上的满足机制和欲望的结构。占据弗洛伊德心头的问题是，为什么无意识需要通过一种迂回地运作方式——移置和凝缩、审查和变形——才能获得满足。为什么不能以不掩饰和不扭曲的满足呢？为了回答这个问题，弗洛伊德提出了一个假设，即无意识欲望与现实的要求之间存在矛盾。由于这种矛盾，梦的运作为欲望的满足生产了双重条件，其中商品形式的分裂成为克服欲望与现实之间矛盾的最佳手段。在表面的满足中，一种“其他满足”[161]开始显现。这种内在的双重满足是通过操纵白天剩余物、在意识边缘积累的材料，在前意识中实现的，这是意识与无意识之间的灰色地带。在这个中间空间，我们遇到了仍然可以有意识地表述的愿望。因为这个原因，人们可能会指责弗洛伊德对梦的样本分析夸大了它们的意义。讨论的案例只包含平凡、简单和幼稚的欲望的实现。弗洛伊德关于伊尔玛注射的梦，这个本应展示他的发现的革命性的最佳例证，揭示了他试图逃避治疗癔症失败的责任。儿童的梦，另一个证实愿望-实现理论的例子，只关注具体的客体（糖果、玩具等）。几乎所有的例子似乎都选择不当，并且与“其他满足”的现实相悖。它们给人的印象是，所讨论的欲望仅仅是前意识的，暂时从意识和注意力中消失，但并没有以任何方式改变其特性。它仍然针对相同的具体对象，并与白天剩余物的内容交织在一起。最重要的是，至少对弗洛伊德的批评者来说，这里完全没有性的迹象，更不用说婴儿的性（infantile sexuality），没有必要用压抑和审查来复杂化这个问题。

英弗洛伊德在写作中预见到了这些批评，他写道：“然后看起来好像只有有意识的愿望在梦中得到了实现”[162]，这是一种具体的满足，假设了一种幻觉的和表演的形式。重点在于表象，在于将特定类型的满足推向前台的表象。这种表象与联合商品两个方面并掩盖使用价值和交换价值之间结构性裂隙的那种表象相同。据此，梦之形式意味着两种满足，其中一种取决于其明显的直接意义，另一种取决于其语言价值。从质到量的转变涉及客体形式的转变。拉康的客体小a，是欲望之客体，一个没有质的客体，它预设了价值的自动性。因此，只有在资本主义宇宙和现代科学中商品形式的条件下，对这一客体的发现才是可能的。在现代之前，欲望之客体要么作为可望而不可即的超越性事物（拉康在谈论中世纪宫廷爱情中女士地位时提到的das Ding），要么作为内在的神像（agalma）（就像在柏拉图《会饮篇》中苏格拉底和阿尔西比亚德之间的转移关系中的那种神像）。客体小a，既不是超越的、也不是内在的，它在现代性之外是不可想象的，可以说是一种现代的发明，是科学建立在普遍数学化和社会关系建立在量化和大规模生产基础上的结果。

英梦中的幻觉性满足表明，满足被推迟了，并且满足预设了对即时满足的放弃，就像儿童之梦的情况一样。推迟暴露了满足之中的转变，这种转变在愿望-实现中保持不可见，而愿望的直接性相对于它而言则像是一个面具。换句话说，欲望的显现总是通过愿望的表面直接性来中介。欲望寄生于客体的使用价值。我们已经可以注意到，有意识“愿望”和无意识“愿望”之间的关系也铭刻在语言中：“愿望-欲望”这对概念完美对应于“工作-劳动”，就像使用价值之生产和价值之生产与满足和“其他满足”重叠一样。愿望仍然可以归因于意识，因为它的客体是具体的，而欲望似乎没有客体，只要它不与商品形式的定量和抽象特性联系起来。弗洛伊德的梦之分析只是试图证明“无意识愿望”确实有一个客体，因为它在通过对心理材料的操纵所产生的剩余中找到了满足。这个客体的名字也是现成的——它简单地就是肉欲，快乐。尽管弗洛伊德很快就会发现，这种无意识产生的快乐的地位比看上去更有问题。

英在指出掩盖了“其他满足”的那种表象之后，弗洛伊德最终引入了前文提到的经济学类比，这一类比应该用来阐释无意识欲望的本质，并使他的无意识的概念更易于理解。“我现在能够给出一个鲜明的描述”——鲜明的，因为表象需要被重新聚焦，以便使欲望呈现出来——“关于无意识愿望在梦中所扮演的角色”[163]。他承认有些梦的刺激来自白天的残余，因此来自使用价值，尽管这个触发因素对梦之形成来说并不足够。例如，在弗洛伊德关于伊尔玛注射的梦中，他对患者状况的担忧并不足以达到梦之形成。然后他引用了无意识生产与资本主义生产的类比，这个类比值得在这里重复：英梦所需要的动力必须由一个愿望来提供；令人担忧的问题是，要抓住一个愿望，使之作为梦之动力。这个姿态可以通过一个类比来解释。一个白天的想法完全可以充当梦的企业家（entrepreneur）；但企业家——正如人们所说，有理想和主动性去落实梦——没有资本就什么都做不了；他需要一个能够承担开销的资本家，而且为梦提供心理开销的资本家总是并且无疑是——无论前一天的想法是什么——一个来自无意识的愿望[164]。英弗洛伊德并没有说——后来的弗洛伊德-马克思主义者所声称的——无意识解释了资本主义；他明确地提出了相反的观点：是资本主义阐明了无意识。在《梦的解析》中发现的无意识，无非是资本主义的无意识，即无意识满足与资本主义生产方式的结构和逻辑的交织。

英弗洛伊德似乎采取了与索绪尔相似的举措。提及资本家和企业家（经济人）使得整个类比听起来更像是“弗洛伊德与亚当·斯密”而不是“弗洛伊德与马克思”。根据经典经济自由主义，资本家与劳动者的相遇发生在一个自由的平等机会空间中，并通过交换行为实现：用钱换商品，用一种抽象物交换另一种抽象物。同样的相遇在无意识中回响：用心理能量交换白天的残余思想。我们可以顺便提一下，在弗洛伊德后来的一篇文本中，他将“心理能量”——当时被重新命名为力比多——描述为心理生活的标准“流通货币”[165]。一切都可以被翻译成这种精神上的一般等价物。然而，情况比弗洛伊德的类比看起来要复杂得多。无意识劳动与经济人不相容，所以它甚至没有出现在类比中。然而，对梦的讨论毫无疑问地表明，“梦中唯一本质性的东西是支配思想-材料的梦之工作”[166]。在弗洛伊德的例子中，将资本家与“无意识中的愿望”联系起来更为关键，因为它暴露了资本家的一个本质特征。与企业家不同，企业家保留了对经济学认知之主体的参照，而资本家则被识别为去中心化的欲望，这使得这一类比更接近马克思对资本家的描述，即作为恒定增值和盈利的非个人的和系统性命令的人格化。弗洛伊德还提到了资本家和企业家之间其他可能的关系，从他们完全的不同，他们的较小或较大的重叠，到几个企业家向同一个资本家提出要求或几个资本家支持同一个企业家的情况。这些组合不会改变潜在关系本身，尽管它们确实模糊了弗洛伊德不断以单数谈论无意识欲望的事实。与愿望不同，欲望不具有多样性，只有单一的无意识欲望，这被归结为一个无法满足的/贪得无厌的命令（insatiable imperative）。同样显而易见的是，这种单一的欲望并不意味着一个主体：欲望恰恰是一个“无主体的过程”[167]。

英弗洛伊德的类比并没有解释无意识生产，而是集中在表象上。当劳动理论展示了无意识就是欲望和劳动之间的那种分裂时，实际的复杂性就出现了。这种双重特性包含了进一步区分弗洛伊德式概念与其它可能概念的方面。首先，无意识被置于对社会结构的依赖性关系中。然后，这个标记被解释为矛盾，即弗洛伊德在他的早期工作中通过“心理冲突”的概念已经推到前台的“一分为二”的构成性分裂。当弗洛伊德将资本家与劳动者之间的社会连接应用于无意识时，他逐字重复了马克思在《资本论》中的举措，在那里，他们都逐渐从心理学个人中抽离出来，描述过程而非个体。无意识欲望表明，资本家作为统治领域（field of mastery）的一个异常（anomaly）进入舞台：一个无头的主人[168]。

英正如前文提到的，弗洛伊德将梦之工作分类为四个基本操作。他的分析表明，这些操作发生在两个不同的层面上。基础层面是凝缩工作和移置工作：无意识劳动的两个基本方面，与语言的两个主要操作——隐喻和转喻相匹配。弗洛伊德在另一个与社会劳动的类比中优先强调了这些过程：“梦的移置和梦的凝缩是两个熟练工人，我们基本上可以将梦所采取的形式归因于它们的活动”[169]。这些过程表现为一种知识之形式：知道怎么做，未反思的知识，未知的知识。这区分了无意识劳动者与企业家，后者仍然处于认知主体的范式中，政治经济学假定它既拥有对其内在利益的知识，也拥有对外部市场关系的知识。

英另外两个操作，即表征考量和次级加工，呈现为凝缩和移置在想象界中的重复。弗洛伊德指出，这个想象维度不是可被还原的视觉化，当他在讨论次级加工时引用了海涅的诗句，这些诗句在三十年后将用于他对世界观的批判：英区分并同时揭示这部分梦之工作的是其目的。这个功能以诗人恶意归咎于哲学家的那种方式行事：它用破布和补丁填补梦之结构中的裂隙。由于它的努力，梦失去了荒谬和不连贯的外观，接近了可理解经验的模型。但它的努力并不总是成功的[170]。英梦之形成的第二阶段与这种总体化有关。在这里，梦获得了一致性和叙事，这使其可以与世界观的“智性建构”（intellectual construction）相比较，更不必说与商品的使用价值相比较了。但是，劳动的倾向并不必然与隐喻和转喻中的相同，因为它试图填补使用价值与交换价值之间的裂隙，填补无意识形成物的意义与价值之间的裂隙。弗洛伊德通过指出次级加工的任务是消除荒谬的外观来强调这种最小差异，一旦“享乐之价值”（正如拉康在研讨班14中对交换价值的翻译）与意义完全分离，这一点就变得尤为突出。在次级加工和表征考量的层次上，梦之价值在其意义上显现：享乐呈现出“享乐-意义”（joui-sense）的形式（享乐的意义，这里涉及另一个拉康式文字游戏）。

英当拉康用马克思取代了索绪尔时，他将精神分析重新导向无意识劳动者的形象，并因此激进化了他自己引入的主体的含义。这一定位在《电视》中得到了最清晰的阐述，拉康毫不怀疑地表明，精神分析和政治经济学批判发现了相同的主体：英无意识意味着它被倾听吗？在我看来，是的。但这肯定不意味着，如果它没有通过话语而向外-存在（ex-sists），人们就会认为它是一种不思考、不计算、不判断的知识——这并不妨碍它在运作着（例如，在梦中）。让我们说，它就是理想的工人，马克思将他视为资本主义经济的花朵，希望看到他接管主人话语；实际上，这种情况确实发生了，尽管是以一种意想不到的形式。在这些关于话语的问题总是充满着惊喜，而这，的确，是无意识的事实[171]。英“无意识意味着倾听”这种观点，并不会使精神分析变成一种对话（dialogue），它不会退回到某些抽象和理想的交流模型，正如各种形式的心理学和心理治疗所做过的那样。真正重要的是真理重新获得了言说的力量[172]。它的主观表现是言说在身体中引发的抑制（inhibitions）、症状和焦虑。言说着的真理，真理的力量超越了单纯的事实性（facticity）或真理-价值，是精神分析与马克思主义相遇的主要领域，劳动者的形象是这种相遇的特权概念体现。从1969年起，拉康几乎所有的文本都涉及无意识主体与资本主义劳动者的交织，从而表明精神分析在其实践中努力产生的主体之转变与社会变革的政治问题有着直接的连续性。毫不奇怪，《电视》将精神分析的目标之一定义为“摆脱资本主义话语之路”（way out of capitalist discourse），拉康补充说，“如果它只对某些人发生，它将不会构成进步”[173]。在政治事务中，精神分析设想了与马克思主义政治相同的普遍主义。

英拉康通过谈论“理想劳动者”来浓缩弗洛伊德对无意识欲望、梦之工作、资本主义之间关系的分析，它是一种探索无意识生产和资本主义生产之间同源性的另一面的表达。理想劳动者不同于异化的主体。它位于能指之间进行的多种操作那里，一种去中心化的知识形式可以归因于此。理想劳动者并不自知为一种知识形式，但这并不妨碍它完成任务。只有当无意识不仅仅意味着劳动、还意味着倾听，即真理的阐明破坏了无意识知识的自动机时，破坏了作为“享乐的手段”[174]即“生产的手段/生产资料”的知识的自动机时，劳动之主体才登上舞台。相比之下，无意识主体是知识体制中的一个干扰，一个异常，通过症状来表达其阐明：“只有一个社会症状——每个个体实际上都是无产阶级，也就是说，他没有可以用来建立社会连接的那种话语，换句话说，一种假象（semblant）”[175]。在资本主义生产方式中，每个人的真实地位都类似于马克思努力通过无产阶级来表达的地位。无产阶级是“作为对实在的反应的主体”[176]。在这里，我们再次遇到了马克思的主体假设的回响，而正统马克思主义后来通过将无产阶级与知识主体等同起来而废除了这一假设。用黑格尔的话来改述，世界观马克思主义将无产阶级仅仅理论化为实体（阶级意识）而不再是主体（劳动力）。阶级意识没有转变资本主义主体，而是转变了理想劳动者，使其未知的知识成为反映性的“科学”知识。这也正是拉康在《电视》中所指的那种惊诧：历史和结构的发展从主人话语开始，其现代版本是第二次工业革命前的资本主义，到后工业资本主义的大学话语，在其中恰恰是知识，因此是理想劳动者，占据了主人的位置。在苏联，也完成了相同的结构转变，在那里党的知识，无产阶级阶级意识的历史性具身化，成为了特权性话语代理。

英拉康的结论因此是：无产阶级是无意识主体。马克思和弗洛伊德无疑押注于这一形象的革命潜力。对马克思来说，工业无产阶级的政治任务在于其现实化（realisation），即通过对劳动力的废除来自我废除（self-abolition），这将产生新的社会联系和新主体性形象。弗洛伊德也认为，无意识的发现将启动认识论的和社会的转变。他在《一个幻觉的未来》中对宗教的批判，在《群体心理学与自我分析》中对政治的批判，以及在《文明及其不满》中对资本主义的批判，都是针对根植于支配关系的社会结构。精神分析的主体革命潜力应该证明，自我并非家里的主人，并因此推翻了“我-政权”（拉康语），后者标志着现代意识哲学，并为经济自由主义奠定了其经济人的基础。

英拉康显然采取了一种更现实主义的（realistic）立场，并发现了马克思主义和弗洛伊德主义的政治失败。无产阶级，这一社会和无意识劳动的特权形象，确实完成了一场社会和认识论的革命，但这场革命本质上发生在权力和知识之间的关系上。劳动的解放引入了一个抽象知识占据主人地位的社会体系。与此同时，理想劳动者改变了其面貌，在资本主义（专家、欧盟官僚）和斯大林主义（党的官僚）中变成了统治的形象。马克思实际上预见到了事态发展成这样的可能性。在《资本论》第一卷中，劳动的资本主义转型是在生产的技术组织中完成的，劳动者和机器之间的关系发生了倒置。当马克思写到资本主义中的机器使用时，他不断强调“科学知识”在“资本主义抽象物”的“进步的社会实施中”的重要作用。机器的重要性不在于它们的物理在场，而在于它们体现了资本主义中知识的生产本性，知识作为生产手段和现代权力关系的工具。因此，马克思对卢德分子运动（Luddite movement）持有保留态度。他主要担心的是，他们错误地将问题归咎于机器本身，而不是这些机器在生产过程中所实现的那种知识的全新社会角色。他们对机器的直接攻击确实可以被视为“将机器作为剩余价值生产者”这一资本主义拜物教的另一面[177]。

英拉康的理想劳动者诠释了弗洛伊德的熟练工人，即凝缩和移置，这些逻辑操作在不知情的情况下完成了它们的劳动，不自知为一种知识形式。将理想劳动者称为“不思考、不判断或不计算的知识”立即让人想起《梦的解析》中的一个重要段落，在那里弗洛伊德从次级加工的角度提供了梦之工作的浓缩叙述，并得出了以下结论：英在梦之建构的过程中，心理活动可以区分出两个独立的功能：梦之思想的生产，和将其转化为梦之内容……无论梦之思想可能涉及多少有趣和令人困惑的问题，但这些问题毕竟与梦没有特殊关系，也不需要在梦之问题中进行处理。另一方面，在梦之构建期间，心理活动的第二功能，即将无意识思想转化为梦之内容，是梦之生命所特有的，也是其特征。这种梦之工作严格意义上进一步偏离了清醒的想法，甚至超出了最坚决贬低梦之形成期间心理功能的人的预期。梦之工作不仅仅是比清醒时的思想更粗心、更非理性、更容易遗忘和更不完整；它在质量上（qualitatively）与清醒时的思想完全不同，因此不能直接与之比较。它根本不以任何方式进行思考、计算或判断；它仅限于给事物以新的形式[178]。英无意识劳动的双重特性是显著的，但梦之工作的实际对象是形式而非内容，正是这种形式支撑着无意识欲望的满足。前意识材料的转变涉及表象的生产，这种表象不仅会导致欲望的满足，而且会在字面上将欲望隐藏在愿望之中。梦之工作本质上在于创造这种隐藏的条件，它还将“其他满足”（other satisfaction）编码为“满足”，将交换价值转化为使用价值，最终将享乐（jouissance）转化为快乐（pleasure）。因此，“梦是愿望-实现”绝不是一个单纯的（innocent）陈述[179]。

英弗洛伊德对梦的所谓神秘特性并不太感兴趣。他将其解释为梦本身的形式的效果。这就是为什么精神分析不通过赋予它们意义来解释梦。解释学策略将聚焦于内容，这样做会忽视梦的生产机制、梦的劳动和劳动的主体。因此，赋予梦更深层的意义会使梦拜物教化。有趣的是观察弗洛伊德是如何拒绝梦之过程中的谜样外观和非理性假设。他隐含地提到了具体劳动和抽象劳动之间的区别：梦展示了纯粹理性形式（pure form of rationality），因为生产了梦的那种劳动被剥离了像思考、计算和判断这样的积极的质，这些质仍然定义了认知之主体。因为梦之工作仅仅完成它的任务，它是谨慎的、正确的、非迫使的（unforceful），因此是理想的：没有质的劳动。

英然而，在梦之工厂中，有些事情出了差错，这是由无意识引入到话语之中的另一个惊喜方面。弗洛伊德很快发现，并非所有的梦都符合愿望-实现的一般情景。他遇到了再现创伤经历的梦，例如战争神经症患者或性侵受害者所报告的梦；最后还有著名的燃烧的孩子的梦，弗洛伊德最初将其作为愿望实现的例子。通过不断地回到创伤经历——战争、虐待、死亡等——这些梦揭示了强迫性重复。有了这一发现，创伤性神经症被证明是资本主义的附带损害。文化不满将立即成为弗洛伊德对现代文化批判的主要主题。不符合一般装置的梦具有唤醒（awakening）的特征，它破坏了享乐之生产。在这个意义上，无意识不能简化为单一的话语结构。它已经提出了“它的出口”这一问题（the question of its exit）。

英当拉康重申无意识的语言结构时，他引入了一个汇集了马克思和弗洛伊德对劳动分析的术语。这就是“它言说”（it speaks，ca parle）的功能。精神分析式干预在三个层面上运作：思考、工作和言说。关于精神分析的讨论经常提到，弗洛伊德的发明在于他倾听了他的癔症的言说，他们向他揭示了无意识的秘密：癔症的症状在言说，并且通过言说阐明了规定着它的那种话语的真相。这种阐明已经在抑制满足的机制。在这一点上，精神分析最直接地与马克思的发现相吻合，即在劳动中也发生了一种阐明，它表达了资本主义生产关系的真相。这就是马克思发明的社会症状对精神分析具有全部重要性的地方。症状是无产阶级和无意识主体的相遇，是劳动者和言说着的存在的相遇。

快乐利润

英在《梦的解析》出版四年后，其课程在阐述力比多无意识方面得到了进一步的发展。1905年，弗洛伊德出版了两本表面上看似无关的书籍，《笑话及其与无意识的关系》和《性学三论》。虽然关于笑话的书在方法和风格上延续了《梦的解析》的方向，但《性学三论》将对语言的引用替换为对身体的讨论，并将满足的结构分析替换为性发展的理论。媒体对第一本书表示欢迎，而对性的讨论则遇到了阻力和不满。尽管存在明显差异，但这两样作品在引入弗洛伊德的“Lustgewinn”（快乐利润或快乐利润）概念时却相遇，不难在这个表达中识别出拉康的剩余享乐（surplus-jouissance）和马克思的剩余价值（surplus-value）之间的概念中介。通过这个概念，弗洛伊德最终命名了无意识生产的客体和满足无意识倾向的客体。这两样工作也在引入将从此占据弗洛伊德理论工作并要求阐述一种元心理学的倾向方面相交：驱力及其拓扑悖论。快乐利润和向驱力理论（Trieblehre）的转变，克服了结构与解剖学之间的对立，将精神分析定位在它们交汇的灰色地带。弗洛伊德由此开创了方向，当拉康将能指定义为享乐装置时，又回到了这个方向。

英从一开始，弗洛伊德就通过经济学隐喻来探讨心理装置的运作模式。随着他的理论变得更加复杂，这种经济现实也越来越多地展现出其对抗性特征，其中之一是无意识生产趋向于绝对化享乐的生产。在弗洛伊德后期的一篇文本中写道：“我们的心理活动追求的要么是有用的目的，要么是直接的快乐利润”[180]，这再次符合使用价值和交换价值之间的区别。梦的分析已经表明，欲望的满足不是针对日间残余的使用价值，而是通过梦之工作获得的享乐之价值，将无意识劳动等同于无意识欲望。术语快乐利润定义了作为剩余的快乐，因此是心理活动在追求有用性之外达到的东西。从使用价值和它预设的需求（need）的角度来看，快乐表现为一种伴随身体刺激的消除和紧张减少的情感。然而从价值的角度来看，快乐不再是或多或少偶然的副作用，而是满足的客体。因此，快乐利润与任何质无关，这也意味着它没有相应的需求。弗洛伊德对Lust的概念的转变解释了为什么拉康将德语术语翻译为“jouissance”（原乐）而不是“pleasure”（快乐）。从一开始，快乐利润就明显涉及到一个根本的颠覆，它不是满足的一个次要副作用。需求的满足总是已经被寄生、被殖民和被颠覆，被无意识倾向（欲望和驱力）的满足所影响，这些倾向的存在依赖于能指的自主性和价值。

英将快乐与使用价值相联系，将商品定义为满足需求并作为快乐的源泉，这也是马克思的出发点。在这里，需求的不同类型或质以如下方式等同起来：英商品首先是一个外部客体，一个凭借其特性满足人类各种需求的事物。这些需求的性质，无论它们是来自胃部还是来自幻想，都没有差别。同样，商品如何满足这些需求，无论是直接作为生存手段，即消费对象，还是间接作为生产手段，在这里也不重要[181]。英急于求成的精神分析解读可能会得出结论，马克思在分析商品形式时，通过排除欲望维度，因而也排除了主体[182]，因为他简单地将直接的身体需求与在象征层面上被中介、最终植根于幻想的需求——即严格意义上的需求和欲望——等同起来。然而，马克思恰恰没有这样做。通过揭示商品的双重特性，他引入了价值之体系和满足之倾向之间的歧义性，最终将相对化需求和使用价值的非幻想状态。马克思声称，为了分析商品的质的方面，我们首先需要废除，一方面，直接满足和间接满足之间的划分，另一方面，生理满足和心理满足之间的划分。商品形式成为普遍的快感源泉：在现代宇宙中“只有商品快乐”[183]，因此有一种单一的满足，然而由于商品在“无物之质”和“无质之物”之间的分裂，这种满足在内部变得复杂，正如米尔纳所强调的。即使幻想也被使用价值所标记，反之亦然，交换价值殖民了生理或心理需求。马克思设想的复杂性因此变得显而易见。为了理解任何满足，首先需要分析商品的结构。像钻石这样无用的对象显然是被拜物化的，但这种拜物教关系伴随着幻想性需求。欲望贯穿了需求，并由幻想的有用性屏幕所支持。需求的满足和“其他满足”（欲望和驱力的满足）的共存揭示了同一对象中两个异质性的耦合，幻想的一个功能就是精确地链接不可链接的。通过这种幻想的链接，使用价值和交换价值相互污染，使所讨论的对象变得非常复杂（sehr vertrackt），正如马克思所写，变得复杂、模糊甚至疯狂[184]。

英当马克思将生理需求（胃）与智力需求（幻想）等同时，他表明需求不应被理解为准自然现象。需求已经使我们进入了话语领域，需求不能从其与要求（demand）和欲望的辩证关系中完全孤立出来。不存在单纯的需求，需求的满足不会被结构性地被规定（be structurally determined）。回到弗洛伊德，他区分了有用性和快乐，表明需求的满足只能作为副作用引起快乐，而这个副作用不包含快乐利润。有用性和需求在弗洛伊德描述的减少紧张或消除身体痛苦的角度来看，仍然暗示着心理装置包含一种本质上自我调节的倾向，朝向稳态，即亚里士多德式的适度。为了谈论快乐利润，需求和满足之间必须有一个第三项：话语（社会联系，差异）。没有话语就没有享乐，也没有非话语性的享乐。拉康在前述将交换价值与享乐价值的翻译中强调了这一点。从话语的角度来看，需求及其满足总是已经被另一种与力比多身体和能指的物质性相关联的满足所污染。对象的具体性——其质被认为是引起快乐的——变得模糊，而真正重要的是“抽象的”客体，这最终反转了快乐与紧张之间的关系。这是心理装置的结构接近资本主义经济模型的地方。在“其他满足”中，紧张不是减少而是增加。需求的满足是次要的，并且完全融入了另一种满足中，作为其内在的、准虚构的时刻。无意识的倾向和资本的自我增值（self-valorisation）驱力首要地要求不断生产剩余和不断增长的紧张。这是弗洛伊德驱力概念的一个主要特征，它要求对心理装置的功能进行彻底的重新制定，并废除最初的稳态模型。

英价值的辩证法表明，使用价值与交换价值的关系类似于现象与逻辑的关系。弗洛伊德得出了一个惊人的类似结论：“有用的东西本身（众所周知）只是通往快乐满足的一条迂回路径：梦属于这一类，通过此，弗洛伊德提醒他的读者，认为做梦是一种仅仅以幻觉（表演性）的方式结束和解决白天的关注的活动，将是错误的：“那是前意识思想的工作。这种有用的工作与梦一样遥远，就像向他人传达信息的任何意图一样[185]。”梦最小化了能指的有用性和指涉性。相反，它们加强了其自动性和因果性。在这方面，资本主义也是一个永恒的梦，或者更确切地说，是一个持续的噩梦，从其中醒来似乎是不可能的。

英一旦欲望和驱力成为考量的因素，需求的每一次满足似乎都成了问题：“所有言说着的存在的需求都被牵涉到其他满足中，这种满足可能是他们无法达到的[186]。”商品形式是这种扭曲的特权性物质化，即使马克思讨论了这种污染的发达形式，即虚构资本，在那里，价值的价值创造成为生产的规则（M - M’），他仍然重复了第一卷中的批判性姿态，即资本的自我生成（self-engendering）这一表象是建立在质与价值直接重叠的拜物教幻想基础上的。弗洛伊德在超越快乐原则那里也采取了相同的方向——从心理装置的稳态观念到冲突观念——在那里享乐似乎被剥夺了所有指涉性，成为了它自己的主体。但是，如果得出在力比多无意识中否定性的能指之主体被废除，无意识劳动者消失了，或者被压抑的无意识倾向成为它自己的生产性劳动者的结论，那将是错误的。这将是享乐的拜物教化，类似于金融抽象概念的拜物教化。

英弗洛伊德在快乐利润的生产中发现了快乐的转化。需求的满足不能产生作为利润的快乐，因为伴随着需求满足的快乐仅仅是标志着重新建立那个被认为是稳态的秩序，而从其他满足的视角来看，这种秩序证明是虚构的。这里的关键词是稳态（homeostasis），弗洛伊德在1905年仍然相信它决定了心理装置的总体功能。快乐利润是第一个迹象，表明快乐原则的稳态是纯粹的虚构。尽管如此，它表明需求的满足不能产生更多的快乐，就像没有剩余价值可以在逻辑上从流通（C - M - C）中产生一样。剩余享乐，快乐与盈利的联系，并没有简单地破坏快乐原则的所谓稳态特征；它表明稳态是一个必要的虚构，它结构化并支持无意识生产，就像世界观机制的想象成就在于提供一个封闭的整体，在其整体构造中没有裂缝。快乐利润是弗洛伊德首次与超越快乐原则的概念相遇，即重复的强迫，以及将引入精神分析等价于流通（circulation）（M - C - M '）。

英快乐利润的引入，对《梦的解析》中快乐和满足的地位进行了回溯性解释，但也使问题复杂化，因为无意识欲望被驱力所取代。在这两种情况下，剩余客体的运作方式不同。在欲望的层面上，剩余客体表现为匮乏、缺席和否定性。这种表象（appearance）与转喻结构（metonymic structure）相关，导致客体从一个具体具身化（concrete embodiment）转移到另一个具体具身化。瓦伊曼（Wajcman）在收藏家和守财奴的案例中广泛阐述了这种逻辑连接[187]。收藏的结构保持开放，因为收藏的客体（object of collecting）与被收藏的客体（collected objects）不是同一的。没有一个客体能够使收藏完整，从而实现欲望的那种满足。弗洛伊德对梦的分析提供了另一个案例，其中无意识欲望的现实（reality）取决于表面上完全不同的元素的关联。欲望与其自身的解释相重叠，白天残余材料和对其坚持存在（insistence）的编码化的结合。因此，满足（meet）剩余的一种方式是通过转喻运动，其中与客体的邂逅总是失败的：没有客体是那个欲望的客体，因此剩余总是面对着匮乏的形式。对于无意识欲望来说，剩余永远不是足够的（enough）剩余；它不能与单一客体（one object alone）关联。只有在与驱力的关系中，剩余才呈现为肯定的（positive）。并非转喻性转移（metonymic shifting）和对客体的撤回（withdrawing of the object），驱力通过循环（circulation）和重复（repetition）被结构起来。

英马克思并不陌生于驱力的悖论，他的手稿中已经包含了驱力的结构、一般等价物的抽象本性和剩余价值之生产的联系：马克思并不陌生于驱力的悖论，他的手稿中已经包含了驱力的结构、一般等价物的抽象本性和剩余价值之生产的联系：英“因此，货币（money）不仅是一个客体，而且是贪婪的客体……贪婪本身，作为一种特定的驱力形式——即，与对特定种类的财富的渴望（craving）不同，例如对衣服、武器、珠宝、女人、酒等的渴望——只有在一般财富、作为一般财富已经个体化在某个特定事物中时，即一旦货币以其第三品质（third quality）被设定时，才是可能的。因此，货币不仅是客体，也是贪婪的源泉。没有货币，占有欲的狂热是可能的；但贪婪本身是一定社会发展的产物，是历史的，而不是自然的[188]。”英驱力与一般等价物的双重地位密切相关——作为交换手段和作为总体化客体宇宙的特定使用价值。与欲望不同，欲望的客体尚未与特定的具身化相同一，因此支持转喻结构，而驱力则预设（presupposes）了具体普遍性的悖论，即一般等价物应该所是的东西。因此，对客体（财富）的欲望积累了一系列具身了价值的客体——它专注于价值之客体（objects of value），而不是作为客体的价值（value as object）。另一方面，驱力固着在客体，一般等价物上，由于其悖论性的地位——既是单一的又是普遍的，是一种商品又是一种反射所有商品的大写商品——支持满足的无限化，也就是说，支持满足的不可能性和无尽的延续（endless perpetuation）。资本的自我增值驱力是一种无法满足的要求（demand），没有任何劳动能够达到。马克思在将驱力概念与其生物学或生理学内涵分割时提出了一个重要观点。他完全将其与一般等价物的社会性存在和历史发展联系起来。因此，资本主义驱力不是唯一可能的驱力。存在着一种驱力的历史，一种固着的历史性转变，这改变了驱力的社会表达以及一般等价物在主导生产方式中的职能。柏拉图和亚里士多德已经指出了驱力的问题，尽管在古代宇宙中，这个问题与资本主义宇宙中的问题不同，在资本主义宇宙中，生产方式基于剩余价值的数学化和以虚构资本形式释放自我增值的要求。旧的高利贷精神远远不是现代资本主义精神的胚胎形式，即使两者都可以通过一般等价物的存在来解释。让我们回顾《提纲》中的另一个关键段落：英“饥饿就是饥饿，但是通过刀叉享用煮熟的肉所满足的饥饿，与用手脚、指甲和牙齿吞食生肉的饥饿不同。因此，生产不仅产生了客体，也产生了消费的方式，不仅在客观上，也在主观上。生产因此创造了消费者。生产不仅为需求提供了材料（material），它还为材料提供了需求（need）[189]。”英马克思再次着眼于驱力的历史和社会转型，毫无疑问，将驱力置于假定的自然需求与其文化表达的交叉点上，可以被视为精神分析概念的前身。因为弗洛伊德的驱力概念不是吞食生肉的饥饿，而是通过煮熟的肉、餐具和餐桌礼仪的组合达到满足的饥饿。实际上，拉康在将驱力比作超现实主义拼贴画（surrealist collage）时，提出了一个关键点，他强调异质元素的组合包含了目的（aim）与目标（goal）之间的区别，因此再次涉及到使用价值和交换价值之间的区别[190]。

英现在让我们转到弗洛伊德在他对笑话和幽默的分析中对剩余享乐的发现。在《笑话及其与无意识的关系》中，剩余的生产是在社会背景中讨论的。弗洛伊德在书的一开始就强调了这一点，当他为已经写过关于梦和失误行为的科学论文之后，再次将另一篇科学研究献给一个看似边缘和微不足道的对象时，他为这一事实辩护。对笑话的科学讨论可以被证明是合理的，因为“一则新笑话几乎像是一个普遍感兴趣的事件”；笑话永远不仅仅是笑话——它是一个“社会加工”（social process）[191]。它所编码的不过就是无意识与社会联系之间的关系。与梦不同，梦似乎是做梦者的私人活动，而且很难证明社会机制的存在（毕竟梦的功能是保持睡眠，从社会中撤出），而笑话则立即指向一个社会框架；它们揭示了社会关系的结构和剩余享乐的社会经济。

英当然，事情要复杂得多。并不是说无意识在笑话中比在梦中更具有社会性，也不是说将个体无意识注册为社会无意识。相反，对于弗洛伊德来说，梦和笑话呈现了相同的论述条件的两个案例。对笑话的讨论并没有从个体转向社会；相反，它展示了无意识超越了内在与外在、个体与社会、私人与公共之间的划分。如果梦揭示了社会联系在无意识中的铭刻，笑话则展示了无意识在社会联系中的体现，这是能指因果性的两个方面。

英对笑话的分析首先指出，它们的特点并不与特定的想法（thought）相关，而是与其表达形式、措辞（Wortlaut）相关。整个焦点放在含糊性/歧义性（equivocity）上，它实现了意义和价值之间的分裂。笑话的效果取决于Witzarbeit（译注：德语，意为“机智的工作”），即笑话中的无意识劳动，如何形成措辞。无意识生产再次由凝缩和移置指导，但在这个案例中，它们的结合揭示了一个经济学悖论。

英不同的笑话技巧（techniques）有共通的策略，包括对相同材料的多重使用，对给定材料的回收利用。含糊性、双关语或文字游戏将不同语境结合在同一产物中。对相同材料的多重使用描绘了凝缩的非隐喻性使用：“玩弄言辞（play upon words）不过是没有替代形成（substitute-formation）的凝缩（condensation）”。在这种凝缩的转变中，弗洛伊德遇到了倾向于节省（saving）的经济趋势：“所有这些技巧都受到压缩（compression）趋势，毋宁说节省趋势的支配。这一切都似乎是经济问题。用哈姆雷特的话来说：“‘节俭，节俭，霍雷修！[192]’”，从这个角度来看，无意识的劳动者出现了，作为理想的节省者，其凝缩的倾向应该生产剩余：为了创造利润、稳定化经济关系而节省。听起来相当熟悉。

英节省的趋势被认为是笑话技术一般特征的声明，尽管这种节省形式在经济上存在某些低效性，因为整个过程伴随着移置。为了解释无意识节省的表面荒谬性，弗洛伊德重新使用了以下经济比较：英笑话技术所做的节约并没有给我们留下深刻印象。它们可能会让我们想起一些家庭主妇节省的方式，她们为了在遥远的市场上买到更便宜的蔬菜而花费时间和金钱。笑话通过其技术节省了什么？不过是将一些新的词汇组合在一起，而这些词汇大部分本来可以毫不费力地出现。相反，它不得不费心去寻找一个能涵盖两个想法的词。实际上，它经常必须先将其中一个想法转换成一个不寻常的形式，以便为与第二个想法的结合提供基础。难道简单地表达这两个想法，即使没有共同的表达形式，不是更简单、更容易，实际上也更经济吗？在言语上的节省难道不正是通过智力努力的支出来平衡的吗？那么，谁通过这种方式节省了？谁又从中受益了呢[193]？英节省转变为消费，无意识表现为理想消费者。问题在于，转喻运动创造了很长的兜圈子，并现实化了消费的倾向。这两种操作的结合，凝缩和移置，节省和消费，因此产生了明显的矛盾，一种经济荒谬性。弗洛伊德的分析表明，笑话生产了一种损失，是为了获得快乐-利润（pleasure-profit）。剩余是在消费和节省相互依存的背景下产生的，只有在表明节省不应被视为过程的最终目标，而应被视为一种消费形式，一种不同于储蓄积累（accumulation of savings）的剩余之生产时，家庭主妇的这个隐喻才恰当。节省的表象掩盖了背景中存在一种不同种类的生产。同样，经济削减和限制的命令是生产剩余的命令的不可避免的另一面。家庭主妇的例子表明，利润不应归因于家庭主妇，而应归因于整个程序。经济之所以能获利，是因为她在看似合理的节约中损失了金钱。

英这种结构性操作被部署在笑话的社会维度。笑话“毕竟，不应该，被描述为毫无意义、毫无目的，因为[它们有着]明确的目的：唤起听众的快乐。”它们引发快乐，而这一特性意味着从有用性到无用性的转变。在这一点上，事情变得复杂，因为与梦相同的缘由。笑话中的快乐是通过迂回方式实现的，并且在快乐的“先前放弃”基础上：“如果我们目前不需要我们的心理装置来提供我们不可缺少的满足之一，我们允许它自身朝着快乐的方向工作，我们试图从其自身的活动中获得快乐[194]。”当心理装置不满足需求时，它就产生快乐，但确定一项活动何时结束，另一项活动何时开始是不可能的。生产需要与有问题的倾向联系起来，这开辟了三种可能性：要么这种倾向是单纯的（这本身就是值得怀疑的；为什么它会被掩盖？），要么笑话服务于敌意或淫秽的倾向（攻击或暴露）。这个过程被力比多投资所标记，这种投资指向了驱力，这个新研究对象与无意识构成相关联，并且可以说是资本主义的新隐喻，无意识的投资者现在已经取代了欲望。欲望不知道它想要什么，并且已经通过转喻从一客体转移到另一客体；然而，驱力“知道”它想要什么。它固定在对象上。

英敌意和淫秽倾向相结合的一个例子是，弗洛伊德提到了下流话（smut），在这里，精神分析的视角遇到了最纯粹的无意识生产及其客体。这也是支持笑话机制的第三者最终出现的地方，揭示了社会联系在产生享乐中的重要性。三个人促成了无意识倾向的显现：叙述者、笑话的目标（target）和听众。弗洛伊德提出了一个重要的观点，即讲述笑话的人与享受其效果的人不是同一个人。享乐的生产被外包给了被动的听众这一边。它绑定到所听到的东西，绑定到不符合任何需求的攻击性和淫秽内容的结合。为了阐释这种结构，弗洛伊德提出了对下流话的详细分析：英我们知道“下流话”指的是：通过言语故意突显性事实和性关系……另一个相关的事实是，下流话是针对特定人的，说话者因性兴奋而提及此人，预期对方听到后会意识到说话者的兴奋，并因此反过来感到性兴奋。对方可能没有感到兴奋，而是感到羞耻或尴尬，这只是一种对兴奋的反应，并且，以一种间接的方式，是对兴奋的承认。因此，下流话最初是针对女性的，可以等同于勾引的尝试。如果一个男人在一群男人中喜欢讲述或听下流笑话，那么原本由于社会禁忌而无法实现的情境，被同时想象出来。听到下流话而发笑的人，就像是在观看性侵犯行为的旁观者那样在笑。英我们可以在这里评论说，一旦能指被视为享乐的装置，语言就显现为无穷尽的下流话。现在弗洛伊德的结论是：英当第一个人认为他的力比多冲动（impulse）被女性压抑（inhibited）时，他对这个第二人发展出敌意，并呼吁最初干涉的第三者作为他的盟友。通过第一人的下流话，女性在第三者面前被暴露，而第三者作为听众，现在已经被他自身力比多的不费力满足所贿赂[195]。英下流话缺乏笑话的形式条件。笑话会绕一个大弯，用一个复杂的隐喻来掩盖性暗示，下流话则公开谈论性，“毫不掩饰的裸露给第一人带来享受，并使第三人发笑”。在这里，弗洛伊德很快发现下流话引向了社会隔离的核心。对于以真诚资产阶级身份发言的弗洛伊德来说，通过下流话获得的满足是普通人的特征，而在上层阶级，只有在它以笑话的形式出现，通过凝缩和移置对淫秽内容进行复杂编码时，下流话才被容忍。在下流话中，我们遇到了隐喻和转喻的零级，而在精致的社交圈中，下流话被转化为典故（allusion）。下流话和笑话之间的共同点仍然是在障碍面前对驱力的满足：“它们绕过这个障碍，以这种方式从原本被障碍封锁的源头中获得快乐[196]。”社会语境表明，第一种情况，即普通人使用下流话，仅在表面上与上层阶级的复杂化不同。工人和农民对驱力的压抑并不弱。当弗洛伊德倾向于得出普通人更接近满足，并且比上层阶级享受更多的结论时，他重复了一个典型的资产阶级偏见，但他也表明抑制是结构性的，无论是下流话还是笑话都受到需求与要求、快乐与享乐、有用与无用之间的差距制约。如果我们想象一种情况，其中叙述者直面下流话的对象，生产享乐的条件就被废除了。在这种情况下，叙述者面对的是阉割。他只能通过第三人享乐，这引入了大他者的维度，就他们与享乐的关系而言，上层阶级和下层阶级之间没有区别。在这两种情况下，为了支持享乐的生产，性与暴力都需要被掩盖，即使这种伪装意味着性被掩盖成性，暴力被掩盖成暴力，如下流话的情况。

英下流话在任何方面都不比精致的笑话更本真。它只是表明，对性的直接涉及，下流话的淫秽性，掩盖了立即满足的不可能性，因为性并不对应任何需求。拉康的公理“没有性关系”恰恰意味着没有性的需求（sexual need）。性是享乐之生产能够发生的那个领域。性的“生殖使用价值”仅仅是虚构。基于这个原因，超我甚至不禁止享乐，它要求享乐，当拉康提出他的最小拟人化超我（prosopopoeia of the superego，Enjoy！）时，他实际上阐述了资本主义命令在心理装置中的回响，资本主义超我的淫秽性。为了更多、恒定和不间断的剩余之生产的贪得无厌的要求，来自大他者中的裂隙，这指向了商品形式对资本主义宇宙中每个客体强加的使用价值和交换价值之间的切割。或者用弗洛伊德对幽默分析的主要经济学教训来表述，笑话中的快乐并不意味着某种失去的享乐被恢复，主体和客体之间的差距被废除，而是享乐是在满足的结构性不可能性背景下产生的。

英弗洛伊德的关键政治洞察是，每个社会秩序都建立在力比多经济基础之上。因此，资本主义效率的重要组成部分来自于它成功地动员了力比多经济的结构性僵局——臭名昭著的“性关系的不存在”——并将其转化为利润的来源。因为其生产逻辑与欲望和驱力相结合，从精神分析的角度来看，坚持认为资本主义的压抑性、欲望或驱力是没有意义的。恰恰相反，资本主义生产方式似乎是历史上第一个为它们的社会实现创造了理想条件的社会和经济体系。难怪弗洛伊德在资本与劳动的关系中找到了对无意识生产模式的最佳阐释。资本主义扩展了其在无意识中的后果，但这并不意味着资本主义就是无意识。

压抑和生产

英驱力无法直接得到满足的原因在于压抑，其中，弗洛伊德发现了另一种可能是最不寻常的无意识劳动的类型：英我们所说的“压抑”，是指使享受未伪装的淫秽变得困难或不可能的力量……我们相信文化和高等教育对压抑的发展有很大的影响，我们假设，在这些条件下，心理组织会经历一种变化……结果，以前感觉愉快的事物现在似乎变得不可接受，并被尽可能的心理力量所排斥。文明的压抑劳动（repression labour，Verdrängungsarbeit）导致了，享乐初始可能性现在已经被我们内在的审查制度所排斥，从而丧失了。但对人类心理而言，所有的放弃都是非常困难的，因此我们发现，带有倾向性的笑话提供了一种撤销放弃和寻回失去之物的手段。当我们在听到一个精致的淫秽笑话时发笑，我们笑的和农民听到粗俗的下流话时笑的是一样的。在这两种情况下，快乐都源自同一源泉[197]。英弗洛伊德的描述立即让人回想起福柯在他的作品中批评的“压抑假设”。一方面，压抑的劳动服务于更高的倾向，这些倾向努力维护文化理想和制度；另一方面，原始的但被排除的原乐，享乐的直接可能性，必须为了文化进步而被放弃。笑话等文化现象，创造了绕过禁令并重新获得一部分丧失的和被禁止的原乐的印象/感觉（impression）。这是弗洛伊德压抑理论想要提出的最终观点吗？引用的段落当然支持这一点，因为弗洛伊德将驱力的存在置于文化之前，从而提出了原乐之前的原乐的假设，一种原初的享乐，后来被法律的介入所禁止和扼杀。弗洛伊德后来的理论努力试图将这种假设的原乐具身化在原父（primordial father）的神话形象中，但他的系统发生学推测（phylogenetic speculations）被一个复杂的结构所标记，这种结构质疑了简化的批判性阅读。在《图腾与禁忌》中，弗洛伊德主要讨论的是法律诞生于原初的弑父（patricide），原父显然是原初原乐的人格化，但他同样是一个强加原初禁令的实例——只有他拥有原乐的权利，而不是他的儿子们，后者即遭受淫荡父权暴力的主体，在这种暴力中，原乐和律法无从区分。原父只能代表原乐之前的原乐，就他同时也是律法之前的律法而言。这种原乐与律法的融合使他成为一个无法满足的实例，要求人类部落的所有其他成员声明放弃（renunciation）。

英弗洛伊德对这一史前父亲形象的描述因此表明，原父的两个主要特征仅仅是对与笑话、暴力和淫荡相关的两种倾向的夸张：对儿子们的暴力和他对所有女性的淫荡权利。原父字面上就是一个笑话——但是一个弗洛伊德认真对待的笑话。这种推测性的讨论并没有解决将弗洛伊德的理论推向认识论僵局的困境，而是将现存的力比多经济的悖论浓缩在了一个假想的角色中。列维-斯特劳斯和拉康已经认识到，在弗洛伊德从民族学（ethnological）和进化背景中采纳的原始弑父故事中，存在一个科学神话。但在弗洛伊德的案例中，这一神话成为了马克思努力在原始积累下解决的问题的一个奇特的结构等价物，一种历史虚构，旨在概述决定主观与社会现实两者的现代对抗的起源。

英压抑假设虽然诱人，但它和原父的神话并不能成功解决弗洛伊德在无意识劳动中遇到的所有内在矛盾，即它产生了快乐利润（pleasure-gain）并创造了明显的绕远路，显然破坏了直接满足。压抑的劳动，一方面，在凝缩和移置的成就之间呈现出分裂，另一方面，在压抑和审查之间呈现出分裂。无意识生产受限于这种失调，表明至少有一部分压抑质疑了将其简化为从更高层次的心理或文化实例（自我和超我）对被压抑的欲望和驱力（本我）起作用的力量的理解。作为一种生产性的无意识劳动，甚至对于其成就的多样性的最一般描述，压抑必须与其在压抑假设中被赋予的含义——即压制（suppression）和压迫（oppression）——区分开来。这种误解肯定受到了弗洛伊德对压抑最初解释的鼓励，但在将压抑翻译成英语和法语时，译者显著地听到了压迫和压制的含义，从而加强了这种误解。

英拉康回归弗洛伊德的主要成就之一在于重新肯定了压抑在生产性劳动方面相对于被压抑物的首要性，从而为区分压抑、压制或压迫提供了必要的基础。压抑可能为压迫创造条件，但它并不是压迫的同义词。家庭和社会远非压抑的实例和机构，它们是压抑的产物，因此具有与被压抑的驱力和欲望相同的地位。一旦压抑与压迫区分开来，它的生产性特征就显得双重。弗洛伊德关于笑话的书已经表明，压抑在原乐之生产方面起着至关重要的作用，而后来的元心理学著作则认为，压抑也构成了被压抑物（the repressed）。像异化一样，压抑本身在构成性压抑和被构成的压抑上也是内在双重的，弗洛伊德在“原初压抑”（Urverdrängung）的概念中解决了构成性压抑的问题[198]。这个概念无疑强调了压抑的先验特性，这立即让人想起结构主义的象征先验主义（the structuralist transcendentalism of the symbolic）。但是原初压抑更进一步，因为它还暴露了压抑内在的双重结构，从象征结构的自动性中，它推导出两种生产性成就。

英在考虑压抑对于精神分析与马克思主义相遇的意义之前，有必要回顾弗洛伊德压抑理论的基本论述。压抑被揭示为一种折衷过程（compromise procedure）——Mittelding，即中间物（intermediate thing）——介于逃避（escape）和谴责（condemnation）之间，这已经剥夺了后来对弗洛伊德解读中最终被赋予的完全否定（exclusively negative）的含义。它既不避免被压抑的倾向，也不拒绝其满足。核心问题在于为什么在一开始这种倾向被压抑，而自发的回答很可能是其满足会引起不快乐。但情况恰恰不是这样：英它的发生的一个必要条件显然必须是驱力达成其目标时产生的是不快乐而非快乐。但我们很难想象这样的情况。不存在这样的驱力：驱力的满足总是令人快乐的[lustvoll]。我们不得不假设某些特殊的情况，某种过程，通过这个过程满足的快乐被转变为不快乐[199]。英每一种满足都是充满快感的（lustvoll）；没有不生产快乐的满足。为了应对这一困境，驱力和快乐的概念需要被彻底质疑。

英弗洛伊德的驱力概念即使在今天也仍然存在争议。就像“劳动力”一样，这个术语是从生理学和生物学背景，甚至从力学中借用过来的，但它描述了一个现象，即驱力超越了生理学肉体的限制（even if traversing the biological body, reaches beyond its limits）。在自然主义背景下，驱力代表一种身体上的需要，可以追溯到生理机制。因此，弗洛伊德区分了指向准自然需要的驱力（例如，饥饿和口渴）——这可能是Trieb最初被翻译为“本能”的原因——其中压抑不在考虑范围内的；以及偏离这种明显的自然满足并臣服于压抑的驱力（弗洛伊德将性归入这一类）：英让我们考虑这样一个情况，像饥饿这样的驱力刺激（drive stimulus）没有得到满足。这时，它变得迫切（imperative），并只能通过满足它的行动来缓解；它维持着一种对需求的持续紧张。在这个案例中，似乎根本不涉及任何形式的压抑[200]。英在这种生理学意义上，因此与有机体的保存（preservation）相关，驱力可以完全化约为需求，并且不能成为压抑的目标。它只能通过相应的行动（如吃饭、喝水等）得到满足。要求进行压抑之劳动的驱力太过象征性，以至于不能是生物学的或生理学的。这，而不是别的，就是弗洛伊德声称驱力“对我们来说是一个在心理和躯体之间边界的概念”或者说是“源自有机体内部并延伸到心智的那种刺激的心理表征”（the psychical representative of the stimuli originating from within the organism and reaching the mind）的含义[201]。这种对驱力的谨慎定位——既非生理学也非心理学——充分表明弗洛伊德旨在超越经典的身心二元论（mind-body dualism），但也因此没有陷入活力论一元论（vitalist monism）。驱力是一条生理和力比多之间的边界，从内部穿越和分割身体（The drive is the border that from within traverses and splits the body on the physiological and the libidinal），以至于我们处理的是某种包括了否定性的矛盾一元论（conflictual monism），恰恰是表征的否定性，将能指的物质性和依赖其自动性的因果性带入了视野。作为一条内在的边界，它使生物学与语言学含糊不清，驱力仍然是一个身体现象，甚至看起来与它所转译或表征的需求无法区分。将生理刺激与其表征相融合，驱力成为语言自动性的物质回响，但它也是能指的介入在有机体自我保存的倾向中所隔离的东西。弗洛伊德的探询围绕这个认识论僵局：因为回响太过物质性，它不能被宣称为一个唯心主义实体或科学虚构，但是因为它的满足似乎引起了不快，这与生理需求的情况不同，某些东西违反了满足机制。这个丑闻最终暴露了驱力和有机体需求之间最小的差距：驱力是对它们的要求的象征性孤立（the drive is the symbolic isolation of their demand），它们所包含的为了满足的命令（the imperative for satisfaction that they contain）。从其重复的有机背景中分离出来，对满足的要求就获得了自己的生命，这就是满足的不快乐方面进入画面的地方。

英弗洛伊德对驱力的本体论地位持谨慎态度。在他的《New Introductory Lectures》中，他著名地写道，驱力可以比作神话生物，而他的驱力理论可以比作古代神话。当然，驱力是一种假设，旨在解释这样一个事实：制约（conditions）意识与无意识之间分裂的能指装置，并不追求有用的目标、需求的满足，而是倾向于直接的快乐-增益。驱力命名了能指的一系列物质后果的倾向，而这些后果并没有在分析师眼前显现为积极实体：“在我们的工作中，我们一刻也不能忽视它们，但我们从未确信我们清楚地看到了它们”[202]。驱力承担了与物理学中的“能量”相同的本体论和认识论地位。其假设是不可或缺的，但人们永远无法直接面对它，只能观察到它的后果，首先是快感增益的生产，以及快乐向不快乐的转化。驱力的满足的可见性可以比作熵的可见性，只有当科学将数学的形式语言置于物理世界之上时，熵才能被观察到。生理需求的显现进一步模糊了驱力的可见性，或者更确切地说，因为所有的身体需求都是通过驱力作为其特权表征来引导的，它们不再不成问题。驱力是“traduttore-traditore”（翻译者-背叛者）的典型案例。它以一种不忠实的生产方式表征（翻译）了看似自然的需求，从而背叛了其满足。

英翻译首要地生产了快乐状态的变化。没有任何驱力的满足不会引起快乐，尽管这种快乐不再是一种随着紧张度减少而出现的情感。我们可以回到马克思在《Grundrisse》中提到的两种饥饿的例子。与满足饥饿相关联的快乐与附着在吃这一行为上的快乐是不同的。两种命令的交织，即需求和要求，在满足生理需求中掩盖了这样一个事实：驱力的要求是恒定的，它在需求之外重复满足之命令。过于简单的想法是，将一个贪得无厌地吞噬生食的饥饿视为一种前象征的自然本能（pre-symbolic natural instinct），它与对食物的文化化消费相对立。赤裸的本能性生命（Bare instinctual life）是对发生在生理需求明显满足背后的事物的想象性呈现，是超越每一次满足尝试的命令之持存。弗洛伊德没有忽视驱力这一特征：“一种驱力...从来不是以给予瞬间冲击的力量那样运作，而是作为一种恒定的力量”[203]。命令从具体参照物中分离出来，因此依赖于能指的自动性的要求的自动性，使得驱力与每一种本应该是自然或本能需求不符（discrepancy）[204]。口腔驱力的要求，在对营养的需求中被独立出来，持存在不同且表面上无关的活动背后，如吃、吸烟、说话、吸吮等。由于这种持存性，驱力的恒定的力量只能被体验为不快乐，更准确地说，作为肉欲（Lust），即不能被感受为快乐的快乐[205]（die nicht als solche empfunden werden kann，pleasure that cannot be felt as such）。只能被体验为不快乐的快乐——用这个表述，弗洛伊德为拉康关于原乐的概念提供了最好的定义。在需求中，不快乐先于其满足；在驱力中，不快乐伴随着满足，并且就是快乐的特权形式。满足现在发生在紧张度的增加中，而这种紧张度是由于贪得无厌的Drang（pleasure，压力），它是“所有驱力共有的；实际上，它就是它们的本质”[206]。驱力作为生理需求的表征归结为命令性的能指，S1，原乐的被压抑的能指（the repressed signifier of jouissance）。

英这里驱力的第二个本质特征进入画面，它阐明了马克思在赤裸的饥饿与文化化的饥饿之间的对立实际上凸显了驱力的两个内在方面，而不是自然与文化的对立。弗洛伊德理解了，在持续的压力下，“劳动力的数量，或它所表征的对劳动的要求的度量”（amount of force or the measure of the demand for labour [207]。在驱力的核心，存在着一个对劳动的永久性要求，劳动力的表征，因此弗洛伊德尝试构建驱力的能量学。这种对劳动的要求解释了无意识满足中快乐与不快乐的同一与差异。此时，弗洛伊德对资本主义的早期类比找到了另一种重复。因为无意识分裂在资本家和劳动者之间，满足的过程必然在两端都体验到，即快乐与不快乐。然而，享乐者并不是主体，因为正如弗洛伊德的分析一再表明的，不存在原乐的主体。只有劳动的主体，对劳动的要求的接受者（the addressee of the demand for labour）。没有劳动的命令，就没有原乐的命令。因此，“劳动！”是超我命令“享乐！”的真正含义。弗洛伊德关于无意识劳动理论的核心再次凸显，因为马克思将政治经济学劳动价值理论重新构建为唯物主义的主体理论，这是第一次确立了这两种要求的相互依存，这两种要求可以和资本联系起来：对剩余价值的不断要求和对劳动的不断需求[208]。

英需求与要求之间的差异最终在客体的层面上反映出来。与需求不同，驱力似乎没有客体：英驱力的客体是一个事物，关于这个事物，或通过这个事物，驱力可以达到其目的（aim）。它是驱力中最易变的要素，并且并不原初地与驱力相联系，只有因其特别适宜于使满足成为可能，才被归属于驱力[209]。英拉康后来引用这段话来解释客体小a如何关联于驱力之蒙太奇（montage of the drive）。然而，我们不能忽视一个事实，弗洛伊德——在拉康的发展之前——再次暗示了内容与形式之间的差异，这已经支持了欲望之机制。驱力在客体-形式（object-form）中达到其满足，这对应于差异的自动性，并且基于这种移置，对满足的要求可以变成命令。驱力变成了一个没有终点的象征机器，为了消费而消费客体（即，提取剩余），并指定了需求的永久性失调（Entstellung）、变形和移位。

英现在让我们转向压抑的悖论。弗洛伊德写道，压抑不是一种原始的防御机制，它只有在“意识与无意识心理活动之间发生了明显的分裂[210]”之后才能变得有效。压抑已经预设了无意识，它的功能不太在于压制、抑制或阻碍满足，而在于让驱力保持远离意识。压抑的悖论在于，压抑是次要的；尽管它对被压抑物是构成性的。它只能在意识与无意识之间心理装置的分裂已经被建立好后出现，但它是这种分裂的必要条件。原初压抑的假设旨在解决压抑与被压抑物之间的关系中的悖论：英我们有理由假设存在一种原初压抑，压抑的第一阶段，它在于驱力的心理（观念）表征被拒绝进入意识。这样，固着（fixation）就建立了；所讨论的表征从那时起保持不变，并且驱力仍然附着于它[211]。英被压抑的东西，不是某种原始的本能性实体，这种实体会被语言的介入所抑制，而是驱力的能指，这个能指的目的是原乐，并且将原本的生理需求向象征性要求的转译依赖于它。弗洛伊德再次使用了更易于理解的压抑假设的语言，但实际上他指向的是能指的自动性。原初压抑的实际成就是主人能指的生产，主人能指与差异系统的自动性是同义词（synonymous），是要求之能指和原乐之能指。因此，原初压抑面对着一个不可能的任务，即检查在形成状态中的被压抑物（the repressed in statu nascendi），被压抑物的起源，这最终与语言的起源相同。压抑结构的描述以如下方式继续：英压抑的第二阶段，恰当的压抑（repression proper），影响的是被压抑的表征的心理衍生物（mental derivatives of the repressed representative），或者是那些起源于其他地方、与其建立了联想连接的思想链（or such trains of thought as, originating elsewhere, have come into associative connection with it）。由于这种联想，这些想法经历了与最初被压抑的东西相同的命运。因此，恰当的压抑实际上是一种后续压力（Nachdrängen，after-pressure）。此外，仅仅强调从意识方向对被压抑内容的排斥是错误的；同样重要的是，最初被压抑的内容对可以与之建立联系的一切所施加的吸引力。如果这两种力量不相互协作，如果没有什么先前被压抑的东西准备好接收意识所排斥的东西，那么趋向于压抑的趋势可能就会失败[212]。英被构成的压抑，压抑的第二阶段，是一种生产性的无意识劳动。所有其他形式的无意识劳动都可以归结为压抑，压抑如今表现为驱力的满足，而不是其压制或阻碍。这里又出现了另一个复杂性。我们不仅仅是在处理两种不同的压抑，其中一个在过去，另一个在现在。历史性解读忽视了压抑的拓扑学方面，这与其内在的双重性有关：为了有压抑，必须至少有两个压抑。单一的压抑无法构成弗洛伊德精确描述的关于吸引和排斥的关系。每一次具体的压抑行为的内在时刻都是原初压抑（被压抑物的构成）和压抑的劳动（对被压抑的倾向的满足）。这种双重结构可以与能指链相比较。产生意识和无意识之间分裂的切口是加倍的，作为对剩余-原乐的被压抑的要求之能指（S1-a），以及作为与另一个能指的差异（S1-S2），切口开启了无意识生产并表征了“对劳动的要求量”，即劳动力。压抑活动包含了能指的两个轴，表征和生产。这种内在的双重性揭示了弗洛伊德明确强调的视差，他提醒说，除了来自意识的排斥，人们也应该同样承认来自原初压抑的吸引点，即主人能指。从意识的角度看，压抑表现为一种防御机制，以压迫的意义进行压抑。压抑假设将这一视角绝对化，我们可以在新自由主义中找到其最当代的政治例证。难道新自由主义意识形态不是围绕着这样一个观念，即市场包含着需要通过放松管制来解放的“创造性潜力”？自由市场的概念调动了压抑假设，通过它，资本主义误导并中和了现代解放运动的政治激进性[213]。只有从主体的立场，即弗洛伊德关于无意识劳动理论的立场和马克思对拜物教的批判的立场，压抑才能表现为一种操作，通过剩余客体和异化主体在具体形式中的双重生产来调节驱力之满足的操作。现在，驱力不再表现为被剥夺了其直接满足，排斥/拒绝（repulsion，rejection）变成了吸引/满足（attraction，satisfaction），不快乐变成了一种特定形式的快乐。

英这个问题与马克思并非无关，因为在压抑的双重结构中，弗洛伊德遇到了与资本积累相同的问题。当马克思转向资本主义的历史条件时，他重新构建了古典政治经济学在其为资本主义辩护中所使用的原始积累问题。马克思揭示了它的虚构特性，但随后也在资本主义逻辑的历史生成、旧守财奴精神向现代资本主义精神的转变中，重新提供了它的合理解释，它加深了统治的社会关系，通过将之根植于事物之间的关系（rooting them in the very relations between things）。对主人的现代物化（modern reification），即，从旧的神圣君主形象中脱离出来，不可避免地带来了对主体的物化。

英马克思对资本主义起源的思考在精神分析学上的价值在于，他揭露了原乐与意识形态之间的联系，更具体地说，是经济自由主义植根于享乐之主体的虚构——这一虚构在当今的新自由主义条件下仍然保存完好。当然，原始积累的重要性众所周知，并且已经被多位作者讨论过[214]。马克思从积累与生产之间关系的结构性悖论出发。正如压抑与被压抑物的情况一样，压抑构成了它同时预设的被压抑物，对积累的分析包含了一个恶性循环，其中生产和积累相互指称：没有先前剩余的生产就没有资本的积累，但同样，没有先前资本的积累也没有剩余的生产。

英马克思首先指出一个事实，原始积累，正如政治经济学中所使用的，包含了一个道德教训（moral lesson），因此在理论上承担了原罪的角色。它也因此承担了神话的功能，因为它试图解释资本积累的无法达到的历史起源——这一点只能通过虚构的结构和幻想的方式来理解。这个故事基于如下两个预设：原始无产阶级（proto-proletarian）的原乐和原始资本家（proto-capitalist）的放弃：英在很久以前，有两种人；一种是勤劳、聪明，尤其是节俭的精英；另一种是懒惰的流氓（rascals，Lumpen）[215]，挥霍着他们的财产，在放荡的生活中更甚……就这样，前者积累了财富，后者最终除了自己的皮以外没有什么可出卖的了。从这个原罪开始，大多数贫穷的人，尽管他们劳动，但如今除了他们自己没什么可以出卖的，而少数人的财富不断增加，尽管他们早已停止了工作[216]。英在最开始，有禁欲者（the ascetic）和消费者（the consumer）：放弃之主体（the subject of renunciation）和享乐之主体（subject of enjoyment）。政治经济学神话因此试图解释剩余的肯定的和否定的起源：剩余价值，源自禁欲（abstinence）并具身化在最初的积累起来的财富中，以及劳动力，源自过度（excess），神话声称它不可避免地产生债务。禁欲有助于积累剩余，最终使少数人能够占有生产资料，而原乐创造了否定因素，最终将迫使大多数人出卖自己的身体。对于政治经济学来说，这个场景听起来完全合理：资本主义的祖先通过个人牺牲积累了最小限度的财富，因此，他们的当代后代似乎有权利无限制地继续从中获利。同时，无产者要为自己的悲惨（misery）负责，因为他们的祖先所挥霍的超出了他们所拥有的，挥霍了他们的一切乃至更多（ihr alles und mehr）。这个看似微不足道的表述至关重要，因为它设想了原乐和债务的相互依存，似乎是从宗教中采纳的，因此马克思将原始积累比作原罪的寓言。

英政治经济学神话显著地影响了最近合法化紧缩措施的尝试（attempts to legitimise austerity measures），正如其他人已经注意到的[217]。南半球被呈现为享乐主体的空间，而不合理的（absurd）国债则将其变成了剩余人口的绿洲；而其对立面，北半球，特别是德国，似乎成了节俭/储蓄（saving）之地，只有在经济增长锚定在对原乐的持续放弃的条件下，一个成功故事才是可能的。当然，每个人都可以看到实际情况恰恰相反：强加的储蓄启动了一个负面螺旋，所产生的债务比可能偿还的要多。这种债务不是一个寻求偿还的道德义务，而实际上具有生产性功能：紧缩措施应该创造经济灾难，这将加强公民与负债主体这一结构性功能的联系。这一最新发展再次证实了这样的论点：原始积累不是一个过去的过程，而是现在的内在时刻，它再生产了资本主义积累和剥削的可能性条件。它指定了将个体构成为价值主体的话语性过程的根源，正如原初压抑解决了能指自动性的根源，通过它，无意识之主体和剩余享乐之主体的双重生产启动了。意识和无意识之间的分裂是弗洛伊德解决这种自动性的方式。

英根据政治经济学故事的内在偏见，劳动者继续享乐（消磨时光、变得更加负债累累），而资本家继续储蓄（增加他的财富）。马克思对这一场景进行了最小的纠正。“资本家主体在一开始无疑是一个债务主体，但从未作为一个主体去享乐。换句话说，资本家主体性的形象并不是从某种假定的原乐之主体转变为劳动力中显现——正如政治经济学家所鼓吹的——而是从原乐本身的特定转变中显现。资本家的禁欲理论强调了这一发展：英积累，积累！这就是摩西和先知们说的！“勤劳提供了储蓄积累的材料”（Industry furnishes the material which saving accumulates）。因此，储蓄，储蓄，也就是说，将尽可能多的剩余价值或剩余产品重新转化为资本（reconvert……into capital）！为了积累而积累，为了生产而生产：这是古典经济学在其统治时期表达资产阶级历史使命的公式……在古典经济学的眼中，如果无产者仅仅是生产剩余价值的机器，那么资本家也仅仅是将这种剩余价值转化为剩余资本的机器[218]。英马克思的纠正关注于在现代守财奴精神中已经存在的积累与储蓄之间的联系的外在化（externalisation）。在系统的根基中，存在着禁欲的命令，这可以直接转译为负债的命令：主体的义务是承担并内化（interiorise）由系统之原乐所创造的债务——并正因为如此，马克思评论说国债是唯一进入所有现代民族手中的财富，即，属于每个人的东西，没有人有权从中豁免自己。当仅仅是少数人人格化了系统性原乐时，劳动力成为了资本主义宇宙中唯一普遍的主体立场。原始积累的政治经济学故事包含了一丝扭曲的真理，表明没有先于放弃的原乐，但是放弃与原乐之生产有强烈相关性，两者都是彻底普遍的负债（both through generalised indebting）。

英在批评政治经济学的起源神话之后，马克思提出了自己的原始积累的合理化变体。在这种重建中，它承担了历史编纂小说的地位，生产者与生产资料的分离是通过“血与火”完成的，这种构成性的暴力逐渐将封建的统治和服从关系转变为资本主义式的。我不打算深入探讨马克思对资本主义起源的重建，其准确性和普遍有效性仍然是一个讨论的话题[219]。更重要的是马克思对资本主义历史起源的概述的逻辑背景，在许多方面预示了弗洛伊德关于压抑的拓扑学描述。在马克思的解读中，起源的关键部分在于国债的发明。他强调前现代宗教债务，仍然嵌入在其神秘化的形而上学意义中，转变为了现代债务，建立在公共信用之上，并变成了被量化的和无意义的抽象物。这种转变是通过改变封建社会联系的逻辑来完成的，拉康将其为主人话语：英发展的起始点——既产生了工资-劳动者（wage-labourer），也产生了资本家——是对工人的奴役。进步在于这种奴役形式的变革，在封建剥削向资本主义剥削的转变之中[220]。英形式上的改变发明了一种新的负债形式，它不再存在于对封建领主、君主或地球上任何其他神权代表的经济-形而上学根据的服从中，而是存在于经济不平等中，这种不平等在看似无问题和具体的交换行为中被编纂成法典（codified）。资本主义世界观的真相是普遍的负债，由诸如自由和平等这种被掏空了的政治范畴所生产。国债和公共信用的发明和社会实施相当于一种新的话语性生产，但没有废除旧的统治和不平等结构。它仅仅将前现代的农奴转变为抽象的劳动力，一个生产剩余价值的机器，并且在同一举动中引入了一个新的主人形象，资本家，他人格化了将剩余产品转化为资本的机器。这种转变将剩余产品整合到社会联系中，通过对客体的拜物教化引入了社会关系的一种新的拜物教化形式。在同一举动中，封建主人被剥夺了他的拜物教属性，这也意味着新的资本主义主人不再依赖于具体的人格化。主宰（Mastery）变成了一种抽象物，具身化在进入经济领域的每一个客体中：商品、货币和金融抽象物。如果国王有两个身体，凡人的和崇高的，那么资本家只有一个，但因此被赋予了资本的灵魂，正如马克思所声称的。

英在资本主义中，主体既不欠尘世（secular）的债，也不欠神圣主人的债，而是欠经济系统本身的债。因此，资本主义并不是像马克斯·韦伯所论证的那样，是新教精神的实现，而是沃尔特·本雅明在其著名的批评性注释中指出的对欠债的崇拜（a cult of indebting）[221]。如果我们想要保持资本主义与宗教逻辑之间的联系——这仍然说得通，因为债务的结构性功能在两种情况中都建立在道德和经济的模糊性上——但我们必须考虑到宗教的某种退步：从天启的制度化宗教到同样制度化的崇拜（通过中央银行、公司、跨国公司、政治的三驾马车等）。马克思在将资本主义社会联系化约为商品拜物教时，他瞄准了这种退步：从自认为是真理之宗教的宗教，本质上是“真正的宗教”（拉康语）的宗教，转变为“新-异教”（neo-paganism），一种非理性的、世俗化的对资本的自我增值（self-valorising）能力的信仰。

英随着主人向抽象物的转变，抽象的债务不再作为主人与农奴之间社会联系的基础，而是转而支撑起公民与国家之间的社会联系：英公共信用体系，即国债体系，其起源可追溯至中世纪的热那亚和威尼斯，整个欧洲都受到了它的影响……国债，即国家的外在化（Veriiusserung，externalisation）——无论该国是专制的、立宪的还是共和的——标志着资本主义时代的特征。所谓的国民财富中，真正进入现代人集体所有的部分就是国债。因此，作为必然的结果，现代学说认为一个国家越富有，它的债务就越深。公共信用成为资本的信条（credo）。随着国家性的债务-生产，对国债的不信任取代了反对圣灵的罪，这是不可饶恕的[222]。英随着国债的诞生，马克思对原始积累的分析无疑改变了其性质。虽然对英国农村人口的构成性暴力的描述仍然停留在想象性的历史坐标中，并且处于压抑假设的视野内，就像弗洛伊德早期关于压抑的叙述一样，但是对国债的关注朝向了在社会生产方式中的逻辑置换（logical displacement），这不可避免地包含了对“作为特定的资本主义主体性形式的劳动力”的生产：唯一对应于抽象债务体系和现代信用系统的主体。

英国债的发明和相应的主体性生产揭示了马克思在“国家外在化”这一术语中指出的资本主义异化形式的核心。资本主义国家简单地就是一种更深层次的构成性异化的制度化形式，它规定了经济“抽象物”、资本和劳动力之间的逻辑关系。国家在国债中的外在化伴随着其内在化，在这个意义上，它塑造了现代主体性的本性。本质上基于负债，并代表国债本身，现代国家将每个公民置于债务人（debtor）的位置，而债权人（creditor）的位置则由资本的社会机构来承担：中央银行。在这一点上，变得最为明显的是，现代国家的兴起不可避免地伴随着一个超国家权力的诞生，这一权力属于金融机构，并且本质上是威权主义的[223]。

英将公民置于债务人位置的等价物是将主体转变为可量化和可剥削的主体性，这种主体性是预先负债的，并且也是作为这样而被生产出来的。通过这种方式，马克思拒绝了在抽象债务主体之前幻想性投射某种假设的原乐主体。他对政治经济学神话的合理化表明，资本主义对前现代宗教债务的去神秘化和量化创造了一个更有效的抽象普遍性——国债——它不让任何主体脱离其影响范围，从而引入了一种新的“圣灵”：即建立在生产性负债的消极螺旋之上的社会联系，从这种螺旋中升起了资本的幽灵性和表面上的自动性。

英重复一遍，马克思对原始积累的合理化变体中所涉及的问题是构成性异化问题，在这一层面上可以观察到资本主义主体性的生产[224]。抽象债务和抽象劳动因此成为主体不可分割的两个方面。由于资本主义生产方式的结构是内在双重的，对原始积累概念的批判性占有和合理化确实显示出与弗洛伊德关于原始压抑的概念严格同源的特征，在这一概念中，构成性异化的主体性的生产同样居于核心地位。即使马克思和弗洛伊德可能按字面意义采取了起源的概念，他们仍然提醒人们注意到一个结构和时间上的悖论，这一悖论通过回溯性因果性的概念破坏了历史的线性表述。因此，所讨论的史前起源结果更多是当下内在的史前史，回溯性地投射到过去，并作为资本主义生产关系不断重新建立的内在条件在当下起作用[225]。在对历史起源的表面探索背后，马克思和弗洛伊德提出了关于原因的逻辑问题和唯物主义问题，这个问题使负债的主体和无意识主体得以存在。

英支撑着资本主义结构和效率的积累与生产之间的悖论关系，确实可能使这种生产方式成为一个恶性循环，似乎无法逃脱。同时，这个悖论也是其结构性泄露和永久不稳定的原因，预示着相反的现象，即系统迫在眉睫的崩溃。由政治经济学批判和精神分析所共享的拜物教和症状这对概念，恰恰解答了资本主义这两种相对立的现象。

CHAPTER 2

The Capitalist Unconscious:

A Return to Freud

WELTANSCHAUUNG

中When it comes to Freud’s relation to politics, notably to Marxism, we cannot ignore his self-proclaimed indifference in political matters. However, as soon we go through his writings on culture and religion, we notice that this indifference is expressed in a rather unusual way. Freud never simply avoids political issues. Instead, he proposes a new form of addressing them, through distortions and displacements, a form that corresponds to the psychoanalytic method and to the nature of its object. It would therefore be wrong to see in the unconscious a retreat from the social into a sphere of strictly private life that has absolutely no connection to social reality. Yet it would be equally false to presuppose the existence of a collective unconscious, a container of universal cultural artefacts and archetypes. The Freudian unconscious is clearly more sophisticated. It abolishes the division of the subjective and the social, the private and the public, albeit not in the sense of the slogan ‘the personal is the political’ but in the sense that the existence and the formal mechanisms of the unconscious depend on the same structures, which determine the functioning of social links.

中Both Lacan’s axiom ‘the unconscious is structured like a language’ and his later claims that the unconscious ‘ex-sists’ only in discourse, address this singular status of the unconscious within social structures. This implies that the subject of the unconscious - the subject in its dependency on the signifier, and not the subject of cognition - is the subject of politics. Psychoanalysis isolates the political subject from its ideological fictions, be it homo legalis, the abstract subject of right, homo economicus, the no less abstract subject of political economy, citoyen, etc. With this distinction, the flip side to the constitution of the social is brought to light: the discursive ex-sistence of the unconscious, its insistence as an extimate discursive consequence uncovers the point, in which the given social order determines the production of subjectivity, and names the instability of the given order, the point from which emancipatory or revolutionary politics inevitably needs to depart in order to produce social change. This is, as we shall see in the following section, the main point of Marx’s determination of the proletariat as a social symptom, this concrete social embodiment of the universal subjective position in capitalism and the only possible point from which the abolition of the capitalist mode of production can be brought about. The motto shared between Marx and Freud would therefore be: the impersonal is the political - namely the impersonal core of the personal.

中The difference between Freud and Lacan in these matters is nevertheless striking. While Lacan never avoids polemical confrontation with the logic of capital, Freud barely addresses capitalism under its proper name. Instead, he prefers to speak about culture, thereby giving the discussion an apparently neutral, scientific and sociological tone. Another example is ideology. In his works, Freud undoubtedly develops a critique of ideology but under the screen-notion of Weltanschauung (worldview), an expression that covers everything from philosophy and politics to art and religion, designating a specific tendency in the constitution of reality, its totalisation and meaningful framing. Freud’s discussion of Marxism will take place within this perspective and within the broader epistemological framework of the distinction between the worldview knowledge and the scientific knowledge. Freud’s entire published work contains one single reflection on Marxism, and even this turns out rather disappointing, as he approaches it with the highest possible reserve. Freud expresses his lack of competence in discussing the variety of Marxist orientations and focuses merely on the so-called worldview Marxism, which enables him to envisage a logical similarity between Marxism and religion. Of course, most Marxists will be horrified by this idea. But before passing any judgment it is worth looking at the broader context of Freud’s take on the general worldview mechanisms.

中We find these developments in the closing chapter of Freud’s New Introductory Lectures on Psychoanalysis. The collection was published at a dramatic historical moment, 1933, four years after the economic crash and the same year in which Hitler was elected German chancellor; it was also a time when no one could ignore the dramatic failure of the Soviet revolution with the dominance of Stalinism. The lectures address a fictional audience and revise Freud’s metapsychological theories. The chapter on Weltanschauung forms an exception, both epistemologically and critically, since behind the discussion of the antagonisms between science and religion Freud simultaneously delivers his critical responses to the already widespread Freudo-Marxism, whose enfant terrible at the time was none other than Wilhelm Reich.

中When Freud insists that all efforts should be made to inscribe psychoanalysis in the modern scientific paradigm, he implicitly condemns the efforts in his broader circle to shape psychoanalysis in accordance with an actually existing political worldview. Certainly one could argue that the political readings of psychoanalysis are not unrelated to Freud’s discussions of social mechanisms, which already produced some sort of spontaneous political philosophy. In the face of works such as Group Psychology and the Analysis of the Ego, on which the Frankfurt school later grounded its critique of totalitarian personality, or Civilisation and Its Discontents, which guided Marcuse’s critique of social repression, it is all the more surprising that Freud concludes not only that there is no such thing as a psychoanalytic worldview but even that every immediate application of psychoanalysis to politics should be avoided. Where does this reserve come from?

中The answer lies in the logic of worldviews, as the lecture in question outlines it. Freud begins his critique by enumerating and discussing the general features of every worldview. His definition sounds classical from the outset:中In my opinion, then, a Weltanschauung is an intellectual construction, which solves all the problems of our existence uniformly on the basis of one overriding hypothesis, which, accordingly, leaves no question unanswered and in which everything that interests us finds its fixed place. It will easily be understood that the possession of a Weltanschauung of this kind is among the ideal wishes of human beings.中The main achievement of a worldview thus consists in totalising reality and thereby providing its meaningful interpretation. It does not leave any questions open and situates the variety of human interests under one general hypothesis (Annahme, presupposition). At first glance, the definition does not seem to bring any novelties to the understanding of worldview mechanisms. Yet such novelty lies in the conclusion. A unifying worldview stands in a specific relation to unconscious desire, whose reality manifests itself through the construction of a given worldview. A worldview, then, appears as a neutral interpretation of the world, a construction of reality, but behind this interpretation Freud reveals a mechanism that establishes the conditions for the satisfaction of desire, a dispositif that supports its undisturbed fulfilment.

中In this respect, the critique of worldview mechanisms reaches back to the earliest psychoanalytic discoveries regarding the mechanisms that satisfy an unconscious tendency through the production of symbolic formations. Freud aims here notably at dreams, which are nothing less than intellectual formations that codify a demand for satisfaction, so that he extends his early wish-fulfilment theory to the way discursive mechanisms construct intersubjective reality. More precisely, through his worldview critique, Freud points out the place where the unconscious should be situated. Desire is not simply a psychological formation but the name of a specific structural dynamic that needs to be placed on the very line that joins subjective and social reality. Desire is the border beyond which there is strictly speaking no other reality: the same structure and the same formal mechanisms work in the unconscious and in the social link. Freud’s worldview critique is therefore not to be rejected as yet another psychologism.

中Worldviews thus raise a logical problem that Freud approaches through the work of interpretation, which amounts to the totalisation of reality. He thereby evokes the famous lines from Heine, in which the poet mocks philosophy:中Life and the world's too fragmented for me!
A German professor can give me the key.
He puts life in order with skill magisterial,
Builds a rational system for better or worse;
With nightcap and dressing-gown scraps for material
He chinks up the holes in the universe.中Freud already used the very same reference in the Interpretation of Dreams to illustrate one of the main achievements of the dream work, secondary elaboration, through which unconscious labour combines the loosely linked dream material in a whole and narrated structure. The philosopher is thus comparable to the unconscious labourer, whose main task is to create the conditions for the fulfilment of unconscious desire, to interpret reality so that it will support satisfaction (clearly this is not a very flattering vision of philosophy). The more an interpretation is totalising and the more meaning it produces, the more the constituted reality successfully masks unconscious demand. The connection of desire with worldview means that unconscious fantasy is implemented in reality, that it supports the constitution of reality as a consistent and framed totality. What Freud criticises in philosophical ontologies and theories of cognition is that they remain blind to the structuring function of fantasy: there is no reality without a fantasmatic support, and, consequently, there is no discourse without the unconscious. With the same move, Freud dismisses the Freudo-Marxist hypothesis of the exclusively oppressive character of social mechanisms: social reality does not simply repress or suppress the creative potentials of desire, drive and sexuality; on the contrary, it serves as its privileged articulation and consistency. Desire is not the producer -it is itself produced, while the producer is situated elsewhere. How exactly Freud approaches the relation between desire and productive unconscious labour will be examined further below; what matters for now is that for Freud no reality is consistently objective and every worldview, every ideological construction, contains a ‘wish-fulfilment’.

中This logical connection between desire and interpretation that Freud encounters in worldviews explains why he categorically rejects every attempt to construct a psychoanalytic worldview. Psychoanalysis intervenes on a different level. Its function is not to provide the conditions for satisfaction but to uncover the mechanisms that articulate unconscious desire in a specific dispositif of satisfaction, thereby revealing that behind the apparent conflict between this desire and social reality there is a certain complicity between desire and interpretation. For this reason, psychoanalysis does not ‘liberate desires’. It rather transforms, through interpretation, the formal mechanism of satisfaction, directing the subject towards the problematic kernel of the unconscious mode of production. This is the main point of the famous Freudian Wo Es war soll Ich werden: where there seems to have been an automatic regime of production, the unconscious mode of jouissance, there the place of the subject should be revealed, a place where a subjectivation can take place. And this subjectivation entails a transformation of the overall mechanism. The task of psychoanalysis is thus in clear opposition to worldviews. It does not interpret reality by feeding it with more meaning - it creates the conditions under which the subject will be able to produce a transformative act. This change appears to be impossible due to repression, which is actually the case, although the Freudian notion of repression differs significantly from suppression or oppression. For Freud, the mechanisms of repression are constitutive of the unconscious tendency, and if we want to attribute to the unconscious ‘productive potential’, then it does not pertain to the repressed desire but to repression itself, in which Freud recognises productive unconscious labour.

中Freud’s response to the attempts to construct a psychoanalytic worldview is highly enigmatic: ‘As a specialist science, a branch of psychology - a depth psychology or psychology of the unconscious - [psychoanalysis] is entirely unsuitable to construct a Weltanschauung of its own: it must assume the scientific one.’ Psychoanalysts should refrain from inventing a worldview because there is an underlying incompatibility between psychoanalysis and worldview-tendencies, which makes psychoanalysis appear as a saboteur. Consequently, an analyst cannot unveil the underlying mechanisms that support the satisfaction of unconscious tendencies and provide conditions for their perpetuated satisfaction. The contradiction between psychoanalysis and ideological tendencies could not be sharper. But the conclusion Freud draws from this contrast is that not even the analysts can do entirely without a worldview, so they should simply follow the example of the father of psychoanalysis, who adopted the scientific one. Freud’s persistent claim to a scientific status of psychoanalysis is only seemingly neutral. It actually contains a scientistic worldview, a fulfilment of Freud’s ‘epistemological’ desire.

中Behind the apparent unsuitability of forming a consistent worldview there is a more fundamental impossibility. Psychoanalysis cannot totalise reality, nor can it predict future events in mental life, and, finally, it reveals that even the past is subjected to retroactive modifications. The past is not a state but a movement. These restrictions differentiate psychoanalysis from other positive sciences, notably from physics, medicine and biology, on which Freud wanted to construct the scientificity of his invention and which are all orientated towards the future and can presumably predict events based on the already acquired knowledge. The limits of psychoanalysis logically follow from the status of the unconscious, which is by far neither an ontological substance nor a positive entity. It entirely depends on contingent and unpredictable traumatic events and on the dynamic of linguistic structures, so that no particular case is universal enough to support the prediction of future developments, which is, in the end, an important part of the achievement of worldviews: the exclusion of contingency from reality, life and thinking. The unconscious may be marked by the absence of time, and even by the absence of contradiction, as Freud occasionally claimed, but this absence is misleading. It does not automatically imply that the unconscious is unchangeable; it rather demonstrates its dependency on the actually existing social condition and hence on the ‘eternity’ of ruling ideologies. As Althusser argued, the absence of time and the deformation of social antagonisms represent two central features of ideology, which consequently appears as neutral and coextensive with reality. But while Althusser declared every subject to be an imaginary effect of ideology, Lacan recognised in the subject of the signifier the central discursive consequence on which the difference of psychoanalysis from sciences and worldviews rested. If psychoanalysis wants to join positive sciences, it must abandon the hypothesis of the subject of the unconscious: herein lies the risk of Freud’s attempts to ground psychoanalysis on energetics, neurology and biology. If, however, it wishes to produce a consistent worldview, it has to recentralise the subject: the ego should dominate the id, as many of Freud’s successors interpreted Wo Es war soll Ich werden. Ego-psychology and various forms of psychotherapy remain within the capitalist ideological framework and even openly adopt the centralised subjectivity of economic liberalism - namely a subjectivity, which is consolidated around the egoistic pursuit of private interest, just as in the context of cognition the subject is consolidated around the self-transparent consciousness or intentionality.

中A more general problem concerns the idea of a scientific worldview. Does it make sense to speak of such a worldview at all? What does it designate? The personal convictions of scientists, their ‘spontaneous philosophies’? To stick to Freud’s definition, a scientific worldview should not be an exception. In order to seriously compete with philosophy or religion, it would have to solve all problems of human existence, provide a meaningful interpretation of reality and finally articulate guiding principles for social life. In short, it would have to produce knowledge, belief and ethics. Modern science fulfils merely the first condition. What might come close to a scientific worldview are the ideals of enlightenment. Let us recall their Kantian summary:中Enlightenment is mans emergence from his self-incurred immaturity. Immaturity is the inability to use one’s own understanding without the guidance of another. This immaturity is self-incurred if its cause is not lack of understanding, but lack of resolution and courage to use it without the guidance of another. The motto of enlightenment is therefore: Sapere aude! Have courage to use your own understanding!中Would a scientific worldview entail universalisation of the courage to know, the social implementation of a presumably epistemological desire that would awaken the subject from its ignorance? Acheronta movebo, the Virgil quote that Freud placed to the head of Interpretation of Dreams, announcing that his publication shall shift the underground regions, repeating the Copernican revolution in psychic life, can be read together with the Kantian Sapere aude. Freud had his most evident moment of enthusiasm for the enlightenment in The Future of an Illusion, his most explicit confrontation with religion, predicting the triumph of scientific knowledge over ‘religious illusions’. Along the same lines, the New Introductory Lectures express a hope that ‘the intellect - the scientific spirit, reason - may in process of time establish a dictatorship in the mental life of man’. Thus for Freud a scientifically supported dictatorship of reason in mental life is the political ideal of psychoanalysis. Except that this reason, this psychoanalytic cogito, is unconscious, so that the dictatorship of reason would be an impossible dictatorship of the decentralised subject of the signifier that would replace the current capitalist dictatorship of the ‘strong ego’ (what Lacan called Je-cratie, I-cracy). Is the dictatorship of reason a psychoanalytic response to the dictatorship of the proletariat, maybe even just an extravagant name for it? Freud would then be only one step away from Lacan’s identification of the proletarian with the subject of the unconscious.

中On other occasions, Freud claims that modern science harms human narcissism, thereby leaving no doubt that scientific knowledge satisfies no desire whatsoever. The main condition for the formation of a scientific worldview falls away. To recall again, Freud mentions three scientific insults: the decentralisation of the universe in physics, which abolished the ancient idea of the finite, centralised and harmonious cosmic order with the infinite and contingent universe; then the decentralisation of life in biology, which abolished the hierarchy of beings with man as its privileged metaphysical crown; and finally the decentralisation of thinking in psychoanalysis, which questioned the primacy of consciousness and most definitely rejected the hypothesis of a metaphysical soul. The modern scientific paradigm has exactly the opposite effect of worldview mechanisms. Instead of totalising and stabilising both the external and the internal reality, it deprives them of their centre; instead of grounding them on necessity and order, it exposes their contingency and instability; and finally, instead of producing their meaningful interpretation, it reduces them to nonsensical formal mechanisms. A scientific worldview consequently follows an entirely different logic: production of falsifiable (uncertain, provisory) knowledge, de-totalisation and foreclosure of meaning.

中Freud determines the psychoanalytic relation to the scientific worldview by using the ambiguous expression annehmen. This can either mean that the scientific worldview already exists and psychoanalysis merely has to reach out and adopt it; or it can also suggest that such a worldview is simply presupposed, which would imply that positive sciences as such assume the position of a ‘subject supposed to know’, and indeed Freud often treats positive sciences in such a way. Finally, the Annahme, the assumption Freud talks about in relation to the scientific worldview, can also be understood in a formal sense, as the announcement of a concurrent regime of interpretation that will undermine the established worldview-form. This is what the Freudian idea of revolutionary sciences seems to address. While the existing worldviews satisfy ‘human narcissism’, scientific decentralisations inflict wounds because a concurrent, essentially materialist worldview announces itself at least on the logical level. The struggle between science and religion is first and foremost a conflict between two concurrent forms of thinking. The scientific worldview does not depart from the tendency of providing definite answers to human questions but reformulates the questions themselves. It also does not satisfy desire but alters the subject’s relation to it. The break with the worldview interpretation is a matter of formalisation because it is only here that a concurrent regime of interpretation can be approached.

中This Freudian epistemological optimism is nevertheless marked by a significant shift. The pessimistic turn that accompanies writings such as Beyond the Pleasure Principle and Civilisation and Its Discontents encounters a new problem. Instead of discussing the historic conflict between science and religion, it turns to modern culture, precisely to capitalism, where the political potential of modern scientific revolution met a more challenging limit that again concerns a specific form of thinking, the commodity form. The modern worldview operates within these formal constrictions, and in this respect the main failure of the scientific revolution consists in the incapacity to detach thinking from universal commodification; and even more so in its complicity with capitalism, the embedding of scientific knowledge in the permanent capitalist revolution. Freud’s pessimist turn is closely related to the fact that the universality of commodity form successfully integrated scientific knowledge into the capitalist mode of production and into its articulation of desire. What Marx described as commodity fetishism stands above all for a specific transformation of desire within and through the implementation of the capitalist worldview in social and subjective reality. The four cornerstones of this worldview (freedom, equality, property and private interest)form an abstract coordinate system, in which the sharpness of revolutionary sciences is neutralised in advance.

中At this point we can move to Freud’s engagement with the Marxist worldview in his lecture on Weltanschauung. After expressing his lack of competence in discussing Marxism, he sums up his reservations in the following passage:中Theoretical Marxism, as realised in Russian Bolshevism, has acquired the energy and the self-contained and exclusive character of a Weltanschauung, but at the same time an uncanny likeness to what it is fighting against. Though originally a portion of science and built up, in its implementation, upon science and technology, it has created a prohibition of thought which is just as ruthless as was that of religion in the past.中Freud then continues with how the critical confrontation with Marxism is forbidden and how the Soviet regime produced a fetishisation of Marx’s works that is comparable to that of religious texts, and so on. Freud’s critique of the worldview Marxism resembles a typical right-wing moralisation, yet there is something symptomatic in his discontent, something that goes beyond the moralistic tone of his remarks and concerns the very outcome of the Soviet revolution: the epistemic transformation of Marx’s critique into dogmatism and the recentralisation of his theory of the subject. Freud does not talk about Marx but about scientific socialism; and the outcome of the revolution is not so much Lenin but Stalin, the bureaucrat and not the revolutionary.

中Lenin nevertheless announced the worldview tendency of Marxism, when he wrote: ‘Marx’s theory is omnipotent because it is true. It is comprehensive and harmonious, it gives men a unified worldview’. Lacan returned to this passage on several occasions in order to claim the same link between omnipotence and truth for Freud’s invention of psychoanalysis, and it is rather symptomatic that the citations of this passage often omit Lenin’s specification of this omnipotence and truth. Worldview Marxism is the necessary step to dogmatism, where the dialectical materialist method that oriented the critique of political economy is replaced by the three nondialectical worldview achievements. Lacan, too, envisaged this inversion when he expressed his astonishment that the majority of Marxists depart from the primacy of a specific figure of subjectivity, which is only subsequently alienated in the commodity form, in the process of production and in the movement of History, while Marx’s critical project openly departs from the autonomy of value, which consequently helps him discover the decentralised subject of politics, labour-power, and its privileged social embodiment, the proletariat. The foundation of Marxism as a worldview demanded the abolition of this critical ground of Marx’s theory:中The proletariat means what? It means that labour is radicalised on the level of pure and simple commodity, which also reduces the labourer to the same price. As soon as the labourer learns to know himself as such through theory, we can say that this step shows him the way to the status of-call it what you want - a scientist [savant]. He is no longer a proletarian an sich, if I may say so, he is no longer pure and simple truth, but he is für sich, what we call class-consciousness. He can even become the Party’s class-consciousness where one no longer speaks the truth.中The failure of the Communist Party would then consist in the fact that, in the end, it was the worldview-form which determined the political organisation and sabotaged the invention of a new party-form, and not the other way around. This political failure is accompanied by an entire set of epistemological regressions, which have already been mentioned.

中The difference between Marx’s interpretation of the proletariat as the social embodiment-personification of the truth of labour, and worldview Marxism, which promises to abolish alienation and to constitute a revolutionary subject of cognition, overlaps with the difference between truth and knowledge. The Soviet regime replaced the social embodiment of truth, the proletarian as the true subject of revolutionary politics, with a particular social embodiment of knowledge, the party as the placeholder of the collective subject of knowledge and the Subject of History. Again, the movement of the critique of political economy proceeds exactly in the opposite direction, from the economic forms of knowledge to the progressive deduction of the subject of value, where also the horizon of a possible transformation is outlined, albeit without a prospective insight into the future social order: this is where Marx, too, adopted what Freud called the scientific worldview. Worldview Marxism reverts from this critical perspective by reducing the subject of capitalism back to knowledge, making of the proletarian a savant, a scientist, subject of cognition, in which the proletarian knows itself as knowledge. The point of departure is no longer the identity of alienation and structure, which in the end determines the gap between the subject of cognition and the subject of politics. This critical point of departure is now replaced by the hypothesis of a centralised and unalienated Subject of History, which supposedly reaches the highest form of self-consciousness through the Party, another subject supposed to know. The problem is not so much in the introduction of the party but in the fact that the party becomes the privileged embodiment of a presupposed historical knowledge and not an organisation that opens up the space in which the historical and political truth embodied in the working class and in the surplus population can be transmitted. The Party appears as the perfect opposition of what, for instance, Lacan strived to establish through the idea of the School, founded on the imperative of renewing the sharp razor of Freudian truth, the gap between knowledge and truth, and to insist on the inexistence of the Other, which stands for the impossibility of the ultimate abolition of alienation.

中By reintroducing the subject of cognition into the critique of political economy through the hypothesis of class-consciousness, worldview Marxism futilely seeks to abolish all forms of alienation and establish authentic intersubjective relations. It thereby regresses into a pre-critical framework. The Party’s class-consciousness is the end-result of this movement: one no longer speaks (of) the truth, only (of) knowledge, which is most faithfully embodied in the Party’s bureaucratic apparatus. Positive scientific knowledge - and this explains Stalin’s tendency to provide an essentially positivistic foundation for dialectical materialism - serves as the point where the subject of capitalism can presumably reach a promised self-realisation beyond alienation.

中Freud’s theory of the subject saw a similar fate, when the post-Freudians recentralised the subject on the ego and deduced from Freud’s Wo Es war soll Ich werden an imperative of normalisation and reintegration. Lacan’s political struggle against the International Psychoanalytic Association, the psychoanalytic analogue of the Stalinist Party, for which the strong ego is the central instance in mental life, repeatedly turned around the translation of this ambiguous Freudian axiom. Post-Freudians have read it through the lenses of the theory of cognition and in closest compatibility with economic liberalism, while Lacan, in contrast, made it his privileged formula for alienation that constitutes the subject of the unconscious and points towards the real subject of politics.

中Aside from all of the humanistic and moralistic appearances, Freud’s critique of worldviews brings him suspiciously close to the break that inaugurated Marx’s critique of political economy. The lecture on Weltanschauung contains a certain repetition of the critical programme from Marx’s Theses on Feuerbach, which leaves no doubt that for Marx political struggles necessarily address the form of the interpretation of the world, not so much through the all too simple opposition of theory (worldview interpretation) and praxis (political action) but through the actual subversion of the very praxis of interpretation. Among the many targets of Marx and Freud’s critique is philosophy, of which they promote a highly problematic and out dated image. But this detail should not distract us from the fact that the true object of their critique is religion and political economy, their competition with philosophical interpretations, which in the capitalist universe clearly are found in a worse position, discredited in advance as ‘self-centred’ and ‘unprofitable’. Philosophy and science are simply not as successful when it comes to satisfying desire.

中For the critique of political economy, the form of interpretation will be no less important as the organisation of the proletariat. And indeed, the transformation of the form of interpretation necessitates the form of organisation. When Marx examines the intertwining of the social form and the commodity form, or Freud the intertwining of the worldview mechanisms and the unconscious mechanisms of satisfaction, this already presupposes an inversion in the form of interpretation, which, in psychoanalysis and in the critique of political economy, supports their critique of appearances and recognises in the commodity form the general envelope of social links and unconscious production.

中Another crucial aspect of Marx’s critique of appearance, to repeat, concerns the break with the humanism and the essentialism of Feuerbach’s conception of alienation. Marx’s mature discussion of fetishism no longer departs from the illusion that the commodity form distorts more immediate and authentic social relations. Here it makes sense to repeat the distinction between constitutive alienation - alienation that is equivalent to structure - and constituted alienation - for instance, commodity fetishism, which follows from the misperception of the relation between the appearance of value and the structure that causes this appearance. The doubling of alienation does not prevent their confusion. This is what Marx criticised in Feuerbach. Simultaneously, the twofold character of alienation reveals that constituted alienation functions as a mask or a mystification of the constitutive alienation. The flip side of commodity fetishism is the appearance that there is a more fundamental and unalienated position in the background, a position from which it would be possible to cognise the mistake that determines commodity fetishism - precisely the position of an unsplit and conflict-free ego or consciousness, this common presupposition of political economy, post-Freudian psychoanalysis and scientific Marxism. Homo oeconomicus, strong ego and class-consciousness are conceptual and ideological variations of the same attempt to mystify the subjective split produced by the autonomy of discourse.

中In distinction to these attempts to abolish alienation, which really do deserve to be called utopian, Marx’s critique of political economy contains an effort to think alienation not only as reproduction of the relations of production but also as a structural transformation of the existing mode of production. We cannot overlook that the double meaning of the term ‘revolution’ is at stake here, the scientific (circular movement of astronomic bodies) and the political (subversion of the given social order). There is also no doubt that constitutive alienation does not address solely the alienation of the subject but above all the alienation of the Other: it makes the Other appear in its split, incompleteness, contradiction and therefore inexistence. The correlate of this inexistence is the existence of the subject, the actual agency of the revolutionary process, which, however, does not assume the position of knowledge but the place of truth, as Lacan persistently repeated. Because the subject is produced, brought into existence in and through the gap in the Other, in other words, because there is a social entity, the proletariat, which articulates a universal demand for change in the name of all (being the social embodiment of a universal subjective position), this very enunciation grounds politics on the link between inexistence, alienation and universality.

中Capitalism, by contrast, rooted its politics on the hypothetical existence of the Other (the Market and other economic abstractions), the strong ego of a fictitious economic subject (the narcissism of private interest)and social segregation. Before anyone remarks that we have seen in the communist experiments how the political consequences of inexistence, alienation and universality look in practice, let us recall that the twentieth-century communist regimes failed in all three tasks. They have supported their political projects on the triad of History, class-consciousness (even if they were not all Lukacsian) and the no less intense forms of segregation. The political task of a Party that wants to claim the predicate ‘communist’ remains in insisting at this interplay of the subject’s existence and the inexistence of History, just as for Lacan the politics of his School was rooted in the existence of the subject of the unconscious and the inexistence of the Other. With his critical move, Marx grounded the first theory of the subject that presupposed the total abolition of two central worldview illusions, human essence and social homeostasis, on which the capitalist worldview is grounded. Abstract freedom and abstract equality presuppose an equally abstract human essence, while private property and private interest ground the social consensus, behind which there is nevertheless a fundamental submission of political universalism to the particular interest of capital. The proletariat (the social embodiment of the subject) and class struggle (a concrete manifestation of the inexistence of the Other) represent two critical responses to the construction of a worldview and openly sabotage the undisturbed satisfaction of the insatiable capitalist imperative of creation of value.

中Marx addressed the necessity of displacing the struggle from the interpretation of reality - the infamous ‘conflict of interpretations’ - to the form of interpretation in his often cited and almost as often misunderstood 11th thesis on Feuerbach: ‘The philosophers have only interpreted the world, in various ways; the point is to change it’. The thesis formulates the opposition between interpretation and change, theory and praxis, philosophy and revolutionary politics. Here, worldview Marxism is disqualified from the very outset. It may have brought about a revolutionary change but it adopted an interpretation of history that pushed it back in the centralised and totalising framework of a worldview. Even a reactionary thinker like Heidegger understood that Marx’s final thesis in fact questions the dichotomy between thinking and action and conditions the actual change of the world with the change of the form of interpretation, thereby articulating a demand for a new form of philosophy that would account for the change. Behind the apparent opposition of theory and praxis, the 11th thesis opposes two heterogeneous logical regimes of interpretation. All past philosophies presumably remained within the dispositif of worldview interpretations, where the change, the conflictuality of the historic movement is excluded from interpretation, or where History and Reality know no contradiction.

中Looking back at the history of philosophy, one can, of course, immediately object that it would be difficult to find philosophers who were merely occupied with the static interpretation of reality, without raising the question of political change: from Plato’s ideal state, theorised on the background of the crisis of Greek polis, via Descartes’s foundation of philosophy on the changes introduced by scientific modernity, up to Kant, Fichte and Hegel’s enthusiasm for the French Revolution. Philosophers seem to have been more preoccupied with thinking possible changes rather than interpreting the given order and filling the gaps in reality. But, as already stated, the problem of the critical interpretation in Marx concerns first and foremost the closed world of universal commodification, where the commodity form is the ultimate horizon of other forms of thinking and where the change already is the actual state of things, the permanent revolution mentioned by the Communist Manifesto. Reality already includes change, but what the critique of interpretation envisages is an articulation of political theory and practice that departs from the formalisation of the structural contradictions that determine the functioning of social links, as well as the consequent abolition of the hypothetical Other and of the centralised model of subjectivity. The Theses target young Hegelians and political economists, and not so much philosophy as a whole. Marx’s insistence that a materialist theory of the subject conceives the latter as a consequence of social relations and not on a false hypothesis of an abstract human essence indicates that the displacement of the accent from interpretation to change should also be read as a shift in the understanding of change itself. In the capitalist-scientific universe where reality essentially comes down to permanent change, the latter loses its a priori revolutionary character. The structural change that could bring about a new social link, abolish the abstract universality of commodity form and construct a new figure of political subject presupposes a correct interpretation of the given logic of change, the conditions of the permanent capitalist revolution. Again, the point of departure should be that ‘the Other is lacking’ (Lacan), and from this viewpoint it is not astonishing that a major portion of philosophy seems to fall into the totalising regime of interpretation.

中In his critique of worldviews, Freud outlines their three central functions and exemplifies them in reference to the conflict between modern science, the motor of revolutionary changes in the register of knowledge, and Christianity, the most persistent and consistent worldview in history, which successfully integrates every change in its form of interpretation:中If we are to give an account of the grandiose nature of religion, we must bear in mind what it undertakes to do for human beings. It gives them information about the origin and coming into existence of the universe, it assures them of its protection and of ultimate happiness in the ups and downs of life and it directs their thoughts and actions by precepts, which it lays down with its whole authority. Thus it fulfils three functions. With the first of them it satisfies the human thirst for knowledge; it does the same thing that science attempts to do with its means, and at that point enters into rivalry with it. It is to its second function that it no doubt owes the greatest part of its influence. Science can be no match for it when it soothes the fear that men feel of the dangers and vicissitudes of life, when it assures them of a happy ending and offers them comfort in unhappiness. . . In its third function, in which it issues precepts and lays down prohibitions and restrictions, religion is furthest away from science. For science is content to investigate and to establish facts, though it is true that in its application rules and advice are derived from the conduct of life.中The knowledge of a worldview satisfies the desire for knowledge much better than science, with its epistemological revolutions and instabilities. Worldviews, in addition, produce meaning, which satisfies the desire for persistence; and, finally, they generate order, which satisfies the desire for security, excluding the change from the realms of reality. A worldview first and foremost produces a reality that appears to function, a reality without lack or negativity.

中With these three achievements in mind the contrast between Marx’s critique of political economy and worldview Marxism becomes even more striking. Marx precisely does not ‘solve all the problems of human existence based on an underlying hypothesis’; on the contrary, he formulates the central problem of modern political thought: commodity form as the ultimate horizon of social relations in capitalism. The ruling ideologies insist that Marxism is a worldview, the object of which is not the way things are, the ‘question of being’, but the way things should be, the question of change, not the present but the future. However, Marx’s critique is neither a worldview nor a utopian theory. It is rather a reclaiming - as an object of thinking and as the condition of politics and revolutionary change - of an irreducible negativity that traverses social and subjective reality, and of which no one can be excepted: there is no metaposition that would ground politics on positive knowledge, but there is the subjective position, which grounds politics on conflictual truth. The notion of class struggle replaces the old, inadequate questions and answers, the social or the economic contract, with a new, radicalised problem: rather than being backed by some mythical contract, convention or relation, society rests on an irreducible struggle and social non-relation. Capitalism exploits this non-relation, but it can do so only under the condition of mystifying the actual source of wealth with a multitude of ideological fictions, fantasies and fetishisations.

中In political economy, Marx uncovers the same three tendencies that, according to Freud, support the efficiency of religion. These three tendencies come down to the endeavour to ground the market on stable and predictable laws, which turn it into a positive Other that will support a fully functioning social relation. The association of economy with religious mechanisms is most evidently formulated in the famous lines of The Poverty of Philosophy, where Marx describes the metaphysical-theological tendencies of political economy:中Economists have a singular method of procedure. There are only two kinds of institutions for them, artificial and natural. The institutions of feudalism are artificial institutions, those of the bourgeoisie are natural institutions. In this, they resemble the theologians, who likewise establish two kinds of religion. Every religion which is not theirs is an invention of men, while their own is an emanation from God. When the economists say that present-day relations-the relations of bourgeois production -are natural, they imply that these are the relations in which wealth is created and productive forces developed in conformity with the laws of nature. These relations therefore are themselves natural laws independent of the influence of time. They are eternal laws which must always govern society. Thus, there has been history, but there is no longer any. There has been history since there were the institutions of feudalism, and in these institutions of feudalism we find quite different relations of production from those of bourgeois society, which the economists try to pass off as natural and as such, eternal.中Smith’s figure of the invisible hand remains the best expression of this metaphysical aspiration of political economy. In the market, it presupposes a pregiven rational knowledge, which makes the market appear as an autonomous subject. When Marx later describes the relation of political economy to the capitalist abstractions as fetishist, he implicitly situates this relation, not on the level of perversion, but on the level of transference. In order to envisage the persistence of this attitude in political economy, one merely needs to recall the jargon of contemporary advocates of neoliberal reforms. As the crisis persists, we get bombarded by warnings that radical measures are needed in order to ‘send a positive signal’ to the markets. The function of reforms and of austerity measures is to ‘calm the markets’. The formulations are more than mere rhetorical figures; they actually demonstrate the fetishist disavowal that Octave Mannoni condensed in the famous phrase Je sais bien, mais quand même: I know very well (that the markets are mere constructions and human inventions) but nevertheless (I believe that they are autonomous and capricious). A double mistake is at work here: yes, the markets are human inventions, but they contain an autonomous dimension, which determines social and subjective reality, and this autonomy is not correctly situated. The reason lies in the fact that political economy, in its apparent rationality and false scientificity, inevitably contains the inversion of the aforementioned fetishisation: I know very well that the markets are autonomous and capricious, but I nevertheless believe that they are mere constructions and human inventions.

中In any case, the autonomy of the structural relations that support the functioning of the market is not taken seriously. Political economy in the same move fetishises economic abstractions as autonomous entities and relativises the dimension of causality in this autonomy by regressing back to the false sobriety of conventionalism. The fact is that the economic crisis does not undermine the fetishist relation to the market, it does not unveil the inexistence of the market Other; on the contrary, the more the crisis unveils the instability of the markets, the more the Market receives a surplus of positive existence. What nevertheless becomes observable is that the capitalist Market seems to be much closer to the God of the Old Testament than to the benevolent and abstract God of philosophers and political economists: not the neutral and self-regulating knowledge of the invisible hand but a desiring God that demands constant sacrifice, not a homeostatic order but a negativity, whose consequences are devastating.

中In addition, the imposition of economic reforms and austerity measures as inevitable and quasi-metaphysical necessities recalls the privileged appearance of class struggle in the first volume of Capital, where its paradigm is the struggle for the length of the working day. Is today this struggle not indicated in the debates regarding the length, not of the working day, but of the working life? One can repeat Marx here: capitalists have their own idea of the ultimate limit of the working life. Evidently a working life cannot be longer than biological life: the ultimate end of the working life is biological death. However, death can be postponed through the improvement of life conditions and medical interventions, biopolitics and so on. The argumentation for the extension of work periods comes down to the argument that the life expectancy in Europe is today longer than it was in the past, the population grows older, and for this reason the neoliberal reforms are said to be inevitable. Every extension of the working life abolishes past achievements of the worker’s struggles in a more efficient manner that an extension of the working day ever would. Life and work become inseparable; the entire lifespan is transformed into the precarious life in work.

THE LABOUR THEORY OF THE UNCONSClOUS

中Freud’s critique of worldviews stands in continuity with the main conclusions of the Interpretation of Dreams. It is well known that this work, in which Freud for the first time systematised his theory of the unconscious, turns around an apparently banal statement: dreams are wish-fulflments. Yet behind this simplicity lies a complex structure that reveals the problematic status of this ‘wish’: Before entering the discussion of the Freudian dream analysis, we should recall the specificity and the epistemological weight of the Freudian approach in relation to his predecessors. Freud was certainly not the first one to attribute a theoretical value and meaning to dreams. The theoretical tradition goes back to Aristotle, and in the first sections of his work Freud leaves no doubt that he did his homework when presenting an exhaustive and detailed account of the past approaches, including psychology, philosophy, literature and so on. The Interpretation of Dreams proposes to move beyond their meaning to the formal mechanisms that can be recognised in the dream processes, thereby isolating their function of satisfaction. In doing so, Freud discovers that behind the production of meaning, narration and visualisation there is another level of the dream text and another production. Here I want to focus on two main features of the Freudian notion of the unconscious, the already mentioned dimension of production, immanently doubled in the production of meaning and the production of satisfaction, and the central role of unconscious labour in the process that supports the satisfaction of the unconscious tendency. The fact that the longest chapter of the Interpretation of Dreams engages with Traumarbeit, dream work, should be taken seriously. Psychoanalysis begins with a labour theory of the unconscious.

中The first complication is already on the level of terminology. In the book, Freud does not talk about desire (Begierde) but wish (Wunsch). This terminological choice makes the structural point of Freud’s analysis of satisfaction more difficult to grasp, since Wunsch in everyday use designates a desire that aims at a specific object, while Begierde appears as desire without a strictly determined object. From this nuance, practically all Freud’s troubles in ‘selling’ the idea of an unconscious wish to the scientific community emerge, a wish that is not simply without an object but, at the same time, does not aim at an empirical, immediate or concrete object either. The unconscious desire is neither Wunsch nor Begierde but somehow a third category that both abolishes and complicates the dichotomy of the presence and absence of the object, or, more precisely, demands a rethinking of what an object is.

中Wish-fulfilment results from the manipulation of psychic material, the ‘day residues’. This requires a consumption of energy that can, in the end, be quantified and hence understood in terms of labour-power. This explains Freud’s strong interest in energetics, which became crucial in his later efforts to construct an energetics of the drives but is already present in his abandoned early attempt to ground a (positivist) scientific psychology (1895). The idea of unconscious production, approached through the notion of labour-power, thus forms the central difference between Freud and his predecessors, who saw in the unconscious either unclear representations or psychic depth, subconsciousness. The unconscious labour also cannot be conceived without the double character of labour in capitalism. In English, this division is inscribed into language, ‘work’ and ‘labour’, which cover both aspects of commodities, use-value and exchange-value. This linguistic inscription was already pointed out by Engels in an editorial footnote to Marx’s Capital: ‘Labour which creates use-values and is qualitatively determined is called “work” as opposed to “labour”; labour which creates value and is only measured quantitatively is “labour”, as opposed to “work”. Engels accentuates the opposition between qualitative and quantitative labour, between sensual qualities and discursive matter. A commodity does not merely abolish or solve the contradiction between both poles, thereby becoming matter with qualities; it consists only as this split. Engels’s comment relates to the passage in which Marx links the two aspects of commodity with labour and production:中On the one hand, all labour is an expenditure of human labour-power, in the physiological sense, and it is in this character of being equal, or abstract, human labour that it creates and forms the value of commodities. On the other hand, all labour is an expenditure of human labour-power in a particular form and with a definite aim, and it is in this character of being concrete useful labour that it produces use-values.中Here Marx most clearly situates the split in labour: all labour is on both sides at the same time; the question is therefore not that the commodity form would in any way encroach labour and introduce its inadequate representation. We are dealing with a parallax structure, according to which labour appears first on one side and then on the other, once as abstract matter, labour-power, once as concrete form, labour-process. In the same move Marx shows that his mature critical materialist orientation implies a more sophisticated and openly anti-empiricist notion of matter, which privileges the apparently ‘abstract’ discursive materiality, where labour-power and surplus-value can finally be thought as real discursive consequences, over the misleading ‘concrete’ empirical materiality, whose product is an apparently univocal commodity.

中With the division between abstract and concrete labour in mind, unconscious labour falls on the side of abstract labour, notably because it cannot be associated with a concrete psychological agent. Freud will additionally complicate the matter by showing that unconscious production is not univocal either. It brings about two achievements and is itself internally doubled. The satisfaction of desire thus contains two satisfactions, in accordance with the double character of commodities, which now reflects on the couple ‘wish’ and ‘desire’. The minimal difference between meaning and satisfaction conserves the division of use-value and value, as is also the case with meaning and linguistic value in Saussure. This difference is noticeable in Freud’s emphasis on the quantitative factor in dream work and his insistence that the imaginary aspect of dreams should not seduce us in believing that nothing logically different takes place behind the visualisation:中The dream-thoughts and the dream-content are presented to us like two versions of the same subject-matter in two different languages. Or, more properly, the dream content seems like a transcript of the dream-thoughts into another mode of expression, whose characters and syntactic laws it is our business to discover by comparing the original and the translation. The dream-thoughts are immediately comprehensible, as soon as we have learnt them. The dream-content, on the other hand, is expressed as it were in a pictographic script [Bilderschrift], the characters of which have to be transposed individually into the language of the dream-thoughts. If we attempted to read these characters according to their pictorial value [Bilderwert] instead of according to their symbolic relation [Zeichenbeziehung], we should clearly be led into error.中Dreams are like commodities: hieroglyphs (the actual meaning of Bilderschrift), where meaning and value should be differentiated. Hence Freud’s insistence that we should pass from the imaginary to the symbolic, the focus on Zeichenbeziehung, the relation between signs independently from their meaningful and adequate relation to images. Just like commodities, dreams, too, appear as an unproblematic universal experience that everyone seems to understand spontaneously. The more their formal analysis progresses, the more their complexity becomes apparent and the deeper the gap between their pictographic script, the imaginary aspect of dreams, and their structure. And again, just as commodities, dreams bring together two languages, not the original and the translation but the language of values and the language of meaning (need, communication), which in the end resume the split within one and the same language. These two levels do not overlap, their interaction is merely accidental, but they both need to be taken into account in order to understand unconscious production, just as we cannot simply omit use-value from the production of value, since we thereby lose the entire paradox of the commodity form. Focusing only on the sequence of dream images, the product appears to us senseless and worthless, without meaning or value, and the ‘science of dreams’ (as Freud’s volume was initially titled in French translation) is only possible through the shift from the appearance of meaning to the logic of value. The science of dreams is also a science of value. With this move, Freud outlines the structural background that supports both the production of meaning in a seemingly senseless sequence of images, and the articulation of a demand for satisfaction that aims beyond the meaning of dreams and that can solely open up the ‘royal road to a knowledge of the unconscious’, the autonomy of the signifier that marked Lacan’s first return to Freud. The Interpretation of Dreams without any doubt grounds psychoanalysis as a logic and not as a hermeneutic of the unconscious.

中Let us move on to unconscious labour. The dream work stands for various formal operations. Freud names them condensation, displacement, consideration of representability and secondary elaboration. Unconscious labour is already implied in the inverted relation between concrete and abstract labour, which prevents the identification of unconscious labour with the psychological subject. Marx pointed out the fundamental achievement of the capitalist decentralisation of labour when he claimed that the capitalist and scientific development of the means of production does not free the labourer from labour but instead frees labour of its content, which means that labour is freed first and foremost of the empirical labourer, while the inverse, the liberation of the labourer from labour, appears as an impossible task. The liberation of labour radicalizes the dependency of the labourer on labour, it accomplishes the transformation of the subject into labour-power, a commodified, capitalist subject. There is more at stake in this asymmetry than the fact that abstract labour simply becomes the privileged representation of all concrete forms of labour, or that exchange-value abstracts from use-value, thereby making of labour, too, an abstraction. Because of the asymmetrical relation between abstract and concrete labour, no return to concrete and presumably more authentic forms of labour will abolish the alienation of labour. The alienation of labour is, of course, not a result of capitalism, no more as is discursive alienation. What is its achievement, though, is the objectification of this alienation in a specific commodity.

中From a psychoanalytic perspective, this objectification of alienation, its materialisation in a commodity, unveils a major feature of capitalism, namely that it places the subject in the position of the object that satisfies the Other’s demand for production, the object that is consumed by the Other for the extraction of surplus-object - this, precisely, is Lacan’s definition of perversion. As labour-power, a commodity consumed for the production of value, the subject is deprived of its subjective position. Commodification of labour means as much as imposing a perverse position on the subject, demanding from the subject to assume the position of the object of the Other’s jouissance. The main achievement of Marx’s labour theory of value consisted in the fact that it reclaimed the subjects position, hence reintroducing the position of the subject in the commodity world and abolishing another imposed fantasy, according to which capital is the true subject of the valorisation process.

中At this point we can add another remark regarding Marx’s labour theory of value, for which we hear that it lost its importance in times of financialisation and proliferation of new technologies. Such declarations risk blurring the difference between the political-economic labour theory (Smith and Ricardo) and its Marxian reformulation. The reason why Marx’s theory of value preserves the predicate ‘labour’ is not so much in the simplistic idea, according to which labour would be the central economic category and the privileged source of value. This is what a certain branch of classical political economy seemed to have claimed - and it was wrong. Rather, the main achievement of Marx’s theory of value concerns the fact that it recognises in labour the process, the analysis of which demonstrates that the source of value lies in inequality, exploitation and hence in social non-relation. However, in order to think the source of value rigorously we also need to acknowledge the participation of all the fetishist fantasies in this process - and this is another main achievement of Marx’s labour theory of value. The logic of value can only be thoroughly thought in parallel with an elaborate logic of fantasy. The labour theory of value thus becomes a component of a critical science, which repeatedly evolves around the inter-dependency of exploitation and mystification of exploitation, which both reach their peak in the fetishisation of capitalist abstractions. Marx’s labour theory has never been more theoretically urgent and more practically relevant than in today’s financial capitalism.

中Unconscious labour and abstract labour both lack concrete personification and embodiment, since their materiality consists in labour-power, which the discursive apparatus isolates in the living body and which the signifier or value represents independently from the relation to the signified. Because of this lack of concrete embodiment, Marx and Freud produced two ‘fetishisations’, that is, they forced two social personifications of abstract and unconscious labour. Marx could only invent the social symptom by fetishising the proletariat and the industrial reserve army as the point where the contradictions of the capitalist structure become empirical. This, of course, entails the misunderstanding that Marx’s critique descends from the realm of metaphysical abstractions to the concrete analysis of social conditions and to concrete men and women. The fetishisation in question maybe repeats the very same operation as commodity fetishism, but it articulates something that one might call Marx’s hypothesis: the individual who is affected by capitalism is the same as the one who constitutes the subject of value. This clearly inverts the fetishist hypothesis, according to which the subject of capitalism is capital itself. The sameness of the industrial proletariat and of the subject of value implies that the industrial labourer, in a given historic moment, the industrial revolution, embodies the split in the subject of labour and the alienation introduced by the capitalist organisation of production. Their hypothetical sameness does not contradict the fact that the subject of value designates the radical alienation of the individual that embodies it.

中For Freud, the same privilege, equally in the given historical moment, comes to the hysteric, who from Studies on Hysteria (1895) onward assumes the same function as Marx’s proletariat. The hysteric does not merely embody the symptom; she is the epistemological and the social symptom, e.g., for medical knowledge, which sees in her either a pseudo-illness, simulation and hypochondria, or an inexplicable enigma, around which an entire spectacle is organised: Charcot’s presentations of cases in the Parisian hospital La Salpêtrière had the status of theatre performances and attracted not only other scientists but also the lay public. In the nineteenth century, hysteria was the limit of scientific discourse, the point where the primacy of medical knowledge was suspended because the causes of the hysteric symptom cannot be traced back to anatomical origins solely. It was only Freud, who succeeded in theorising the hysteric as a social symptom, which on the epistemological level introduced a shift from the paradigm of the ‘medical gaze’ to the paradigm of the ‘analytic ear’, in other words, from the primacy of vision and observation to the primacy of speech and listening, and finally, from vulgar materialism to critical materialism. The hysteric is, indeed, Freud’s proletarian.

中The notion of dream work is supposed to explain the logical mechanism of fulfilment and the structure of desire. The question that occupies Freud is why does the unconscious need to work on a detour of displacements and condensations, censorship and deformations, in order to reach satisfaction. Why can there be no unmasked and undistorted satisfaction? In order to answer this question, Freud makes the hypothesis that the relation between unconscious desire and the demands of reality involves a contradiction. Due to this contradiction, the dream work produces double conditions for the satisfaction of desire, whereby the split in commodity form serves as the most comfortable means by which to overcome the contradiction between desire and reality. In the apparent satisfaction, an ‘other satisfaction’ begins to show. This internally double satisfaction is reached through the manipulation of the day’s remains, the material that accumulates on the borders of consciousness, in the preconscious, this grey zone between consciousness and the unconscious. In this intermediate space we come across wishes that can still be consciously formulated. For this reason, one could reproach Freud insofar as his analysis of dream samples exaggerates their meaning. The discussed cases only contain fulfilments of banal, simple and naive desires. Freud’s dream of Irma’s injection, this crown example that is supposed to demonstrate the revolutionary character of his discoveries, unveils his attempts to shirk responsibility for the failed treatment of his hysteric patient. Children’s dreams, another example that confirms the wish-fulfilment theory, are only concerned with concrete objects (sweets, toys and so on). Almost all examples seem to be badly chosen and speak against the reality of the ‘other satisfaction’. They leave the impression that the desire in question is simply preconscious, temporarily dropped out of consciousness and attention but did not change its character in any way. It still aims at the same concrete object and remains intertwined with the content of the day’s remains. And most importantly, at least for Freud’s critics, there is absolutely no trace of sexuality, not to speak of infantile sexuality, and there is no reason to complicate the matter with repression and censorship.

中Freud anticipates precisely such criticisms when he writes: ‘It will then appear as though the conscious wish alone has been realised in the dream’, a concrete satisfaction that assumed a hallucinatory and performative form. The emphasis is on the appearance that pushes a certain type of satisfaction into the foreground. This appearance is the same as the one that unites both aspects of the commodity and masks the structural gap between use-value and exchange-value. In accordance with this, the dream form implies two satisfactions, of which one depends on its apparent immediate meaning and another on its linguistic value. The move from quality to quantity entails a shift in the object form. Lacan’s object a, the object of desire, is an object without qualities that presupposes the autonomy of value. Thereby it becomes clear that the discovery of this object is possible only under the condition of the commodity form in the universe of capitalism and modern science. Before the object of desire appears either as an unattainable transcendent Thing (das Ding that Lacan discusses in reference to the status of the Lady in the medieval courtly love) or as an immanent agalma (like in the transference relation between Socrates and Alcibiades in Plato’s Symposium). The object a, neither transcendent nor immanent, remains unthinkable outside modernity and is so to speak a modern invention, a consequence of the foundation of science on universal mathematisation and of the social relations on quantification and mass production.

中The hallucinatory fulfilment in dreams shows that the satisfaction was postponed and that the fulfilment presupposes a renunciation of immediate satisfaction, as in the case of children’s dreams. The postponement exposes a shift within satisfaction, which remains invisible in the wish-fulfilment and in relation to which the immediacy of wish relates as a mask. In other words, the manifestation of desire is always mediated through the apparent immediacy of wish. Desire parasites the use-value of objects. We can already notice that the relation between the conscious and the unconscious ‘wish’ is also inscribed into language: the pair ‘wish-desire’ perfectly corresponds with ‘work-labour’, just as the production of use-value and the production of value overlap with satisfaction and the other satisfaction. Wish can still be attributed to consciousness because its object is concrete, whereas desire appears to be without an object, as long as it is not associated with the quantitative and abstract character of the commodity form. Freud’s dream analyses simply attempt to demonstrate that the ‘unconscious wish’ does have an object because it finds satisfaction in the surplus produced through the manipulation of psychic material. The name of this object is also at hand - it is simply Lust, pleasure. Although Freud will soon discover that the status of this unconsciously produced pleasure is more problematic than it seems.

中After pointing out the appearance that masks the other satisfaction, Freud finally introduces the already mentioned economic comparison, which should illustrate the nature of the unconscious desire and make his concept of the unconscious more understandable. ‘I am now in position to give a sharp description’ - sharp because the appearance needs to be put back into focus in order to make desire present - ‘of the part played in dreams by unconscious wish’. He admits that there are dreams in which the stimulation comes from the day’s remains, hence from use-value, although this trigger is not enough for the dream formation. For instance, in Freud’s dream of Irma’s injection, his concern about the patients state was not enough. He then has recourse to the comparison of unconscious production with capitalist production that is worth repeating here:中The motive force, which the dream required, had to be provided by a wish; it was the business of the worry to get hold of a wish to act as the motive force of the dream. The position may be explained by an analogy. A daytime thought may very well play the part of entrepreneur for a dream; but the entrepreneur, who, as people say, has the idea and the initiative to carry it out, can do nothing without the capital; he needs a capitalist who can afford the outlay, and the capitalist who provides the psychical outlay for the dream is invariably and indisputably, whatever maybe the thoughts of the previous day, a wish from the unconscious.中Freud does not say what the Freudo-Marxists will claim later, that the unconscious explains capitalism; he states precisely the opposite: it is capitalism that elucidates the unconscious. The unconscious discovered in the Interpretation of Dreams is nothing other than the capitalist unconscious, the intertwining of unconscious satisfaction with the structure and the logic of the capitalist mode of production.

中Freud seems to make a similar move as Saussure. The reference to the capitalist and the entrepreneur (homo oeconomicus) makes the entire comparison sound more like ‘Freud with Smith’ rather than ‘Freud with Marx’. According to classical economic liberalism, the encounter between the capitalist and the labourer takes place in a free space of equal opportunities and is actualised through the act of exchange: money for commodity, one abstraction for another. The same encounter echoes in the unconscious: psychic energy is exchanged for the idea contained in the day’s residues. We can mention in passing that in one of his later texts Freud will describe the ‘psychic energy’, in the meantime renamed libido, as the standard ‘currency’ of psychic life. Everything can be translated into this mental general equivalent. The situation is nevertheless more complex than Freud’s comparisons seem to suggest. Unconscious labour is incompatible with homo oeconomicus, so it does not even appear in the comparison. However, the discussion of dreams leaves no doubt that the ‘only essential thing in dreams is the dream-work that has influenced the thought-material’? In Freud’s example, the association of the capitalist with the ‘wish from the unconscious’ is more crucial because it exposes an essential feature of the capitalist. Unlike the entrepreneur, who conserves the reference to the economic subject of cognition, the capitalist is identified with decentralised desire, which brings the comparison closer to Marx’s description of the capitalist as the personification of the impersonal and systemic imperative of constant growth and of profit-making. Freud also mentions other possible relations between the capitalist and the entrepreneur, from their complete difference, their lesser or greater overlapping, to situations in which several entrepreneurs address the same capitalist or several capitalists support the same entrepreneur. These combinations do not change anything in the underlying relation itself, although they do blur the fact that Freud constantly speaks of unconscious desire in the singular. There is no multiplicity of desires, in contrast to wishes, but one single unconscious desire, which comes down to one insatiable imperative. It also becomes apparent that this singular desire does not imply a subject: desire is precisely a ‘process without a subject’.

中Rather than explaining unconscious production, the comparison focuses on the appearance. The actual complication emerges when the labour theory shows that the unconscious is split between desire and labour. This double character contains a further aspect that distinguishes the Freudian notion from other possible conceptions. First, the unconscious is placed in a relation of dependency on the social structure. Then this mark is interpreted as a contradiction, the constitutive split of One into Two that Freud already pushed into the foreground in his early work through the notion of the ‘psychic conflict’. When Freud applies the social link between the capitalist and the labourer to the unconscious, he literally repeats Marx’s move in Capital, where they are both progressively detached from the psychological personages, describing processes rather than persons. The unconscious desire shows that the capitalist enters the stage as an anomaly in the field of mastery: a headless master.

中As already mentioned, Freud classifies the dream work by four basic operations. His analysis shows that these operations take place on two different levels. The ground level is the condensation work and the displacement work: the two fundamental aspects of unconscious labour that match the two main linguistic operations, metaphor and metonymy. Freud privileged these processes in another comparison with social labour: ‘Dream displacement and dream condensation are the two skilled workers [Werkmeister] to whose activity we may in essence ascribe the form assumed by dreams’. The processes appear as a form of knowledge: savoir faire, knowledge without reflection, unknown knowledge. This is what differentiates the unconscious labourer from the entrepreneur, who still remains in the paradigm of the subject of cognition, for which political economy assumes that it possesses knowledge both of his or her inner interests and of the external market relations.

中The other two operations, consideration of representability and secondary elaboration, appear as a repetition of condensation and displacement within the imaginary. Freud points out that this imaginary dimension is not reducible visualisation, when during his discussion of secondary elaboration he evokes the very same lines in Heine that will three decades later serve him in his critique of Weltanschauung:中The thing that distinguishes and at the same time reveals this part of the dream-work is its purpose. This function behaves in the manner, which the poet maliciously ascribes to philosophers: it fills up the gaps in the dream-structure with shreds and patches. As a result of its efforts, the dream loses its appearance of absurdity and disconnectedness and approximates to the model of an intelligible experience. But its efforts are not always crowned with success.中The second stage of dream formation is related to this totalisation. Here the dream receives consistency and narration, which makes it comparable to the ‘intellectual construction’ of worldviews and even more so with the use-value of commodities. But the tendency of labour is not necessarily the same as in metaphor and metonymy, since it tries to fill the gap between use-value and exchange-value, between meaning and value of the unconscious formation. Freud underlines this minimal discrepancy by indicating that the task of secondary elaboration is to abolish the appearance of absurdity, which becomes striking once the ‘value of jouissance’ (as Lacan translates exchange-value in Seminar XIV) is entirely separated from meaning. On the level of secondary elaboration and the consideration of representability, the value of dreams appears in their meaning: jouissance assumes the form of joui-sens (enjoyed meaning, to refer to another Lacanian wordplay).

中When Lacan replaced Saussure with Marx, he directed psychoanalysis back to the figure of the unconscious labourer and thereby radicalised the implications of his own introduction of the subject. This orientation is most lucidly formulated in Television, where Lacan leaves no doubt that psychoanalysis and the critique of political economy come across the same subject:中Does the unconscious imply that it be listened to? To my mind, yes. But this surely does not imply that, without the discourse through which it ex-sists, one judges it as knowledge that does not think, or calculate, or judge-which doesn’t prevent it from being at work (as in dreams, for instance). Lets say that it is the ideal worker, the one Marx made the flower of capitalist economy in the hope of seeing him takeover the discourse of the master; which, in effect, is what happened, although in an unexpected form. There are surprises in these matters of discourse, and that is, indeed, the point of the unconscious [le fait de l’inconscient].中That the unconscious implies listening does not make psychoanalysis a dialogue in which it would regress back to some abstract and ideal communicative model, as various forms of psychologies and psychotherapies have done. What is at stake is that the truth regains the power of speech. The subjective manifestations of its speech are inhibitions, symptoms and anxieties that the discourse causes in the body. The speaking truth, the power of truth to be more than mere facticity or truth-value, is the main terrain where psychoanalysis encounters Marxism and the figure of the labourer is the privileged conceptual embodiment of this encounter. Practically all of Lacan’s texts from 1969 onwards address this intertwining of the unconscious subject and the capitalist labourer, thereby indicating that the transformation of the subject that psychoanalysis strives to produce in its praxis stands in immediate continuity with the political question of social change. It is not surprising that Television defines one of the psychoanalytic goals as the ‘way out of capitalist discourse’, to which Lacan adds that it ‘will not constitute progress, if it happens only for some’. In political matters, psychoanalysis envisages the same universalism as Marxist politics.

中Lacan condenses Freud’s analysis of the relation between unconscious desire, dream work and capitalism by speaking of the ideal labourer, an expression that explores the flip side of the homology between unconscious production and capitalist production. The ideal labourer is not the same as the subject of alienation. It stands for the multiplicity of operations that take place among the signifiers, to which a decentralised form of knowledge can be attributed. The ideal labourer does not know itself as a form of knowledge, but this does not prevent it from accomplishing its task. The subject of labour only enters the stage as far as the unconscious does not merely imply labour but also listening, the enunciation of truth that sabotages the automatism of unconscious knowledge, of knowledge as ‘means of jouissance’, that is, as means of production. The subject of the unconscious, by contrast, is a disturbance in the regime of knowledge, an anomaly that articulates its enunciation through the symptom: ‘There is only one social symptom - each individual is really a proletarian, that is it has no discourse of which to make a social link, in other words, a semblant’. The real status of each individual as subject in the capitalist mode of production coincides with what Marx strives to address through the proletariat. The proletarian is ‘the subject as a response of the real’. Here we again encounter the echo of Marx’s subject-hypothesis that orthodox Marxism later abolished through the identification of the proletariat with the subject of knowledge. To paraphrase Hegel, the worldview Marxism theorised the proletarian merely as substance (class-consciousness) and no longer as subject (labour-power). Instead of transforming the capitalist subject, class-consciousness transformed the ideal labourer, making of its unknown knowledge a reflected ‘scientific’ knowledge. This, too, is the surprise that Lacan alludes to in Television: the historical and the structural development goes from the master’s discourse, whose modern version is capitalism before the second industrial revolution, to the university discourse in post-industrial capitalism, where it is precisely knowledge, hence the ideal labourer, that assumes the position of the master. The same structural shift was accomplished in the Soviet Union, where the knowledge of the Party, the historic embodiment of the proletarian class-consciousness, became the privileged discursive agent.

中Lacan’s conclusion is thus: the proletarian is the subject of the unconscious. Marx and Freud undoubtedly placed their wager on the revolutionary potential of this figure. For Marx, the political task of the industrial proletariat consists in its realisation, that is, its self-abolition through the abolition of labour-power, which would produce a new social link and a new figure of subjectivity. Freud, too, thought that the discovery of the unconscious would initiate a transformation that is both epistemological and social. His critiques of religion in The Future of an Illusion, of politics in Group Psychology and the Analysis of the Ego, and of capitalism in Civilisation and Its Discontents were directed against the social structures that are rooted in the relations of domination. The revolutionary potential of the subject of psychoanalysis was supposed to demonstrate that the ego is not a master in his own household, and thereby to overthrow the ‘I-cracy’ (Lacan) that marked the modern philosophies of consciousness and on which economic liberalism grounded its homo oeconomicus.

中Lacan clearly assumes a more realistic position and detects the political failure of Marxism and Freudianism. The proletarian, this privileged figure of social and unconscious labour, did indeed accomplish a social and an epistemological revolution, but this revolution essentially took place in the relation between power and knowledge. The liberation of labour introduced a social system in which abstract knowledge assumed the position of the master. The ideal labourer meanwhile changed its appearance and turned into a figure of domination both in capitalism (the expert, the Eurocrat) and in Stalinism (the party bureaucrat). Marx in fact predicted the possibility of such a course of events. In the first volume of Capital, the capitalist transformation of labour is accomplished in the technological organisation of production, the inversion of the relation between the labourer and the machine. When Marx writes about the use of machines in capitalism, he thematises constantly the essential role of scientific knowledge in the progressive social implementation of capitalist abstractions. The importance of machines is not in their material presence but in the fact that they exemplify the productive nature of knowledge in capitalism, knowledge as a means of production and as a tool of modern power relations. For this reason, Marx assumes a reserved position towards the Luddite movement. His main concern was that they mistakenly saw the problem in machines themselves and not in the new social role of knowledge that these machines actualise in the production process. Their immediate attack on the machines could indeed be considered the flip side of the capitalist fetishisation of machines as the producers of surplus-value.

中Lacan’s ideal labourer translates Freud’s skilled worker, condensation and displacement, the logical operations that do their labour, without knowing themselves as a form of knowledge. The designation of the ideal labourer as ‘knowledge that does not think, judge, or calculate’ immediately evokes a crucial passage from the Interpretation of Dreams, where Freud provides a condensed account of the dream work from the viewpoint of secondary elaboration and draws the following conclusion:中Two separate functions may be distinguished in mental activity during the construction of a dream: the production of the dream-thoughts, and their transformation into the content of the dream ... However many interesting and puzzling questions the dream-thoughts may involve, such questions have, after all, no special relation to dreams and do not call for treatment among the problems of dreams. On the other hand, the second function of mental activity during dream construction, the transformation of the unconscious thoughts into the content of the dream, is peculiar to dream-life and characteristic of it. This dream-work proper diverges further from our picture of waking thought than has been supposed even by the most determined depreciator of psychical functioning during the formation of dreams. The dream-work is not simply more careless, more irrational, more forgetful and more incomplete than waking thought; it is completely different from it qualitatively and for that reason not immediately comparable with it. It does not think, calculate or judge in any way at all; it restricts itself to giving things a new form.中The double character of unconscious labour is striking, but the actual object of dream work is the form and not the content, the very same form that supports the satisfaction of unconscious desire. The transformation of preconscious material involves a production of appearance that will not only lead to the satisfaction of desire but will literally mask desire in a wish. Dream work essentially consists in creating the conditions for this masking, which also codifies other satisfaction into satisfaction, exchange-value into use-value, and finally jouissance into pleasure. ‘Dreams are wish-fulflments’ is therefore anything but an innocent statement.

中The supposedly enigmatic character of dreams is of no particular interest to Freud. He explains it as an effect of the form of the dream itself. This is why psychoanalysis does not interpret dreams by giving them meaning. The hermeneutic strategy would focus on the content and in doing so overlook the mechanism of the dream production, the labour and the subject of labour. Thereby it would fetishise dreams by attributing them a deeper meaning. It is interesting to observe how Freud rejects the appearance of enigma and the postulate of irrationality in the procedures of the dream. He implicitly refers to the difference between concrete and abstract labour: dreams display the pure form of rationality because the labour that produces them is stripped of positive qualities like thinking, calculating and judging, qualities that still define the subject of cognition. Because the dream work merely accomplishes its task, it is careful, correct, unforceful, and thus ideal: labour without qualities.

中Something nevertheless goes wrong in this dream factory, and this is yet another aspect of surprise that the unconscious introduces into discourse. Freud soon discovered that not all dreams confirm the general scenario of wish-fulfilment. He came across dreams that reproduced traumatic experiences, for instance those reported by war neurotics or the sexually abused; and finally there is the famous dream of the burning child that Freud initially took as an example of wish-fulfilment. By constantly returning to a traumatic experience - war, abuse, death and so on -these dreams unveil the compulsion to repeat. With this discovery, traumatic neurosis turns out to be the collateral damage of capitalism. Cultural discontent will immediately become the main theme of Freud’s critique of modern culture. The dreams that do not confirm the general dispositif bear the character of awakening, sabotaging the production of jouissance. In this respect the unconscious is not reducible to one single discursive structure. It already raises the question of its exit.

中When Lacan reaffirmed the linguistic structure of the unconscious, he introduced the term that brings together Marx and Freud’s analysis of labour. This is the function of ca parle, it speaks. The psychoanalytic intervention operates on three levels: thinking, working and speaking. Discussions of psychoanalysis often mention that Freud’s invention consisted in the fact that he listened to the speech of his hysteric patients, who revealed to him the secret of the unconscious: the hysteric symptom speaks and by speaking enunciates the truth of the discourse that determines it. This enunciation already inhibits the mechanism of satisfaction. In this psychoanalysis most directly coincides with Marx’s discovery that in labour, too, an enunciation takes place, which articulates the truth of the capitalist relations of production. This is where Marx’s invention of the social symptom gains its full weight for psychoanalysis. The symptom is the encounter of the proletarian and the subject of the unconscious, of the labourer and the speaking being.

LUSTGEWINN

中Only four years after the publication of the Interpretation of Dreams, its lessons found a further development in the elaboration of the libidinal unconscious. In 1905, Freud published two apparently unrelated books, Jokes and Their Relation to the Unconscious and Three Essays on the Theory of Sexuality. While the book on jokes continues the direction of the Interpretation of Dreams, both method- and style-wise, the Three Essays replace the reference to language with the body, and the structural analysis of satisfaction with the theory of sexual development. The press welcomed the first book, while the discussion of sexuality encountered resistance and discontent. Despite apparent differences, the two works nevertheless meet in the introduction of the Freudian notion of jouissance, condensed in the expression Lustgewinn, pleasure gain or pleasure profit, in which it is not difficult to recognise the conceptual mediator between Lacan’s surplus-jouissance and Marx’s surplus-value. With this notion, Freud finally names the object of the unconscious production and the object that satisfies the unconscious tendency. Both works also intersect in that they introduce the tendency that will henceforth occupy Freud’s theoretical work and call for the elaboration of a metapsychology: the drive and its topological paradoxes. Lustgewinn and the move towards Trieblehre, the theory of the drive, overcame the opposition between structure and anatomy, situating psychoanalysis in the grey zone their intersection. Freud thereby inaugurated the direction that Lacan came back to when defining the signifier as an apparatus of jouissance.

中Freud from the very outset approached the modus operandi of the mental apparatus through economic metaphors. As his theories became more complex, this economic reality, too, displayed its antagonistic features more and more, one of them being the tendency of the unconscious production towards the absolutisation of the production of jouissance. ‘Our mental activities’, writes Freud in one of his later texts, ‘pursue either a useful aim or an immediate pleasure gain’, again in accordance with the distinction between use-value and exchange-value. The analysis of dreams has already shown that the satisfaction of desire does not address the use-value of the day residues but aims at the value of jouissance they obtain through the dream work, placing unconscious labour in equivocity with unconscious desire. The term Lustgewinn defines pleasure as surplus, hence as something that the mental activities reach beside their tendency to usefulness. Seen from the perspective of use-value and of the need it presupposes, pleasure appears as an affection that accompanies the abolition of a bodily stimulus and the decrease of a tension. From the viewpoint of value, however, pleasure is no longer a more or less accidental side effect but the object of satisfaction. As such, Lustgewinn does not relate to any quality, which also implies that it has no corresponding need. The shift from usefulness to uselessness that directs the Freudian concept of Lust explains why Lacan translated the German term with ‘jouissance’ and not ‘pleasure’. From the very outset it is clear that a fundamental subversion is at stake in Lustgewinn, which is not an insignificant side effect of satisfaction. The satisfaction of needs is always-already parasitised, colonised and subverted by the satisfaction of unconscious tendencies (desire and drive), whose existence depends on the autonomy of the signifier and of value.

中The connection of pleasure with use-value, the definition of commodity as what satisfies a need and serves as a source of pleasure is also Marx’s point of departure, where different types or qualities of needs are equated in the following way:中The commodity is, first of all, an external object, a thing which through its qualities satisfies human needs of whatever kind. The nature of such needs, whether they arise, for example, from the stomach or from fantasy, makes no difference. Nor does it matter here how the object satisfies these needs, whether directly as a means of subsistence, i. e. , an object of consumption, or indirectly as a means of production.中Hasty psychoanalytic readings will conclude that Marx begins his analysis of commodity form by foreclosing the dimension of desire and hence of the subject because he simply equates the immediate bodily needs and the needs that are symbolically mediated and in the last instance rooted in fantasy - hence needs and desires in the strict sense. However, this is precisely what Marx does not do. By exposing the double character of commodities, he introduces the equivocity between both regimes of value and the tendencies of satisfaction, which will in the end relativise the non-fantasmatic status of need and use-value. Marx introduces his developments with the claim that, in order to analyse the qualitative aspect of commodity, we first need to abolish the division of immediate and mediated satisfaction, on the one hand, and physiological and psychological satisfaction, on the other. The commodity form becomes the universal source of pleasure: in the modern universe ‘there are only commodity pleasures’; there is thus one single satisfaction, which is nevertheless internally complicated due to the split of commodity between ‘qualities without matter’ and ‘matter without qualities’, to repeat Milner. If even fantasies are marked by use-value, the inverse is no less true, exchange-value colonises physiological or psychological needs. The complication envisaged by Marx is thus apparent. In order to understand any satisfaction whatsoever, one first needs to analyse the structure of commodity. A useless object such as a diamond is evidently fetishised, but this fetishist relation is accompanied by a fantasmatic need. Desire traverses the need and is supported by the fantasmatic screen of usefulness. The simultaneity of the satisfaction of needs and the other satisfaction (of desire and drive) unveils the coupling of two heterogeneities in a unified object, one of the functions of fantasy being precisely to link the non-linkable. Through this fantasmatic link, the use-value and the exchange-value contaminate each other and make the object in question sehr vertrackt, as Marx writes, complicated, fuzzy and even insane.

中When Marx equates the physiological need (stomach) with the intellectual need (fantasy), he indicates that the need should not be understood as quasi-natural. With need we already entered the discursive field, and need cannot be exactly isolated from its dialectical relation with demand and desire. There are no innocent needs, the satisfaction of which would not be structurally determined. Going back to Freud, his distinction between usefulness and pleasure shows that the satisfaction of needs could only cause pleasure as a side effect and that this side contains no pleasure-gain. Usefulness and need remain in the perspective of what Freud describes as the reduction of tension, or the abolition of bodily affection, which still suggests that the mental apparatus contains an essentially self-regulatory tendency towards homeostasis, the Aristotelian right measure. In order to speak of pleasure-gain, a third term must stand between need and satisfaction: discourse (social link, difference). There is no jouissance without discourse, and there is no other jouissance than a discursive one. Lacan emphasises this in the aforementioned translation of exchange-value with the value of jouissance. From the viewpoint of discourse, needs and their satisfactions are always-already stained with the other satisfaction that is tied to the libidinal body and to the materiality of the signifier. The concreteness of the object, whose qualities are supposed to cause pleasure, fades, and what counts is only the ‘abstract’ object, which finally inverses the relation between pleasure and tension. This is where the structure of the mental apparatus approaches the capitalist economic model. In the other satisfaction, tension is no longer reduced but increased. The satisfaction of needs is of minor importance and is entirely integrated in the other satisfaction, as its internal, quasi-fictional moment. The unconscious tendency and the capitalist drive for self-valorisation first and foremost demand a constant production of surplus and a constant growth in tension. This is one of the main features of the Freudian notion of the drive, which demands a thorough re-elaboration of the functioning of the mental apparatus and the abolition of the initial homeostatic model.

中The dialectic of value shows that use-value relates to exchange-value in a similar way as appearance to logic. Freud will come to an astonishingly similar conclusion: ‘What is useful is itself (as is well known) only a circuitous path to pleasurable satisfaction.’ Dreams fall into this category, whereby Freud reminds his reader that it would be wrong to consider dreaming an activity that merely concludes and resolves the day’s preoccupations in a hallucinatory (performative) way: ‘That is the business of preconscious thought. Useful work of this kind is as remote from dreams as is any intention of conveying information to another person.’ Dreams minimise the usefulness and the referentiality of the signifier. Instead, they intensify its autonomy and causality. In this respect, capitalism, too, is an eternal dream, or rather a perpetuated nightmare, from which it appears impossible to wake up.

中Once desire and the drive enter the picture, every satisfaction of needs seems problematic: ‘All the needs of speaking beings are contaminated by the fact of being involved in an other satisfaction that they may not live up to.’ The commodity form is the privileged materialisation of this distortion, and even when Marx discussed the developed form of this contamination, fictitious capital, where the creation of value out of value (M - M’) becomes the rule of production, he nevertheless repeated the critical gesture from the first volume, according to which the self-engendering appearance of capital is grounded in the fetishist fantasy of direct overlapping of quality and value. Freud took the same direction in his move beyond the pleasure principle, from the homeostatic to the conflictual conception of the psychic apparatus, where jouissance appears to be deprived of all referentiality and becomes its own subject. But it would be wrong to conclude that in the libidinal unconscious the negative subject of the signifier is abolished, that the unconscious labourer vanishes, or that the repressed unconscious tendency becomes its own productive labourer. This would be fetishisation of jouissance, homologous to the fetishisation of financial abstractions.

中Freud discovered in the production of pleasure-gain a transformation of pleasure. No satisfaction of needs can produce pleasure as profit because the pleasure that accompanies the satisfaction of needs merely signals the re-establishment of the supposedly homeostatic order that turns out to be fictional from the viewpoint of the other satisfaction. The keyword here is homeostasis, which Freud in 1905 still believed determined the overall functioning of the mental apparatus. Lustgewinn is the first sign that the homeostasis of the pleasure principle is mere fiction. Nevertheless it demonstrates that no satisfaction of needs can produce more pleasure, just as no surplus-value can logically follow from the circulation ( C - M - C). Surplus-jouissance, the connection of pleasure with profitmaking, does not simply undermine the supposedly homeostatic character of the pleasure principle; it shows that the homeostasis is a necessary fiction, which structures and supports unconscious production, just as the imaginary achievement of worldview mechanisms consisted in providing an enclosed whole, without cracks in its overall construction. Lustgewinn is Freud’s first conceptual confrontation with what will later be situated beyond the pleasure principle, the compulsion to repeat, and what will introduce the psychoanalytic equivalent to the circulation (M - C - M’).

中The introduction of Lustgewinn retroactively explained the status of pleasure and satisfaction in the Interpretation of Dreams, but it also complicates the matter because unconscious desire was replaced by the drive. In both cases, the surplus-object functions differently. On the level of desire, it appears as lack, absence and negativity. This appearance is linked to the metonymic structure, which makes the object shift from one concrete embodiment to another. Wajcman extensively elaborated this logical articulation in the case of the collector and the miser. The structure of collection remains open because the object ofcollecting is notidentical to the collected objects. No object is the object that would totalise the collection, thereby bringing about the satisfaction of desire. Another case is provided by Freud’s dream analysis, where the reality of unconscious desire depends on the association of apparently disparate elements. Desire coincides with its own interpretation, the combination of the material from the day’s remains and with the codification of its insistence. One way to meet the surplus is thus through the metonymic movement, where the encounter with the object always fails: no object is the object of desire, and, consequently, the surplus is always confronted in the form of a lack. For the unconscious desire, the surplus is never enough surplus; it cannot be associated with one object alone. It is only in relation to the drive that the surplus appears positive. Instead of the metonymic shifting and withdrawing of the object, the drive is structured through circulation and repetition.

中The paradoxes of the drive were not an unknown for Marx, whose manuscripts already contained the connection between the structure of the drive, the abstract nature of the general equivalent and the production of surplus-value:中Money is therefore not only an object, but is the object of greed . . . Greed as such, as a particular form of the drive, i.e., as distinct from the craving for a particular kind of wealth, e.g., for clothes, weapons, jewels, women, wine, etc. is possible only when general wealth, wealth as such, has become individualised in a particular thing, i.e. , as soon as money is posited in its third quality. Money is therefore not only the object but also the fountainhead of greed. The mania for possessions is possible without money; but greed itself is the product of a definite social development, not natural, as opposed to historical.中The drive is intimately linked to the double status of the general equivalent - as a means of exchange and as a particular use-value that totalises the universe of objects. Unlike desire, whose object is not yet identified with a particular embodiment and therefore supports the structure of metonymy, the drive presupposes the paradox of concrete universality, what the general equivalent is supposed to be. The desire for the object (wealth) thus accumulates a collection of objects that embody value - it focuses on the objects of value and not on value as object. The drive, on the other hand, is fixated on the object, the general equivalent, which due to its paradoxical status - being both singular and universal, a commodity and a Commodity in which all commodities are reflected supports the infinitisation of satisfaction, which is to say, its impossibility and endless perpetuation. The capitalist drive for self-valorisation is an unsatisfiable demand, to which no labour can live up to. Marx also made an important point when he detached the notion of the drive from its biological or physiological connotation. He entirely conditioned it with the social existence of the general equivalent and with historical development. The capitalist drive is therefore not the only possible drive. There is something like a history of the drive, a historical transformation of fixations, which alters the social articulation of the drive together with the function of the general equivalent in the predominant mode of production. In Plato and Aristotle, the problem of the drive is indicated, although in the universe of antiquity this problem was not the same as in the capitalist universe, where the mode of production is based on the mathematisation of surplus-value and on the unleashing of the demand for self-valorisation in the form of fictitious capital. The old spirit of usury is by far no embryonic form of the modern spirit of capitalism, even if both can be explained through the existence of the general equivalent. Let us recall another crucial passage from the Grundrisse:中Hunger is hunger, but the hunger gratified by cooked meat eaten with a knife and fork is a different hunger from that which bolts down raw meat with the aid of hand, nail and tooth. Production thus produces not only the object but also the manner of consumption, not only objectively but also subjectively. Production thus creates the consumer. Production not only supplies a material for the need, but it also supplies a need for the material.中Marx again aims at the historical and the social transformation of the drive, leaving no doubt that the placement of the drive at the intersection of presumably natural need and its cultural articulation can be considered a predecessor of the psychoanalytic notion, for the Freudian notion of the drive is not the hunger that swallows raw meat but the hunger that reaches satisfaction through the montage of cooked meat, cutlery and table manners. Indeed, Lacan brought this to a crucial point when he compared the drive to a surrealist collage, underlining that the montage of the heterogeneous elements contains a differentiation between the aim and the goal, so again between use-value and exchange-value.

中Let us now pass over to Freud’s discovery of surplus-jouissance in his analyses of jokes and humour. In Jokes and Their Relation to the Unconscious, the production of surplus is discussed in the social context. Freud emphasises this at the very beginning when he justifies the fact that, after already writing on dreams and failed actions, he dedicated another scientific study to an apparently marginal and insignificant object. The scientific discussion of jokes can be justified by the fact that a ‘new joke acts almost like an event of universal interest’; a joke is never merely a joke - it is a social process’. It codifies nothing less than the relation between the unconscious and the social link. Unlike dreams, which appear to be a private activity of the dreamer and where the presence of social mechanisms is harder to demonstrate (after all the function of dreams is to preserve sleep, the withdrawal from the social), jokes immediately point towards a social framework; they reveal the structure of social relations and the social economy of surplus-jouissance.

中The matter is, of course, more complicated. It is not that the unconscious is more social in jokes than in dreams, and that one changes the register of the individual unconscious for the social unconscious. On the contrary, for Freud, dreams and jokes present two cases of the same discursive condition. The discussion of jokes in no respect shifts from the individual to the social; instead, it demonstrates that the unconscious stands beyond the division between interiority and exteriority, individuality and society, private and public. If dreams revealed the inscription of the social link into the unconscious, jokes demonstrate the manifestation of the unconscious in the social link, two sides of the causality of the signifier.

中The analysis of jokes is introduced with the note that their character is not linked to a specific thought but to their form of expression, wording (Wortlaut). The entire focus is on the role of equivocity, which actualises the split between meaning and value. The efficiency of jokes depends on how Witzarbeit, the unconscious labour in jokes, forms the word. Unconscious production is again directed by condensation and displacement, but in this case their combination reveals an economic paradox.

中Different joke techniques meet in a common strategy, which consists of the multiple use of the same material, the recycling of the given. Equivocity, double meaning or wordplay, combines different contexts in the same product. The multiple use of the same material characterises the non-metaphorical use of condensation: ‘play upon words is nothing other than a condensation without substitute-formation’. In this transformation of condensation, Freud encounters the economic tendency towards saving: ‘All these techniques are dominated by a tendency to compression, or rather to saving. It all seems to be a question of economy. In Hamlet’s words: ‘“Thrift, thrift, Horatio!”’ From this perspective, the unconscious labourer appears as the ideal saver, whose tendency to condensation is supposed to produce a surplus: save in order to create profit and to stabilise economic relations. Sounds rather familiar.

中The tendency towards saving is declared to be the general characteristic of joke techniques, although there is something economically inefficient in this form of saving, since the entire process is accompanied by displacement. In order to explain the apparent absurdity of unconscious saving, Freud recurs to the following economic comparison:中The economies made by the joke-technique do not greatly impress us. They may remind us, perhaps, of the way in which some housewives economise when they spend time and money on a journey to a distant market because vegetables are to be had there a few farthings cheaper. What does a joke save by its technique? The putting together of a few new words, which would mostly have emerged without any trouble. Instead of that, it has to take the trouble to search out the one word which covers the two thoughts. Indeed, it must often first transform one of the thoughts into an unusual form which will provide a basis for its combination with the second thought. Would it not have been simpler, easier, and, in fact, more economical to have expressed the two thoughts as they happened to come, even if this involved no common form of expression?Is not the economy in words uttered more than balanced by the expenditure on intellectual effort? And who saves by that? Who gains by it?中Saving turns into spending and the unconscious appears as an ideal consumer. The problem is that metonymic movement creates long detours and actualises a tendency to spend. The combination of both operations, condensation and displacement, saving and spending, thus produces an apparent contradiction, an economic absurdity. Freud’s analysis shows that jokes generate a loss in order to reach pleasure-profit. The surplus is produced at the background of the interdependency between spending and saving, and the housewife metaphor is pertinent only in so far as it shows that saving should not be regarded as the ultimate goal of the process but as something that can as well be considered a form of spending, a production of surplus that differs from what would be the accumulation of savings. The appearance of saving masks that there is a different kind of production in the background. Similarly, the imperative of economic cuts and restrictions is the inevitable flip side of the imperative to produce surplus. The housewife example shows that the profit should not be attributed to the housewife but to the entire procedure. Economy can make profit because she is losing money in a seemingly rational economisation.

中This structural operation is deployed in the social dimension of jokes. Jokes ‘should not, after all, be described as pointless or aimless, since [they have] the unmistakable aim of evoking pleasure in [their] hearers’. They cause pleasure, and this feature entails a shift from usefulness to uselessness. At this point, things complicate for the same reason as in dreams. The pleasure in jokes is reached through detour and at the background of the preceding renunciation of pleasure: ‘If we do not require our mental apparatus at the moment for supplying one of our indispensable satisfactions, we allow it itself to work in the direction of pleasure and we seek to derive pleasure from its own activity.’ When the mental apparatus does not satisfy needs, it produces pleasure, but it is impossible to determine when one activity ceases and the other begins. Production needs to be associated with a problematic tendency, which opens up three possibilities: either the tendency is innocent (which is questionable in itself; why would it then be masked?), or jokes serve either a hostile or an obscene tendency (aggression or exposure). The procedure is marked by a libidinal investment that points back to the drive, this new object of study in connection to unconscious formations and, one could say, a new metaphor of the capitalist, the unconscious investor that has now replaced desire. Desire did not know what it wanted and has metonymically shifted from one object to another; the drive, however, ‘knows’ what it wants. It is fixated on the object.

中As an example in which the hostile and the obscene tendency are combined, Freud mentions smut, where the psychoanalytic gaze meets unconscious production and its object at its purest. This is also where the third person that supports the mechanism of jokes and reveals the importance of the social link in the production of jouissance finally enters the picture. Three persons condition the manifestation of an unconscious tendency: the narrator, the target of the joke, and the listener. Freud makes an important remark that the person who tells the joke is not the same as the person who enjoys its effects. The production of jouissance is outsourced to the side of the passive listener. It is tied to what is heard and to the combination of the aggressive and the obscene content that does not match any need. In order to illustrate this structure, Freud proposes a detailed analysis of smut:中We know what is meant by ‘smut’: the intentional bringing into prominence of sexual facts and relations by speech ... It is a further relevant fact that smut is directed to a particular person, by whom one is sexually excited and who, on hearing it, is expected to become aware of the speaker’s excitement and as a result to become sexually excited in turn. Instead of this excitement the other person maybe led to feel shame or embarrassment, which is only a reaction against the excitement and, in a roundabout way, is an admission of it. Smut is thus originally directed towards women and maybe equated with attempts at seduction. If a man in a company of men enjoys telling or listening to smut, the original situation, which owing to social inhibitions cannot be realised, is at the same time imagined. A person who laughs at smut that he hears is laughing as though he were the spectator of an act of sexual aggression.中We can remark here that, once the signifier is envisaged as an apparatus of jouissance, language appears as an endless smut. Now Freud’s conclusion:中When the first person finds his libidinal impulse inhibited by the woman, he develops a hostile trend against that second person and calls on the originally interfering third person as his ally. Through the first person’s smutty speech the woman is exposed before the third, who, as listener, has now been bribed by the effortless satisfaction of his own libido.中Smut lacks the formal conditions of a joke. While a joke would make a long detour in order to mask the sexual insinuation with a sophisticated metaphor, smut openly talks about sexuality, ‘the uttering of an undisguised nudity gives the first person enjoyment and makes the third person laugh’. Here Freud very quickly discovers that smut leads to the very core of social segregation. For Freud, who speaks here as a sincere bourgeois, the satisfaction through smut characterises the common man, while in the upper classes smut is tolerated only on the condition that it appear as a joke, with a complex codification of obscene content through condensation and displacement. In smut we encounter the zero level of metaphor and metonymy, while in refined social circles smut is transformed into an allusion. The common point between smut and joke nevertheless remains the satisfaction of the drive in face of an obstacle: ‘They circumvent this obstacle and in that way draw pleasure from a source which the obstacle had made inaccessible.’ The social context shows that the first case, the use of smut among the common men, only apparently differs from its sophistication in the upper classes. The inhibition of the drive is not weaker among the workers and the peasants. When Freud inclines to the conclusion that the common man is one step closer to the satisfaction and that he enjoys more than the upper classes, he repeats a typical bourgeois prejudice, yet he also shows that the inhibition is structural and that both smut and jokes are conditioned by the discrepancy between the need and the demand, pleasure and jouissance, usefulness and uselessness. If we imagine a situation in which the narrator is confronted with the object of smut, the conditions of the production of jouissance are abolished. What the narrator confronts in this case is castration. He can enjoy only through the third person, which introduces the dimension of the Other, where the linguistic equivocity produces the narrator’s own pleasure-gain in the listener. There is no difference between the upper and the lower classes, as far as their relation to jouissance is concerned. In both cases, sexuality and violence need to be masked in order to support the production of jouissance, even if this masquerade means that sexuality is masked into sexuality and violence into violence, as in the case of smut.

中Smut is in no respect more authentic from a sophisticated joke. It merely shows that the immediate addressing of sexuality, the obscenity of the smut, masks the impossibility of immediate satisfaction because sexuality does not correspond to any need. Lacan’s axiom ‘There is no sexual relation’ implies precisely that there is no sexual need. Sexuality is the field where the production of jouissance takes place. The procreative ‘use-value’ of sexuality is mere fiction. For this reason, the superego, too, does not prohibit enjoyment, it demands it, and when Lacan proposes his minimal prosopopoeia of the superego (Enjoy!) he actually spells out the echo of capitalist imperatives in the mental apparatus, the obscenity of the capitalist superego. The unsatisfiable demand for more, for the constant and uninterrupted production of surplus emerges from the gap in the Other, which points to the cut between use-value and exchange value that the commodity form imposes on every object in the capitalist universe. Or to formulate it with the main economic lesson of Freud’s analysis of humour, the pleasure in jokes does not mean that some lost jouissance is regained and the gap between the subject and the object is abolished but that jouissance is produced on the background of a structural impossibility of satisfaction.

中Freud’s crucial political insight was that every social order builds on libidinal economy. Consequently, an important part of efficiency of capitalism derives from the fact that it successfully mobilises the structural deadlocks of libidinal economy - the infamous ‘inexistence of sexual relation’ - and transforms them in the source of profit. Because its logic of production is coupled to the desire and the drive, it makes little sense, from the psychoanalytic point of view, to insist that capitalism represses sexuality, desire or drive. Quite the contrary, the capitalist mode of production seems to be the first social and economic system in history that created ideal conditions for their social realisation. No wonder, then, that Freud found in the relation between capital and labour the best illustration possible for the unconscious mode of production. Capitalism stretches its consequences in the unconscious, but this does not imply that capitalism is the unconscious.

REPRESSION AND PRODUCTION

中The reason for the impossibility of immediate satisfaction of the drive lies in Verdrängung, repression, in which Freud detects another, probably the most unusual, type of unconscious labour:中The power which makes it difficult or impossible ... to enjoy undisguised obscenity is termed by us ‘repression’ ... It is our belief that culture and higher education have a large influence on the development of repression, and we suppose that, under such conditions, the psychical organisation undergoes an alteration . . as a result of which what was formerly felt as agreeable now seems unacceptable and is rejected with all possible psychical force. The repression labour [Verdrängungsarbeit] of civilisation brings it about that primary possibilities of enjoyment, which have now, however, been repudiated by the censorship in us, are lost to us. But to the human psyche all renunciation is exceedingly difficult, and so we find that tendentious jokes provide a means of undoing the renunciation and retrieving what was lost. When we laugh at a refined obscene joke, we are laughing at the same thing that makes a peasant laugh at a coarse piece of smut. In both cases the pleasure springs from the same source.中Freud’s description immediately recalls the ‘repressive hypothesis’ that Foucault criticised in his work. On the one hand stands the labour of repression, which serves higher tendencies striving to preserve the cultural ideals and institutions, and, on the other, the originary yet excluded jouissance, the immediate possibilities of enjoyment, which had to be abandoned in favour of cultural progress. Cultural phenomena such as jokes create the impression of bypassing the prohibition and regaining a part of the lost and forbidden jouissance. Is this the ultimate point Freud’s theory of repression wants to make? The quoted passage certainly supports this, for Freud places the existence of the drive before culture, thereby formulating the hypothesis of a jouissance before jouissance, an originary jouissance, which was subsequently prohibited and mortified by the intervention of the law. Freud’s later theoretical endeavours tried to embody this hypothetic jouissance in the mythological figure of the primordial father, but his phylogenetic speculations are marked by a complex structure, which questions simplified critical readings. In Totem and Taboo, where Freud’s main topic of discussion is the birth of law from the originary patricide, the primal father is evidently a personification of originary jouissance, but he is equally an instance that imposes originary prohibition - the right to jouissance belongs to him only, not to his sons, the subjects of the obscene paternal violence, in which jouissance and law are indistinguishable. The primal father can stand for a jouissance before jouis-sance only insofar as he is also a law before the law. This fusion of jouissance with the law makes him an insatiable instance, demanding renunciation from all other members of the human horde.

中Freud’s descriptions of this prehistoric father-figure therefore show that his two main features merely exaggerate both tendencies that were discussed in relation to jokes, violence and obscenity: violence over his sons and obscene right over all women. The primal father is literally a joke -but a joke that Freud took seriously. Far from resolving the dilemmas that pushed Freud’s theories towards an epistemological deadlock, its speculative discussion merely condenses the paradoxes of the actually existing libidinal economy in one hypothetical character. Levi-Strauss and Lacan already recognised in the tale of originary patricide that Freud adopted from the ethnological and evolutionary context a scientific myth. But in Freud’s case, this myth becomes a curious structural equivalent of what Marx strived to address under primitive accumulation, a historical fiction, which strives to outline the genesis of modern antagonisms that determine both subjective and social reality.

中The repressive hypothesis, tempting as it may be, and the myth of the primordial father do not succeed in resolving all the immanent contradictions that Freud encounters in unconscious labour, namely that it produces pleasure-gain and creates long detours that apparently sabotage immediate satisfaction. The labour of repression is split between the achievements of condensation and displacement, on the one hand, and those of suppression and censorship, on the other. Unconscious production is conditioned by this discordance, showing that at least one segment of the repression questions its simplified understanding as a force that works from the higher mental or cultural instances (the ego and the superego) on the repressed desires and drives (the id). Being a productive unconscious labour, and even the most general description for the variety of its achievements, repression must be dissociated from the meaning attributed to it by the repressive hypothesis, namely that of suppression and oppression. The misunderstanding is surely encouraged by Freud’s initial explanations of repression, but it was strengthened through the translations of Verdrängung, in which notably the English and French translators heard oppression and suppression.

中One of the main achievements of Lacan’s return to Freud consisted in reaffirming the primacy of repression, in terms of productive labour, over the repressed, thereby providing the necessary ground for distinguishing repression from suppression or oppression. Repression may create the conditions for oppression, but it is not its synonym. Far from being instances and institutions of repression, family and society are its products, thereby assuming the same status as the repressed drives and desires. Once repression is distinguished from oppression, its productive character appears double. Freud’s book on jokes already showed that repression plays the crucial role in the production of jouissance, while the later metapsychological writings argued that it also constitutes the repressed. Like alienation, repression, as well, is immanently doubled on constitutive and constituted repression, whereby Freud addresses the constitutive repression in the notion of Urverdrängung, originary repression. The notion certainly accentuates the transcendental character of repression, which immediately recalls the structuralist transcendentalism of the symbolic. But originary repression goes a step further because it also exposes the inherently twofold structure of repression that, from the autonomy of symbolic structure, deduced two productive achievements.

中Before considering the significance of repression for the encounter of psychoanalysis with Marxism, it is necessary to recall the basic accounts of Freud’s theory of repression. Repression is revealed as a compromise procedure - Mittelding, intermediate thing-between escape and condemnation, which already deprives it of the exclusively negative connotation that later readings of Freud ended up privileging. It neither avoids the repressed tendency nor refuses its satisfaction. The central question is why the tendency is repressed in the first place, and the spontaneous answer would most likely be that its satisfaction would cause unpleasure. This is precisely not the case:中A necessary condition of its happening must clearly be that the drive’s attainment of its aim should produce unpleasure instead of pleasure. But we cannot well imagine such a contingency. There are no such drives: satisfaction of a drive is always pleasurable [lustvoll]. We should have to assume certain peculiar circumstances, some sort of process by which the pleasure of satisfaction is changed into unpleasure.中Every satisfaction is lustvoll, full of pleasure; there is no satisfaction without the production of pleasure. In order to respond to this dilemma, the notions of the drive and of pleasure need to be questioned thoroughly.

中The Freudian concept of the drive remains controversial even today. The term is adopted from the physiological and biological context, and even from mechanics, just as labour-power, but it describes a phenomenon that, even if traversing the biological body, reaches beyond its limits. In the naturalistic context, the drive stands for a bodily need, which can be traced back to physiological mechanisms. Freud, accordingly, distinguishes between drives that point to a quasi-natural need (e. g hunger and thirst)this was probably the reason why Trieb was initially translated as ‘instinct’-where repression is out of the question, and drives that deviate from this apparently natural satisfaction and are subjected to repression (in this category, Freud situated sexuality):中Let us take the case in which a drive stimulus such as hunger remains unsatisfied. It then becomes imperative and can be allayed by nothing but the action that satisfies it; it keeps up a constant tension of need. Nothing in the nature of a repression seems in this case to come remotely into question.中In this physiological sense, hence in relation to the preservation of organism, the drive is entirely reducible to need and cannot become the target of repression. It can be satisfied only by a corresponding action (eating, drinking and so on). The drive that demands the labour of repression is too symbolic to be biological or physiological. This, and nothing else, is the meaning of Freud’s claim that the drive ‘appears to us as a concept on the frontier between the mental and the somatic’ or as ‘the psychical representative of the stimuli originating from within the organism and reaching the mind’. This careful placement of the driven either physiological nor psychological - sufficiently indicates that Freud aims beyond the classical mind-body dualism, without therefore slipping into a vitalist monism. The drive is the border that from within traverses and splits the body on the physiological and the libidinal, so that we are dealing with some sort of conflictual monism including negativity, precisely the negativity of representation, which brings the materiality of the signifier and the causality that depends on its autonomy into the picture. As an internal border, which makes the biological equivocal with the linguistic, the drive remains a bodily phenomenon and even appears indistinguishable from the need it translates or represents. Fusing a physiological stimulus with its representation, the drive becomes a material echo of linguistic autonomy, but it is also what the intervention of the signifier isolates in the tendencies of the organism towards self-preservation. Freud’s inquiries circulate around this epistemological deadlock: because the echo is too material, it cannot be declared an idealist entity or a scientific fiction, but because its satisfaction seems to cause unpleasure, which is not the case with physiological needs, something violates the mechanisms of satisfaction. This scandal in the end exposes the minimal gap between the drive and organic needs: the drive is the symbolic isolation of their demand, the imperative for satisfaction that they contain. Detached from its repetitive organic context, the demand for satisfaction assumes a life of its own, and this is where the unpleasurable aspect of satisfaction enters the picture.

中Freud was most certainly hesitant regarding the ontological status of the drive. In his New Introductory Lectures, he famously wrote that the drive is comparable to a mythological being, and his drive-theory to ancient mythology. Certainly the drive is a hypothesis, which strives to account for the fact that the apparatus of the signifier, which conditions the split between consciousness and the unconscious, does not follow useful goals, the satisfaction of needs, but tends towards immediate pleasure-gain. The drive names the tendency that accounts for a series of material consequences of the signifier, without therefore appearing before the analyst’s eyes as a positive substance: ‘In our work we cannot for a moment disregard them, yet we are never sure that we are seeing them clearly.’ The drive assumes the same ontological and epistemological status as the energy does in physics. Its hypostasis is indispensible, but one can never confront it directly, only observe its consequences, first and foremost the production of pleasure-gain and the conversion of pleasure into unpleasure. The visibility of the drive’s satisfaction is comparable to the visibility of entropy, which can be observed only after science has placed the formal language of mathematics over the physical world. The manifestation of physiological needs additionally blurs the visibility of the drive, or better put, because all the bodily needs are channelled through the drive as their privileged representation, they no longer remain unproblematic. The drive is the paradigmatic case of the pun traduttore-traditore. It represents (translates) the apparently natural need in an unfaithfully productive way, thereby betraying its satisfaction.

中The translation first and foremost produces a change in the status of pleasure. There is no drive the satisfaction of which would not cause pleasure, although this pleasure is no longer an affect that accompanies the decrease of tension. We can return to Marx’s example of the two hungers from the Grundrisse. The pleasure that can be associated with the satisfaction of hunger is different from the pleasure that clings to the act of eating. The intertwining of the two imperatives, the need and the demand, in the satisfaction of a physiological need conceals the fact that the demand of the drive is constant, that it repeats the imperative of satisfaction beyond the need. It would be too simple to see in an insatiable hunger that swallows raw food a pre-symbolic natural instinct, which stands opposite to the cultural consumption of food. Bare instinctual life is an imaginary presentation of what takes place behind the apparent satisfaction of physiological needs, the persistence of the imperative beyond every attempt of satisfaction. This feature of the drive did not go unnoticed in Freud: ‘A drive ... never operates as a force giving a momentary impact but always as a constant one.’ The detachment of the imperative from a concrete reference, and consequently the autonomy of the demand, which depends on the autonomy of the signifier, places the drive in discrepancy with every supposedly natural or instinctual need. The demand of the oral drive, isolated in the need for nourishment, persists behind different and apparently unrelated activities such as eating, smoking, speaking, sucking and so on. Due to this persistence, the drives constant force can only be experienced as unpleasure, more precisely, as Lust, die nicht als solche empfunden werden kann, pleasure that cannot be felt as such. Pleasure that can only be experienced as unpleasure - with this formulation, Freud provides the best definition of what Lacan envisages with his notion of jouissance. In the need, displeasure precedes its satisfaction; in the drive, displeasure accompanies satisfaction and is the privileged form of pleasure. Satisfaction now takes place in the increase of tension, and this tension is due to the insatiable Drang, pressure, which is ‘common to all drives; it is in fact their very essence’. The drive as representation of physiological needs comes down to the imperative signifier, S1, the repressed signifier of jouissance.

中Here the second essential feature of the drive enters the picture, which clarifies that Marx’s opposition between bare hunger and cultivated hunger indeed highlights two immanent aspects of the drive and not the opposition between nature and culture. Under constant pressure, Freud understands the ‘amount of force or the measure of the demand for labour [Arbeitsanforderung] that it represents’. At the very core of the drive stands a permanent demand for labour, representation of labour-power, hence the Freudian attempt to elaborate an energetics of the drive. This demand for labour explains the simultaneous sameness and difference between pleasure and unpleasure in unconscious satisfaction. At this point, Freud’s early analogy with capitalism finds another repetition. Because the unconscious is split between the capitalist and the labourer, the process of satisfaction is necessarily experienced on both ends, pleasure and unpleasure. Yet the one enjoying is not the subject, for as Freud’s analyses demonstrate again and again, there is no subject of jouissance. There is only the subject of labour, the addressee of the demand for labour. There is no imperative of jouissance without the imperative of labour. Consequently, Labour! is true meaning of the superego’s injunction Enjoy! The critical kernel of Freud’s labour theory of the unconscious again becomes strilking, since Marx’s reformulation of the political-economic labour theory of value into a materialist theory of the subject was the first one to establish this interdependency of the two demands that can be associated with capital: the constant demand for surplus-value and the constant demand for labour.

中The difference between need and demand is finally reflected at the level of the object. Unlike need, the drive appears to be without an object:中The object of a drive is the thing in regard to which or through which the drive is able to achieve its aim. It is what is most variable about a drive and is not originally connected with it, but becomes assigned to it only in consequence of being peculiarly fitted to make satisfaction possible.中Lacan later draws attention to this passage in order to explain how the object a relates to the montage of the drive. However, we cannot overlook the fact that Freud -prior to Lacan’s developments -again hints at the difference between the content and the form, which already backed the mechanism of desire. The drive reaches its satisfaction in the object-form, which corresponds to the autonomy of differences, and based on this displacement the demand for satisfaction can become imperative. The drive becomes a symbolic machine without end, consuming objects for the sake of consumption(i. e. , extraction of surplus), and designating the permanent Entstellung, deformation and displacement of the need.

中Let us now turn to the paradoxes of repression. Freud writes that repression is not an originary defence mechanism but can only become operative once ‘a sharp cleavage has occurred between conscious and unconscious mental activity’. Repression already presupposes the unconscious, and its function does not consist so much in supressing, inhibiting or hindering satisfaction but in keeping the drive away from consciousness. The paradox of repression lies in the fact that repression is secondary, despite being constitutive of the repressed. It can only emerge after the scission of the mental apparatus between consciousness and the unconscious has been established, but it is also the necessary condition for this cleavage. The hypothesis of an originary repression is supposed to solve the paradox in the relation between the repression and the repressed:中We have reason to assume that there is an originary repression, a first phase of repression, which consists in the psychical (ideational) representative of the drive being denied entrance into the conscious. With this fixation is established; the representative in question persists unaltered from then onwards and the drive remains attached to it.中What is repressed is not some originary instinctual substance that the intervention of language would suppress but the signifier of the drive, a signifier that aims at jouissance and on which the translation of the supposedly physiological need into the symbolic demand depends. Freud again recurs to the more accessible language of the repressive hypothesis but in fact targets the autonomy of the signifier. The actual achievement of originary repression is the production of the master-signifier, which is synonymous to the autonomy of the system of differences, a signifier of the demand and jouissance. The originary repression thus confronts an impossible task to examine the repressed in statu nascendi, the genesis of the repressed, which is, in the last instance, the same as the genesis of language. The description of the structure of repression continues in the following way:中The second stage of repression, repression proper, affects mental derivatives of the repressed representative, or such trains of thought as, originating elsewhere, have come into associative connection with it. On account of this association, these ideas experience the same fate as what was originally repressed. Repression proper, therefore, is actually an after-pressure [Nachdrängen]. Moreover, it is a mistake to emphasise only the repulsion, which operates from the direction of the conscious upon what is to be repressed; quite as important is the attraction exercised by what was originally repressed upon everything with which it can establish a connection. Probably the trend towards repression would fail in its purpose if these two forces did not co-operate, if there were not something previously repressed ready to receive what is repelled by the conscious.中Constituted repression, the second stage of repression, is productive unconscious labour. All other forms of unconscious labour can be reduced to repression, which now appears as the satisfaction of the drive rather than its suppression or obstruction. Here another complication emerges. We are not simply dealing with two different repressions, of which one would be in the past and the other in the present. The historical reading overlooks the topological aspect of repression that is linked to its inherent doubling: in order to have repression, there have to be at least two. A singular repression could not constitute the relation that Freud very precisely describes in reference to attraction and repulsion. The inner moments of every concrete act of repression are originary repression(the constitution of the repressed)and the labour of repression (the satisfaction of the repressed tendency). This double structure can be compared with the chain of signifiers. The cut that produces the split between consciousness and the unconscious is redoubled, as the signifier of the repressed demand for surplus-jouissance (S1 - a) and as a difference that relates to another signifier (S1 - S2), initiating unconscious production and representing the ‘amount of demand for labour’, labour-power. Repression activity contains both axes of the signifier, representation and production. This internal doubling unveils the parallax that Freud explicitly underlines in the reminder that besides the repulsion from consciousness one should equally acknowledge the attraction that derives from the point of the originary repression, the master-signifier. From the point of view of consciousness, repression appears as a defence mechanism that represses in the sense of oppression. The repressive hypothesis absolutises this perspective, and we can find its most contemporary political exemplification in neoliberalism. Did the neoliberal ideology not turn around the idea that the market contains ‘creative potentials’, which need to be liberated through deregulation? The concept of the free market mobilises the repressive hypothesis, through which capitalism perverts and neutralises the political radicality of modern liberation movements. Only from the position of the subject, which is the position of Freud’s labour theory of the unconscious and Marx’s critique of fetishism, can repression appear as an operation that conditions the satisfaction of the drive through the double production of the surplus-object and of the alienated subject in a concrete form. The drive now no longer appears deprived of its immediate satisfaction, repulsion (rejection) turns into attraction(satisfaction), and unpleasure turns into a specific form of pleasure.

中This problematic is not unrelated to Marx, for in the double structure of repression, Freud encounters the same problem that concerns the accumulation of capital. When Marx turns towards the historical conditions of capitalism, he reformulates the question of primitive accumulation, which served classical political economy in its apology for capitalism. Marx unveils its fictional character but then also provides its rational reinterpretation in the context of the historical genesis of the capitalist logic, the transformation of the old spirit of the miser into the modern spirit of capitalism, which deepened the social relations of domination by rooting them in the very relations between things. The modern reification of the master, i. e. , its detachment from the old figure of divine sovereign, inevitably brought about the reification of the subject.

中The psychoanalytic value of Marx’s speculation on the origins of capitalism consists in him exposing the link between jouissance and ideology, and more concretely, the rootedness of economic liberalism in the fiction of the subject of enjoyment - a fiction, which remains entirely intact in today’s neoliberal condition. Of course, the significance of primitive accumulation is commonly known and has been discussed by several authors. Marx starts from the structural paradox in the relation between accumulation and production. Just as in the case of repression and the repressed, where repression constitutes the repressed that it simultaneously presupposes, the analysis of accumulation contains a vicious circle, in which production and accumulation support each other: there is no accumulation of capital without a preceding production of surplus, but there is no production of surplus without the preceding accumulation of capital either.

中Marx first draws attention to the fact that primitive accumulation, as used in political economy, contains a moral lesson, thereby assuming the role of original sin in theology. It thereby also assumes the function of myth, since it strives to address the unattainable historical origin of accumulation of capital - a point that can be grasped only by means of fictitious constructions and fantasies. The tale is grounded on the presupposition of jouissance on the side of the proto-proletarian and the equally presupposed renunciation on the side of the proto-capitalist:中Long ago there were two sorts of people; one, the diligent, intelligent and above all frugal elite; the other, lazy rascals [Lumpen], spending their substance, and more, in riotous living. . . Thus it came to pass that the former sort accumulated wealth, and the latter sort finally had nothing to sell except their own skins. And from this original sin dates the poverty of the great majority who, despite all their labour, have up to now nothing to sell but themselves, and the wealth of the few that increases constantly, although they have long ceased to work.中At the beginning there were the ascetic and the consumer: the subject of renunciation and the subject of enjoyment. The political-economic myth thus tries to explain the genesis of positive and negative surplus: surplus-value, originating from abstinence and embodied in the first accumulated wealth, and labour-power, originating from excess, for which the myth claims that it inevitably generates debt. Abstinence helps accumulating the surplus that will finally enable the minority to appropriate the means of production, while jouissance creates a negative that will eventually force the majority to sell their own bodies. For political economy this scenario sounds entirely rational: the capitalist forefathers accumulated the minimal wealth through personal sacrifice, so it seems just that their contemporary offspring continue to profit from it without restriction. At the same time, the proletarians are responsible for their own misery because their predecessors wasted more than they possessed, ihr alles und mehr. This apparently insignificant formulation is crucial because it envisages the interdependency of jouissance and debt, seemingly adopted from religion, hence Marx’s comparison of primitive accumulation with the fable of original sin.

中The political-economic myth significantly marked recent attempts to legitimise austerity measures, as others have already noticed. The global South was presented as the space of enjoying subjects that the absurd national debts meanwhile turned into an oasis of surplus population; while its counterpart, the global North, and notably Germany, appeared as the land of saving, a success story possible only under the condition that the economic growth is anchored in the constant renunciation of jouissance. Of course, everyone could witness that the actual situation was quite the opposite: imposed saving initiates a negative spiral that produces more debt than is possible to repay. This debt is not a moral obligation calling for repayment but actually has a productive function: the austerity measures are supposed to create economic devastation that will strengthen the link between citizens and the structural function of indebted subject. This recent development once again confirms the thesis that the primitive accumulation is not a process in the past but an inner moment of the present that reproduces the conditions of possibility for capitalist accumulation and expropriation. It designates the root of the discursive process that constitutes the individual as a subject of value, just as originary repression addresses the root of the autonomy of the signifier, through which the double production of the subject of the unconscious and of surplus-jouissance can be initiated. The scission between consciousness and the unconscious is the Freudian way of addressing this autonomy.

中According to the implicit prejudice of the political-economic tale, the labourer continues to enjoy(to laze around and become even more indebted), while the capitalist continues to save(to increase his wealth). Marx introduces a minimal correction to this scenario. The capitalist subject most certainly is in the first instance a subject of debt but never enjoyed as a subject. In other words, the capitalist figure of subjectivity did not emerge from the transformation of some hypothetical subject of jouissance into labour-power, as political economists suggest, but from a specific transformation of jouissance itself. The abstinence theory of the capitalist highlights this development:中Accumulate, accumulate! That is Moses and the prophets! ‘Industry furnishes the material which saving accumulates’. Therefore save, save, i.e., reconvert the greatest possible portion of surplus-value or surplus product into capital!Accumulation for the sake of accumulation, production for the sake of production: this was the formula in which classical economics expressed the historical mission of the bourgeoisie in the period of its domination ... If, in the eyes of classical economics, the proletarian is merely a machine for the production of surplus-value, the capitalist too is merely a machine for the transformation of this surplus-value into surplus capital.中Marx’s correction concerns the externalisation of the link between accumulation and saving that already existed in the premodern spirit of the miser. In the foundation of the system lies the imperative of abstinence, which is directly translatable in the imperative of indebting: the subject’s duty is to assume and to interiorise the debt created by the jouissance of the system - and precisely for this reason Marx remarks that the national debt is the only wealth that enters into possession of all modern nations, i.e., something that belongs to everyone and from which no one has the right to exempt him or herself. While merely a minority personifies systemic jouissance, labour-power becomes the sole universal subjective position in the capitalist universe. The political-economic tale of primitive accumulation contains a grain of distorted truth, showing that no jouissance precedes renunciation but that there is a strong correlation between the renunciation and the production of jouissance, both through generalised indebting.

中After criticising the political-economic myth of origin, Marx suggests his own rationalised variant of primitive accumulation. In the reconstruction, which assumes no less than the status of a historiographical fiction, the separation of producers from the means of production is accomplished through blood and fire, the constitutive violence that progressively transforms the feudal relations of domination and subjection into the capitalist ones. I am not going to go deeper into Marx’s reconstruction of the genesis of capitalism, the accuracy and the general validity of which remains a topic of discussion. What is more important is the logical background of Marx’s outline of the historical genesis of capitalism, which in many respects anticipates Freud’s topological account of repression. In Marx’s reading, the crucial part in the genesis is attributed to the invention of national debt. He places the emphasis on the transformation of premodern religious debt, still embedded in its mystifying metaphysical meaning, into modern debt, founded on public credit and turned into a quantified and meaningless abstraction. This shift is accomplished through the transformation of the logic that grounded the feudal social link, what Lacan called the master’s discourse:中The starting-point of the development that gave rise both to the wage-labourer and to the capitalist was the enslavement of the worker. The advance made consisted in a change in the form of this servitude, in the transformation of feudal exploitation into capitalist exploitation.中The formal change invents a new form of indebtedness that no longer has economic-metaphysical roots in submission to the feudal lord, the monarch or any other representative of divine power on earth, but instead in the economic inequality that is codified in the apparently unproblematic and concrete act of exchange. The truth of the capitalist worldview is universal indebtedness produced by emptied political categories such as freedom and equality. The invention and social implementation of national debt and public credit amounted to a new discursive production without abolishing the old structure of domination and inequality. It merely transformed the premodern serf into abstract labour-power, a machine to produce surplus-value, and in the same move introduced a new figure of the master, the capitalist, who personifies the machine to transform the surplus-product into capital. This transformation integrates the surplus-product into the social link, introducing a new form fetishisation of social relations, through the fetishisation of objects. In the same move, the feudal master is stripped of his fetish quality, which also means that the new capitalist master no longer depends on concrete personifications. Mastery becomes an abstraction embodied and operative in every object that enters the economic sphere: commodity, money and financial abstractions. If the king had two bodies, the mortal and the sublime, the capitalist has merely one but is therefore endowed, as Marx claims, with the soul of capital.

中In capitalism, the subject is indebted to neither the secular nor the divine master, but to the economic system itself. Consequently, capitalism is no realisation of the spirit of Protestantism, as Max Weber argued, but a cult of indebting, as Walter Benjamin specified in his famous critical note. If we want to maintain the link between capitalism and religious logic - this still makes sense because of the structural function of debt, which in both cases builds on the equivocity of morality and economy - we nevertheless have to take into account a certain regression in religion: from institutionalised religion of revelation to the no less institutionalised (through central banks, corporations, multinationals, political Troikas and so on) cult. Marx aims at this regression when he reduces the capitalist social link to commodity fetishism: from religion that understands itself as a religion of truth and that essentially is a ‘true religion’ (Lacan) into ‘neo-paganism’, an irrational secularised belief in the self-valorising power of capital.

中With the transformation of the master into an abstraction, the abstract debt no longer grounds the social link between the master and the serf but instead supports that between the citizen and the state:中The system of public credit, i.e., of national debts, the origins of which are to be found in Genoa and Venice as early as the middle ages, took possession of Europe as a whole ... The national debt, i.e., the externalisation [Veräusserung] of the state - whether that state is despotic, constitutional or republican - marked the capitalistic era with its stamp. The only part of the so-called national wealth that actually enters into the collective possession of a modern people is the national debt. Hence, as a necessary consequence, the modern doctrine that a nation becomes the richer the more deeply it is in debt. Public credit becomes the credo of capital. And with the rise of national debt-macing, lack of faith in the national debt takes the place of the sin against the Holy Ghost, for which there is no forgiveness.中With the genesis of the national debt, Marx’s analysis of primitive accumulation most definitely changes its character. While the description of the constitutive violence over the English rural population remained in imaginary historical coordinates and in the horizon of repressive hypothesis, just as Freud’s early accounts of repression, the focus on national debt turns towards the logical displacement in the social mode of production, which inevitably comprises the production of labour-power as a specifically capitalist form of subjectivity: the sole subject that corresponds to the regime of abstract debt and to the modern credit system.

中The invention of national debt and the corresponding production of subjectivity expose the kernel of the capitalist form of alienation that Marx indicates in the term ‘externalisation of the state’. The capitalist state simply is an institutionalised form of a more underlying, constitutive alienation, which determines the logical relation between economic ‘abstractions’, capital and labour-power. The externalisation of the state in the national debt is accompanied by its internalisation, in the sense that it shapes the nature of modern subjectivity. Being essentially grounded on indebting and standing for national debt as such, the modern state places every citizen in the position of the debtor, while the position of the creditor is assumed by the social institutions of capital: the central banks. At this point it becomes most evident that the emergence of the modern state is inevitably accompanied by the genesis of an extra-state power, which pertains to financial institutions and which is essentially authoritarian.

中The equivalent of the placement of the citizen in the position of the debtor is the transformation of the subject into a quantifiable and exploitable subjectivity, which is indebted in advance and is also produced as such. In this way Marx rejects the fantasmatic projection of some hypothetical subject of jouissance before the subject of abstract debt. His rationalisation of the political-economic myth shows that the capitalist demystification and quantification of the premodern religious debt creates a more efficient abstract universality -national debt -which leaves no subject outside its reach, thereby introducing a new Holy Spirit, that is, a social link grounded on the negative spiral of productive indebting, out of which rises the spectrality and apparent autonomy of capital.

中To repeat, what is at stake in Marx’s rationalised variant of primitive accumulation is the problem of constitutive alienation, on the level of which the production of capitalist subjectivity can be observed. Abstract debt and abstract labour thereby become two inseparable aspects of the subject. And because the structure of the capitalist mode of production is internally doubled, the critical appropriation and rationalisation of the notion of primitive accumulation indeed shows features that are strictly homologous to the Freudian notion of originary repression, where the production of constitutively alienated subjectivity is no less central. Even if Marx and Freud might have taken the notion of origin literally, they still drew attention to a structural and temporal paradox, which undermines the linear representation of history thanks to the notion of retroactive causality. Consequently, the prehistorical origin in question turns out to be more a prehistory within the present, retroactively projected onto the past and operating within the present condition as a constant refoundation of the capitalist relations of production. Behind the apparent quest for historical origin, Marx and Freud raise the logical and materialist question of the cause, which brought the indebted subject and the subject of the unconscious into being.

中The paradoxical relation between accumulation and production, which supports the structure and the efficiency of capitalism, might indeed make this mode of production a vicious circle, from which no escape seems to be possible. At the same time this paradox is also the reason of its structural disclosure and permanent instability, which announce the opposite appearance, the imminent breakdown of the system. The conceptual couple of the fetish and the symptom, shared by critique of political economy and psychoanalysis, addresses precisely these two opposite appearances of capitalism.

←→

[←76]
我们可以再次回想起《研讨班17》上的这个谜题。这一点可以与马克思对商品拜物主义的批判有关，在后者中，其逻辑机制的重建不只是废除了资本主义抽象物的拜物教，而且表明商品拜物教的有效性建立在思想与行动间的差异之上。马克思会说：“他们并不知道，尽管如此，他们还是这么做了。”阿尔弗雷德·索恩-雷塞尔通过这句话引入了实在抽象的概念，因此人们可以立即注意到它相当接近拉康的话语概念。见阿尔弗雷德·索恩-雷塞尔《商品形式与思维形式》，1978年,103-33.关于他的作品的精神分析背景,请参见斯拉沃热·齐泽克,《意识形态的崇高客体》,伦敦: Verso,1989,16-21.
We can again recall the riddle from Seminar XVII. The point can be related to Marx's critique of commodity fetishism, in which the reconstruction of its logical mechanisms does not simply abolish the fetishisation of capitalist abstractions but rather shows that the efficiency of commodity fetishism is grounded on a discrepancy between thinking and action. Marx will say: ‘They do not know it, nevertheless they do it’. Alfred Sohn-Rethel used this statement in order to introduce the notion of real abstraction, for which one can immediately notice that it comes rather close to Lacan's notion of discourse. See A. Sohn-Rethel, Warenform und Denkform, Frankfurt: Suhrkamp, 1978, 103-33. For the psychoanalytic contextualisation of his work, see S. Zitek, The Sublime Object of Ideology, London: Verso, 1989, 16-21.

←→

[←85]
斯大林的文本也没有简单地宣称语言为基础，因为这只会重新陷入语言与革命、语言转型和社会转型之间关系的困境。关于拉康教学中斯大林公理的详细情境，请参见让·克莱德-米尔纳，《克莱尔全集》，巴黎： Seuil出版社，1995年，85-8年。关于马克思主义的更广泛的讨论，请参见勒内·勒·赫米特《科学与意识形态：马尔，马尔主义，马尔主义者》，巴黎：奴隶练习曲学院，1987年。拉康在政治上仍然是现实的：被能指的逻辑独立出的基本结构性关系与他后来所说的大学话语（统治结构）是一样的。因此，政治包含对统治关系的持久斗争以及统治和解放的倾向间的结构性张力。
Stalin's text also refrained from declaring language simply a base, since this would merely repeat the dilemma regarding the relation between language and revolution, linguistic transformation and social transformation. For a detailed contextualisation of Stalin's axiom in Lacan's teaching, see J. C, Milner, L’oeuvre claire, Paris: Seuil, 1995, 85-8. For a broader discussion of Marrism, see R. LHermitte, Réne, Marr, marrisme, marristes. Science et perversion idéologique, Paris: Institutd’Etudes Slaves, 1987. Lacan remained politically realistic: the basic structural relations isolated by the logic of the signifier are the same as what he later calls the master's discourse, the structure of domination. Consequently, politics would contain a permanent struggle against relations of domination and a structural tension between the tendencies of domination and liberation.

←→

[←128]
马克思在《资本论》的另一个关键摘录中提到了这种实质性的丧失：“如果我们无视商品的使用价值，就只剩下一种属性，那就是作为劳动产物的存在。”但即使是劳动产物也已经在我们手中转变了。如果我们从它的使用价值中进行抽象，我们就同时抽象化了使它成为使用价值的物质成分和形式……伴随着劳动产物的有用特性的消失的，是体现于其中的劳动种类的有用特性的一并消失；这随之导致了不同具体劳动形式的消失。它们不能再被区分了，而是全被简化为同一种劳动，即抽象的人类劳动”（马克思，《资本论》，第1卷，第128页）。
Marx thematises this material reduction in another crucial excerpt of Capital: ‘If then we disregard the use-value of commodities, only one property remains, that of being products of labour. But even the product of labour has already been transformed in our hands. If we make abstraction from its use-value, we abstract also from the material constituents and forms which make it a use-value. . . With the disappearance of the useful character of the products of labour, the useful character of the kinds of labour embodied in them also disappears; this in turn entails the disappearance of the different concrete forms of labour. They can no longer be distinguished, but are all together reduced to the same kind of labour, human labour in the abstract’ (Marx, Capital, Vol. 1, 128).

←→

[←145]
让我们回忆一下拉康在巴黎弗洛伊德学派解散是的著名调解：“大他者消失了。我也觉得这很滑稽。不过我能接受这个打击，尽管这让你们觉得刺激，但是我这么做并不是为了这个”（拉康，《电视》，134)。大他者不存在既是学派的条件（因为只有大他者不存在才能让学派或政党免于成为教会）也是首要的风险（因为大他者的不存总是伴随着一种阻抗，它推动学派或政党的成员回到机构化的转变上，即成为教会）。在组织的平面之上，核心的斗争发生于机构化转变（将组织重新和虚拟的大他者相关联）和主体的政治动员性（由于大他者消失了，动员性才成为可能）之间。
Let us recall Lacan’s famous intervention during the dissolution of the Ecole freudienne de Paris: ‘The Other is missing. It seems funny to me too. I can take the blow though, which gives you a thrill of sorts, but I’m not doing it for that’ (Lacan,Television, 134). The inexistence of the Other is both the condition and the ultimate risk of the School - the condition because only the inexistence of the Other can prevent the School or the Party from turning into a Church; the risk because this inexistence is always accompanied by the resistance that pushes the members of the School or of the Party back into the institutional transference, hence into the Church. On the terrain of organisation, the central struggle takes place between the institutional transference that links the organisation back to the hypothesis of the Other, and the political mobilisation of the subject, which is possible precisely because the Other is missing.

←→

[←168]
因为资本主义话语的效率是基于这种特定的转换的：从封建主义奴隶主到资本主义，从奴隶到无产阶级，拉康后来声称，资本主义逐步揭示了奴隶主的本质，即他不知道他想要什么。在资本家的形象中，主人被简化为需要生产性劳动的基本命令：“例如，在主人的话语中，实际上不可能有一个主人让整个世界发挥作用。如果真的要去做的话，让人们去工作比自己工作更累。主人从不这样做。他给了一个手势，主人能指，每个人都跳了起来。这就是你必须开始的地方，这实际上是完全不可能的。它每天都是有形的”（拉康，《精神分析的另一面》，174页）。
Because the efficiency of the capitalist discourse is based on this specific transformation of the feudal master into the capitalist and the serf into the proletarian, Lacan will later claim that capitalism progressively reveals the very essence of the master, namely that he does not know what he wants. In the figure of the capitalist, the master is reduced to the bare imperative that requires productive labour: ‘In the master’s discourse, for instance, it is effectively impossible that there be a master who makes the entire world function. Getting people to work is even more tiring, if one really has to do it, than working oneself. The master never does it. He gives a sign, the master signifier, and everybody jumps. That’s where you have to start, which is, in effect, completely impossible. It’s tangible every day’ (Lacan, The Other Side of Psychoanalysis, 174).

←→

[←204]

The talk about ‘instincts is not without risks, since the very idea of an instinct is built on shaky ground. Lacan briefly addresses this issue in Television when he talks of the instinct as a potentially inadequate concept: "There is no unconscious except for the speaking being. The others, who possess being only through being named -even though they impose themselves from within the real -have instinct, namely the knowledge needed for their survival. Yet this is so only for our thought, which might be inadequate here’(Lacan, Television, 5). Animals do not have drives; they only have instincts, which could be considered a knowledge in the real, the function of which is to guarantee animals their survival. Lacan’s reservation towards this hypothesis is justified: knowledge in the real is, in the end, an ungrounded and unscientific hypothesis. But this does not annul the initial claim: because the drive is conditioned by the autonomy of the signifier, it can be attributed to humans but not to animals. Animals have a language of signs but one cannot claim(yet)that they have the signifier, the autonomy of which, to repeat again, consists in the fact that it relates to another signifier. The conclusion is thus that one does not need to refer to the instinct in order to theorise the drive, and Freuds Trieblehre did precisely this: it detached the drive from its biological and physiological context.